<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Inscription in honour of the praet. prefect Maternus Cynegius from Alexandria by Theodosius and Arcadius</title>
                <editor role="edition">Andrea Bernier</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Irene Vagionakis</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="plre" corresp="pp. 235-236">75</idno>
                <date when="2020-05-08"/>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person><persName ref="#Cynegius"><name type="gentilicium">Maternus</name> <name type="cognomen">Cynegius</name></persName></person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#unknown">unknown</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#honorary">Honorary inscription for the praetorian prefect Cynegius</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#unknown">unknown</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>unknown</height>
                                        <width>unknown</width>
                                        <depth>unknown</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One inscribed field (frons).</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#undamaged">Undamaged.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#unknown">unknown (no images available)</term>
                                <height>unknown</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Alexandria</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Al Iskandariyah (Egypt)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Aegyptus</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Aegyptus</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">public space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p8" notBefore="0384" notAfter="0387">384/387 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found">found in 1746 in <placeName ref="#">Alexandria</placeName> (find spot unknown)</provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"></provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="la">
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/>Domini nostri, Invictissimi et Venerabiles
                        <lb n="2"/>ac perpetui Augusti, Theodosius et
                        <lb n="3"/>Arcadius, toto orbe Victores,
                        <lb n="4"/>Materno Cynegio, omnium virtutum viro et ad
                        <lb n="5"/>insignem laudem gloriamque progenito, per
                        <lb n="6"/>omnes honorum gradus meritorum con<lb 
                            break="no" n="7"/>templatione provecto, praefecto
                        <lb n="8"/>praetorio per Orientem, statuam
                        <lb n="9"/>civili habitu, ad petitum primorum <sic>nobilissim<supplied reason="omitted">a</supplied>e</sic>
                        <lb n="10"/>Alexandrinae urbis, in eadem splendida
                        <lb n="11"/>urbe, ad perpetuitatis famam, loco cele<lb 
                            break="no" n="12"/>berrimo constitui collocarique iusserunt,
                        <lb n="13"/>per clariss<g ref="palma"/>imos Al<g ref="palma"/>exandrinae civitatis.
                    </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>Edition based on CIL 03, 06587.</p>
                <p><app loc="9"><note>nobilium: CIL 03, 00019.</note></app></p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“Our masters, Undefeated and Venerable and forever Augusti, Theodosius and Arcadius, Victors of the entire world, to Maternus Cynegius, man with all the virtues and born for remarkable praise and glory, who went through all the honorable grades in the consideration of his merits, praetorian prefect of Oriens, at the petition of the first-ranking (men) of the most noble city of Alexandria, in order to perpetuate his fame, ordered that a statue in civil dress be set up and placed in the most renowned place in that splendid city by the men of clarissimus rank of Alexandria.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>“Nos seigneurs, très Invincibles et Vénérables et perpétuels Augustes, Théodose et Arcadius, Vainqueurs du monde entier, ont ordonné que à Maternus Cynegius, un homme doué de toutes les vertus et né pour une louange illustre et la gloire, promu par tous les grades des honneurs en considération de ses mérites, préfet du prétoire de l’Orient, à la demande des plus importants (hommes) de la très noble ville d'Alexandrie, pour perpétuer sa renommée, une statue en tenue civile soit réalisée et placée dans le lieu le plus renommé de cette ville splendide par les clarissimes citoyens d’Alexandrie.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“I nostri signori, Invittissimi e Venerabili e perpetui Augusti, Teodosio e Arcadio, Vincitori del mondo intero, hanno ordinato che a Maternus Cynegius, uomo dotato di tutte le virtù e nato per illustre lode e gloria, promosso attraverso tutti i gradi degli onori in considerazione dei suoi meriti, prefetto del pretorio d’Oriente, su richiesta dei più importanti (uomini) della nobilissima città di Alessandria, per perpetrare la sua fama, fosse realizzata una statua in abito civile e fosse collocata nel luogo più rinomato in quella splendida città dai chiarissimi della cittadinanza di Alessandria.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>The inscription was found in Alexandria in 1746 and published in the <title>Corpus Inscriptionum Latinarum</title> more than a century later (CIL 03, 00019; 06587; cf. ILS 1273). At that time the inscription was probably lost, but was published thanks to the transcription by Claude-Louis Fourmont (nephew of Michel Fourmont, to whom the manuscript “Supplément Grec 301” of the Bibliothèque nationale de France is attributed in the catalogue; the inscription at f. 130/111; cf. CIL 03, p. XXVI). No information survives about the dimensions of the inscription and its present location (see <ref type="inscription" corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail-base.php?record=LSA-872">LSA 0872</ref>).</p>
                <p>The text records the dedication in Alexandria of a statue to the praetorian prefect of the East Maternus Cynegius. The prefect was portrayed in civilian clothing (<foreign>civili habitu</foreign>, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret24">PPRET 24</ref> for a similar statue in Berytus for Domitius Leontius) and his statue was probably in bronze since the inscription registers the permission granted by the emperors Theodosius and Arcadius (metal statues, and at least from 398 AD also statues in marble, could only be put up in public places with imperial permission: <ref type="source">CI 01, 24, 01</ref>; see Feissel 1984, pp. 545-558; for metal statues with imperial permission see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret24">PPRET 24</ref>; <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret54">54</ref>; <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret58">58</ref>). The honour accorded to Cynegius came after a petition of the <foreign>primores</foreign> of the city and the statue was set up by the <foreign>clarissimi</foreign> of Alexandria. The term <foreign>primores</foreign> may refer to the curial class of the city or only to the most eminent members of it, called <foreign>primates</foreign> in a law of Theodosius II in 436 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 190</ref>; numbering five in Alexandria, they formed «an inner ring within the city council»: Jones 1964, p. 731; cf. Laniado 2002, pp. 208-211; Cecconi 2006, pp. 41-43), while the indication of the <foreign>clarissimi Alexandrinae civitatis</foreign> has been considered a reference to the group of men of senatorial rank resident in Alexandria (U. Gehn in <ref type="inscription" corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail-base.php?record=LSA-872">LSA 0872</ref>). They must have constituted a distinct group. Indeed, in the Theodosian Code they are the only senators from a single city to whom an imperial constitution was addressed (Mommsen 1905, pp. CLXII-CLXV; on this constitution, <ref type="source">CTh 10, 10, 19</ref>, see below).</p>
                <p>The text shows many similarities with another inscription for an honorary statue, the one set up in Berytus for the praetorian prefect Domitius Leontius in 344 AD (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret24">PPRET 24</ref>). Here we find the same references to imperial permission, to civilian garb, to the connection between the merits of the men being honoured and the advancements in their careers, even to the steps of the administrative hierarchy. Although we know nothing of the posts occupied by Domitius Leontius prior to his attaining praetorian prefecture, more evidence survives for Maternus Cynegius (PLRE I, Cynegius 3, pp. 235-236; cf. Chastagnol 1965 = 1994, p. 40; Petit 1994, pp. 73-74; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 97-110). Probably a Spaniard who followed Theodosius I to the East, Cynegius soon emerged as a prominent member of the new court at Constantinople (Marique 1963, pp. 43-59; Matthews 1967, pp. 438-446). Attested as count of the sacred largesses in March 383 AD (Delmaire 1989, pp. 96-98), he was promoted after few months to the office of <foreign>quaestor sacri palatii</foreign>, a position that he held until the end of 383 AD (the succession between these two posts was not uncommon, see Harries 1988, p. 157; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 98-99). According to Honoré, the appointment of Cynegius to the quaestorship resulted in a clear change of style in the Theodosian legislation (now «grandiloquent, sonorous, repetitive») something that can be ascribed to the new office holder himself (Honoré 1998, pp. 48-52; Honoré 1986, pp. 151-154, 200; cf. Escribano Paño 2013, pp. 3-5; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 99-100).</p>
                <p>At the very beginning of 384 AD, Cynegius was promoted to the praetorian prefecture of the East (Laniado 2018, pp. 419-422). His tenure lasted until his death in March 388 AD and throughout the central years of Theodosius’ I reign, his activities made a deep impression. The ancient sources focus mainly on two issues that he appears to have made a priority: the restoring of the city councils and the repression of pagan cults and heresies in the eastern provinces (cf. <ref type="source">Lib., Or. 30</ref>, with Petit 1951, and <ref type="source">Lib., Or. 49</ref>; <ref type="source">Chron. Min. 01, p. 244</ref> = <ref type="source">Cons. Const. s.a. 388</ref>; <ref type="source">Zos. 04, 37, 03</ref>; see Matthews 1975, pp. 140-142; Fowden 1978, pp. 62-67; Gassowska 1982, pp. 107-123; but cf. the revisionist view of McLynn 2005, pp. 108-120; see also Jones 2013, pp. 860-865). The relevance of these topics is confirmed by the impressive <foreign>dossier</foreign> of imperial legislation that was addressed to Cynegius throughout his prefecture, much of which has been preserved in the Theodosian and Justinian Codes (more than sixty fragments, a score unmatched by any other official: see the list in PLRE I, pp. 235-236; on the contents cf. Errington 2006, pp. 233-237; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 100-103; Escribano Paño 2013, pp. 5-7; now, Rendina 2020, pp. 20-22). In 388 AD Cynegius reached the peak of his career with his designation to the consulate as colleague of the emperor (CLRE, pp. 310-311). About to move westwards for the final confrontation with Magnus Maximus, Theodosius decided to grant this supreme mark of imperial favour to his praetorian prefect, who was left in control of the eastern part of the empire. However, only a few weeks after his appointment, Cynegius died. Initially, his body was placed in the Church of the Apostles in Constantinople (connections between the families of Theodosius and Cynegius are suggested by Matthews 1967, pp. 444-445), only to be conveyed to Spain a year later by his widow Achantia (<ref type="source">Chron. Min. 01, p. 244</ref> = <ref type="source">Cons. Const. s.a. 388</ref>: on Cynegius’ entry in the consular list and his unusually «lengthy and tendentious eulogy», see Burgess 1993, pp. 197-198; cf. CLRE, p. 55; this is the main evidence for the prefect’s Spanish provenance, contested by García Moreno 2002, pp. 179-186; but cf. McLynn 2005, pp. 96-97 and pp. 117-119 on the possibility that the <foreign>villa</foreign> discovered at Carranque was the final destination of Cynegius).</p>
                <p>The honorary statue of Cynegius was set up in Alexandria during his praetorian prefecture, that is to say after early 384 AD (in December 383 AD his predecessor Postumianus was still in office, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret74">PPRET 74</ref>, while the first constitutions addressed to Cynegius, <ref type="source">CTh 12, 13, 05</ref> and <ref type="source">CTh 15, 01, 23</ref>, were issued on January 18th, 384 AD). Conversely, the missing reference to the consulate suggests a chronology earlier than 388 AD.</p>
                <p>We know from Zosimus and Libanius that Cynegius visited Alexandria at the very beginning of his praetorian prefecture. Zosimus (<ref type="source">Zos. 04, 37, 02</ref>) says that the prefect was sent to Egypt in order to clamp down on pagan cults and while in Alexandria, he displayed the portrait of Magnus Maximus as a new member of the imperial college; however, according to Libanius (<ref type="source">Lib., Or. 49, 03</ref>), the initial purpose of Cynegius’ journey was the restoring of the city councils (on the chronology of this visit to Alexandria, around January 384 AD, see Vera 1975, pp. 277-282; cf. PLRE I, p. 231; different proposals in Petit 1951, pp. 298-301; Matthews 1974, pp. 100-101; cf. also Olszaniec 2013, pp. 102-107). As for our inscription and the honorary statue, it would appear that they were put up to celebrate the re-establishment of the councils. In 387 AD the emperor Theodosius received a delegation of senators from Alexandria, who had come to denounce the activity of informers (<foreign>delatores</foreign>) within the city. Then, in a constitution issued on March 2nd (<ref type="source">CTh 10, 10, 19</ref>), Theodosius communicated to the senators that he had sent letters to the prefect Cynegius instructing him to investigate the allegations, adding that the same official had already addressed the problem of criminal delation earlier. This probably happened in 384 AD during the prefect's visit to Alexandria. His work on the reorganisation of the city council may also have involved patrimonial matters, with first dispositions being made against the informers. Three years later, the problem of the <foreign>delatores</foreign> resurfaced and the Alexandrian senators were urging the prefect to deal with it. Whether this required Cynegius to make another journey to Alexandria is unclear (see now McLynn 2005, pp. 115-116); what is clear is Cynegius’ participation in the affairs of the city in 384 AD and in 387 AD. His statue must have been set up after one of these two episodes. Given that the Alexandrian senators had requested his intervention for a second time and that they had put up a statue in his honour (l. 13: <foreign>per clarissimos Alexandrinae civitatis</foreign>), 387 AD seems the most likely date. This solution is supported by the imperial permission granted by Theodosius and Arcadius. In it, the reference to the eastern emperors alone, instead of the whole imperial college, as was usual in these honorary inscriptions (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret24">PPRET 24</ref>; cf. also <ref type="inscription">CIL 08, 07013</ref> = <ref type="inscription">ILS 1236</ref> = <ref type="inscription" corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail-base.php?record=LSA-2327">LSA 2327</ref>; <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 01736</ref> (cf. p. 4747) = <ref type="inscription">ILS 1256</ref> = <ref type="inscription" corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail-base.php?record=LSA-1439">LSA 1439</ref> = <ref type="inscription" corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?id_nr=EDR130289">EDR 130289</ref>;  <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 01698</ref> (cf. p. 4737) = <ref type="inscription">ILS 1257</ref> = <ref type="inscription" corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail-base.php?record=LSA-342">LSA 0342</ref> = <ref type="inscription" corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?id_nr=EDR123515">EDR 123515</ref> and Feissel 1984, pp. 549-550), would appear to indicate a later date. Considering the growing tension among the co-rulers this date makes more sense than 384 AD when an agreement between the usurper and the eastern court had been reached and when, according to the passage of Zosimus mentioned above, the prefect Cynegius displayed a portrait of Magnus Maximus as a new member of the imperial college in Alexandria itself.</p>
                <p>A last remark on the titulature of Cynegius: the inscription exceptionally records the regional competence of the prefect (<foreign>per Orientem</foreign>). This indication does not occurs in any of the other 4th Century inscriptions that refer to praetorian prefects of the East and have been found within the boundaries of the eastern prefecture (only Olybrius is styled <foreign>praefectus praetorio Orientis</foreign> but on a statue base that was displayed in Rome, probably in the house of the prefect: <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret70">PPRET 70</ref>). The indication of the regional competence on our document might be related to the last period of the clash with Magnus Maximus, when Theodosius I extended his authority first over the Illyrian prefecture and, after the defeat of the usurper, also over the prefecture of Italy. The need to distinguish between praetorian prefects serving in different prefectures may have prompted the chancellery of Theodosius to add this specification, that occurs also in some laws preserved in the Theodosian Code that were issued in the same period (<ref type="source">CTh 08, 04, 17</ref> adressed to Cynegius <foreign>p.p.o per Orientem</foreign> in late 387-early 388 AD, with Porena 2020, pp. 146-147 for the chronology; cf. <ref type="source">CTh 15, 01, 26</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 11, 16, 19</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 05, 11, 12</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 15, 01, 28</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 01, 01, 02</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 03, 01, 06</ref>).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>CIL 03, 00019</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>CIL 03, 06587</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>ILS 1273</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Delmaire 1989, pp. 97-98</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://db.edcs.eu/epigr/edcs_id.php?p_edcs_id=EDCS-21200079">EDCS 21200079</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail.php?record=872">LSA 872</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/text/106277">TM 106277</ref></bibl>
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Burgess R.W. (ed. and transl. by), The Chronicle of Hydatius and the Consularia Constantinopolitana. Two Contemporary Accounts of the Final Years of the Roman Empire, Oxford 1993</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cecconi G.A., Honorati, possessores, curiales: competenze istituzionali e gerarchie di rango nella città tardoantica, in Lizzi Testa R. (a cura di), Le trasformazioni delle élites in età tardoantica, Roma 2006, 41-64</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chastagnol A., Les espagnols dans l’aristocratie gouvernementale à l’époque de Théodose, in Les empereurs romains d’Espagne, Paris 1965, 269-292 (= Id., Aspects de l’antiquité tardive, Roma 1994, 11-42)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Delmaire R., Les responsables des finances impériales au Bas-Empire romain (IVe-VIe s.): études prosopographiques, Bruxelles 1989</bibl>
                    <bibl>Errington R.M., Roman Imperial Policy from Julian to Theodosius, Chapel Hill 2006</bibl>
                    <bibl>Escribano Paño M.V., The Power of Maternus Cynegius in the Theodosian Court, in García-Gasco R., González Sánchez S., Hernández de la Fuente D. (eds.), The Theodosian Age (A.D. 379-455). Power, Place, Belief and Learning at the End of the Western Empire, Oxford 2013, 1-7</bibl>
                    <bibl>Feissel D., Notes d'épigraphie chrétienne VII, BCH, 108, 1984, 545-579</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fowden G., Bishops and Temples in the Eastern Roman Empire A.D. 320-450, JThS, 29, 1978, 53-78</bibl>
                    <bibl>García Moreno L.A., Materno Cinegio ¿un noble hispano o un burócrata oriental?, in Carrié J.M., Lizzi R. (éd.), Humana sapit. Études d’Antiquité Tardive offertes à Lellia Cracco Ruggini, Turnhout 2003, 179-186</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gassowska B., Maternus Cynegius, Praefectus Praetorio Orientis and the destruction of the Allat temple in Palmyra, Archeologia, 33, 1982, 107-123</bibl>
                    <bibl>Haas C., Alexandria in Late Antiquity. Topography and Social Conflict, Baltimore-London 1997</bibl>
                    <bibl>Harries J., The Roman Imperial Quaestor from Constantine to Theodosius II, JRS, 78, 1988, 148-172</bibl>
                    <bibl>Honoré T., The Making of the Theodosian Code, ZRG, 103, 1986, 133-222</bibl>
                    <bibl>Honoré T., Law in the Crisis of Empire, 379-455. The Theodosian Dynasty and its Quaestors, Oxford 1998</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jones A.H.M., The Later Roman Empire, 284-602. A Social, Economic and Administrative Survey, 3 vols., Oxford 1964</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jones C.P., Three Temples in Libanius and the Theodosian Code, CQ, 63, 2013, 860-865</bibl>
                    <bibl>Laniado A., Recherches sur les notables municipaux dans l'Empire Protobyzantin, Paris 2002</bibl>
                    <bibl>Laniado A., L’aristocratie sénatoriale de Constantinople et la préfecture du prétoire d’Orient, in Morrisson C., Sodini J.-P. (éd.), Constantinople réelle et imaginaire. Autour de l’oeuvre de Gilbert Dagron, Paris 2018, 409-454</bibl>
                    <bibl>Marique J.M., A Spanish Favourite of Theodosius the Great: Cynegius praefectus praetorio, Classical Folia, 17, 1963, 43–59</bibl>
                    <bibl>Matthews J., A Pious Supporter of Theodosius I: Maternus Cynegius and his Family, JThS, 18, 1967, 438-446</bibl>
                    <bibl>Matthews J., Review of Later Roman Prosopography, CR, 24, 1974, 97-106</bibl>
                    <bibl>Matthews J., Western Aristocracies and Imperial Court, A.D. 364-425, Oxford 1975</bibl>
                    <bibl>McLynn N., “Genere Hispanus”: Theodosius, Spain and Nicene Orthodoxy, in Bowes K., Kulikowski M. (ed. and transl. by), Hispania in Late Antiquity. Current Perspectives, Leiden-Boston 2005, 77-120</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mommsen Th., Theodosiani libri XVI cum constitutionibus Sirmondianis. Voluminis I pars prior. Prolegomena, Berlin 1905</bibl>
                    <bibl>Olszaniec S., Prosopographical Studies on the Court Elite in the Roman Empire (4th Century AD), Toruń 2013</bibl>
                    <bibl>Petit P., Sur la date du «Pro Templis» de Libanius, Byzantion, 21, 1951, 285-310</bibl>
                    <bibl>Petit P., Les fonctionnaires dans l’œuvre de Libanius. Analyse prosopographique, Paris 1994</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Ipotesi sull’istituzione di una prefettura del pretorio autonoma d’Illirico nel decennio 378-87, in Bigi F., Tantillo I. (a cura di), Senatori romani nel Pretorio di Gortina. Le statue di Asclepiodotus e la politica di Graziano dopo Adrianopoli, Roma 2020, 143-166</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rendina S., La prefettura di Antemio e l'Oriente romano, Pisa 2020</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vera D., I rapporti tra Magno Massimo, Teodosio e Valentiniano II nel 383-384, Athenaeum, 53, 1975, 267-301</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="2">
                    <p n="2.a"></p>
                    <p n="2.1"></p>
                    <p n="2.7">statuam civili habitu</p>
                    <p n="2.9">omnium virtutum viro et ad insignem laudem gloriamque progenito, per omnes honorum gradus meritorum contemplatione provecto</p>
                    <p n="2.10">omnium virtutum viro et ad insignem laudem gloriamque progenito, per omnes honorum gradus meritorum contemplatione provecto</p>
                    <list n="2.11">
                        <item n="2.11.g"></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.2">praefecto praetorio per Orientem</p>
                    <p n="8.5"></p>
                    <p n="8.9"></p>
                    <p n="8.12"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
