<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Greek inscription in honour of Flavius Eutolmius Tatianus praet. prefect from Sidyma</title>
                <editor role="edition">Giordana Franceschini</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Giordana Franceschini</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="plre" corresp="pp. 876-878">87</idno>
                <date when="2021-05-14"/>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name type="praenomen">Flavius</name>
                            <name type="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name>
                            <name type="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#Sidyma">findspot</repository>
                        <idno type="invNo"></idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#burial">Funerary inscription for the praetorian prefect Flavius Eutolmius Tatianus</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#poetry">poetry (uncertain: irregular hexametric rhythm; sotadei according to Merkelbach 1978; rhythmic prose according to Feissel 2011-2012)</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="grc">Greek</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#marble">marble</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#block">two blocks or pillars</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>unknown</height>
                                        <width>unknown</width>
                                        <depth>unknown</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>The text is inscribed on one field for each of the two (square) blocks («auf zwei grossen viereckigen Altären», according to Benndorf who examined them in 1882).</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#fragmentary">The first block looks intact and contains 14 lines; the second block contains 12 lines, but is missing perhaps two lines at the beginning. The written lines on the right end of the two blocks are partially fragmentary. The number of letters in each single line is very different.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#unknown">unknown (no images available)</term>
                                <height>unknown</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Sidyma</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Dudurga Asari (Turkey)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Lycia</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Asiana</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#private">Private space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p8" notBefore="0391" notAfter="0400">391/400 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found">The inscription, chiselled on two large quadrangular marble blocks or altars, was found in <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> near the access to an <foreign>aedicula</foreign> in a garden not far from “the Street of tombs”.</provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"></provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="grc">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="part">
                    <head>(first block)</head>
                <ab> 
 <lb n="1-2"/>1-2 <note>Verse 1 ?</note> <supplied reason="lost">Τ</supplied>ατιανός μετὰ δικανικήν | <supplied reason="lost">τρισὶν</supplied> ἄρχουσιν συνκαθεσθείς | 
<lb n="3-4"/>3-4 <note>Verse 2 ?</note> ἡγεμόνι βικαρίῳ ἀνθυπά<supplied reason="lost">τῳ</supplied> | δυσίν τ’ ἐπάρχοις | 
<lb n="5-6"/>5-6 <note>Verse 3 ?</note> ἀρχήν Θηβαίων λάχεν, ἔ<supplied reason="lost">πειτ’</supplied> | Αἰγύπτου πάσης, | 
<lb n="7-8"/>7-8 <note>Verse 4 ?</note> κεῖθεν ὑπατικὸς Συρίης ἠδ’ ὅ<supplied reason="lost">λης</supplied> | ἄρχος ἐῴας | 
<lb n="9-10"/>9-10 <note>Verse 5 ?</note> θησαυρῶν τε θείων κόμ<supplied reason="lost">ης</supplied> | εἶτ’ ἔπαρχος μέγας φάνη·| 
<lb n="11-12"/>11-12 <note>Verse 6 ?</note> ταῦτα δ’ ἔτι πράττων ἔτ<supplied reason="lost">εσι</supplied> | τριάκοντα καὶ τρισίν | 
<lb n="13-14"/>13-14 <note>Verse 7 ?</note> δέξατ’ ἀείδιον ὑπάτων <supplied reason="lost">στέφανον</supplied> | εἵνεκα πάντων. 
                </ab>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="part">
                    <head>(second block)</head>
                <ab>
<lb/>? [<gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="line"/> | <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="line"/>]
<lb n="15-16"/>15-16 <note>Verse 8 ?</note> <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>ν ἀφ’ ἑαυτοῦ γνω̣<gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/> | <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>λου σπουδῇ τίνο<supplied reason="lost">ς</supplied>; |
<lb n="17-18"/>17-18 <note>Verse 9 ?</note> <supplied reason="lost">οἱ</supplied> θεῖοι βασιλεῖς τοῖς ἔρ<supplied reason="lost">γοισιν αὐτοῦ</supplied> | χαίροντες | 
<lb n="19-20"/>19-20 <note>Verse 10 ?</note> εἵνεκ’ ἀμοιβῆς ὑπατίᾳ στέ<supplied reason="lost">ψαντ’</supplied> | ἀφθάρτῳ | 
<lb n="21-22"/>21-22 <note>Verse 11 ?</note> ὡς ἂν αὐτῷ κῦδος καὶ τι<supplied reason="lost">μήν μεγά</supplied>|λην ὀπάσοιεν | 
<lb n="23-24"/>23-24 <note>Verse 12 ?</note> πάντας ἐπ’ ἀνθρώπους ἅμα τ’ α<supplied reason="lost">ὐτίκα</supplied> | καὶ μετέπειτα | 
<lb n="25-26"/>25-26 <note>Verse 13 ?</note> οὕνεκ’ ἀπειρεσίους πόνους <supplied reason="lost">αἷσιν</supplied> | ἤνυσεν ἀρχαῖς. 
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>This edition follows the text edited by Merkelbach, Stauber 2002 (SGO 04), nr. 17/08/03, with emendations by Feissel 2011-2012, p. 80.
<app loc="1"><note><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>ανὸς CIG; <supplied reason="lost">Τατι</supplied>ανός Kaibel; δικανικὴ<supplied reason="lost">ν τοῖς</supplied> CIG; Kaibel; Benndorf-Niemann; Cougny; ILS; TAM; Delmaire; Livrea; Olszaniec</note></app>
                    <app loc="2"><note><supplied reason="lost">τρισὶν</supplied> Feissel 2011-2012</note></app>
                    <app loc="3"><note>ἀνθυπάτω Grégoire</note></app>
                    <app loc="4"><note>τε ἐπάρχοις Kaibel; Cougny; Livrea</note></app>
                    <app loc="5"><note>ε<supplied reason="lost">ἶτ</supplied>: Benndorf-Niemann; Kaibel; Cougny; ILS; TAM; Grégoire; Delmaire; Livrea; Olszaniec; λάχεν <supplied reason="lost">ἦδ</supplied>: CIG</note></app>
                    <app loc="7/8"><note><supplied reason="lost">καὶ ἔπ</supplied>|αρχος ἐῴας CIG; ἡδ’ <supplied reason="lost">ἔπ</supplied>|αρχος ἐῴας Kaibel; Cougny; Grégoire; Livrea; ἡδ’ὅ <supplied reason="lost">ἔπ</supplied>|αρχος ἐῴας Delmaire; Olszaniec; ἡδ’ ὅ<supplied reason="lost">πλ</supplied>|αρχος ἑώας TAM; ILS; Mekelbach; ἡδ’ὁ | αρχος ἑώας Benndorf-Niemann; ὅ<supplied reason="lost">λης</supplied> | ἄρχος ἑῴας Feissel 2011-2012</note></app>
                    <app loc="10"><note>φαν<supplied reason="lost">είς</supplied> CIG; Cougny; Livrea; φανί<supplied reason="lost">ς</supplied> Kaibel </note></app>
                    <app loc="11"><note>ταῦτα δέ τε π<supplied reason="lost">ρ</supplied>άττων CIG </note></app>
                    <app loc="13"><note>ἀειδίων ὑπάτων <supplied reason="lost">λάχος</supplied> CIG; ἀείδιον ὑπάτων <supplied reason="lost">λάχος</supplied> Kaibel; Benndorf-Niemann; Cougny; ILS; TAM; Grégoire; Delmaire; Livrea; Olszaniec; <supplied reason="lost">στέφανον</supplied> Merkelbach</note></app>
                    <app loc="15/16"><note>[- - - τὴ]ν ἀφ’ ἑαυτοῦ γν<supplied reason="lost">ώμεν</supplied> | ΛΟΥϚΠΟΥΛΗΠΝΟ CIG;  <supplied reason="lost">ὡς παλι</supplied>ν ἀψ’ ἑαυτοῦ γν<supplied reason="lost">ωσθῇ μεγ</supplied>|άλου σπουδή τινο<supplied reason="lost">ς ἄθλου</supplied> Benndorf-Niemann; Grégoire; Delmaire; Olszaniec; <supplied reason="lost">ὡς αὐτὸ</supplied>ν ἀφ’ ἑαυτοῦ γν<supplied reason="lost">ωστὸν με|γ</supplied>ά̣λου σπουδῇ τινο<supplied reason="lost">ς</supplied> TAM; Kaibel, Cougny, Livrea omit both the lines </note></app>
                    <app loc="17"><note><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/> οἱ βασιλεῖς τοῖς ἔ<supplied reason="lost">ργοισιν</supplied> CIG; <supplied reason="lost">οἱ θ</supplied>εῖοι βασιλεῖς τοῖς ἔ<supplied reason="lost">ργοισιν</supplied> Kaibel; Cougny; TAM; οἱ θεῖοι βασιλεῖς τοῖς ἔρ<supplied reason="lost">γοισιν</supplied> Benndorf-Niemann; Grégoire; Delmaire; Livrea; Olszaniec</note></app>
                    <app loc="19"><note>ὑπατίας τ<supplied reason="lost">ίμησαν</supplied> CIG; ὑπατίας τί<supplied reason="lost">μησαν</supplied> Cougny; ὑπατίας τε<supplied reason="lost">ίμησαν</supplied> Kaibel; Livrea; ὑπατία στέ<supplied reason="lost">ψαντο</supplied> Benndorf-Niemann; TAM; Grégoire; Delmaire; Olszaniec</note></app>
                    <app loc="20"><note>ἀφθάρτω<supplied reason="lost">ς</supplied> CIG; Kaibel; Cougny; Livrea </note></app>
                    <app loc="21/22"><note>αὐ<supplied reason="lost">τ</supplied>ῷ CIG; Kaibel; Livrea; τ<supplied reason="lost">ερπω</supplied>|λὴν CIG; τι<supplied reason="lost">μ</supplied>|ὴν Kaibel; Livrea; τιμὴν Cougny</note></app>
                    <app loc="23"><note>τ<supplied reason="lost">οὺς τότε</supplied> CIG; Kaibel; Cougny; Livrea </note></app>
                    <app loc="25/26"><note><supplied reason="lost">δη</supplied>|νυσεν CIG; <supplied reason="lost">ἐξή</supplied>|νυσεν Kaibel; Cougny; Livrea; <supplied reason="lost">ἐξ</supplied>|ήνυσεν Benndorf-Niemann; TAM; Grégoire; Delmaire; Olszaniec 
</note></app>
                    </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Tatianus, dopo l’attività forense, fu assistente di tre dignitari: di un governatore, di un vicario, di un proconsole e di due prefetti; ottenne il potere sui Tebani, poi su tutto l’Egitto, quindi rifulse consolare di Siria, e responsabile di tutto l’Oriente, indi conte dei tesori imperiali, infine grandioso prefetto: e mentre ancora militava nell’amministrazione nel trentatreesimo anno per tutti questi motivi ricevette la corona dei consoli che dona l’eternità. [...] Per volere di chi giunse così in alto ? Gli imperatori di stirpe divina, compiaciuti dal suo agire, in contraccambio lo coronarono con il consolato che dona l’immortalità, così che congiunsero in lui la gloria con un onore grande davanti a tutti gli uomini, nell’immediato e per sempre, perché egli sopportò innumerevoli fatiche durante i suoi incarichi.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“Tatianus, after his legal activity, was assistant to three dignitaries: to a governor, a vicar, a proconsul and two prefects; he obtained power over the population of Thebes, then over all Egypt, he shone as consularis of Syria and was responsible for the whole of the East, (before becoming) count of the imperial treasures, and finally great prefect: and while still in administration in the thirty-third year, for all these reasons, he received the crown of consuls that bestows eternity. [...] At the behest of those who reached so high ? The emperors of divine lineage, pleased by his actions, in return crowned him with the consulate that gave him immortality, so that they united in him the glory with a great honour before all men, immediately and forever, because he endured innumerable labours during his duties.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>“Tatianus, après son oeuvre d’avocat, fut assistant de trois fonctionnaires: d’un gouverneur, d’un vicaire, d’un proconsul et de deux préfets; il obtint le pouvoir sur les Thébains, puis sur toute l’Egypte, puis brilla consulaire de Syrie, et responsable pour l’Orient entier, puis comte des trésors impériaux, et enfin grand préfet : et alors qu’il était encore en administration la trente-troisième année pour toutes ces raisons reçut la couronne de consuls qui donne l’éternité. [...] Par la volonté de qui est-il arrivé si haut ? Les empereurs de la lignée divine, satisfaits de ses actions, le couronnèrent en retour du consulat qui lui donna l’immortalité, afin qu’ils unissent en lui la gloire avec un grand honneur devant tous les hommes, immédiatement et pour toujours, car il a enduré d’innombrables fatigues pendant ses fonctions.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>The monument and its date</p>
                <p>The inscription was chiselled on two large quadrangular blocks and was set up in honour of the praetorian prefect <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="praenomen">Flavius</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (synthesis in PLRE I, pp. 876-878, see below) in the ancient city of <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> (<placeName>Lycia</placeName>), today known as <placeName>Dudurga Asari</placeName> or <placeName>Yukari Dodurga</placeName> (<placeName>Turkey</placeName>). Unfortunately, the exact dimensions of the two stone blocks are unknown. <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> was in all probability the home of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>. There is no doubt that the praetorian prefect was a native of <placeName>Lycia</placeName>, as attested by various contemporary sources (<ref type="source">Lib., Or. 56, 16</ref>; <ref type="source">Athan., Ep. Fest. index 39, p. 271 Martin-Albert</ref> [year 367 AD]; <ref type="source">Lib., Or. 56, 16</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 09, 38, 09</ref>; <ref type="source">Eun., Fr. 57 Blockley</ref> = <ref type="source">Eun., Fr. 59 Müller</ref>; <ref type="source">Zos. 04, 45, 01</ref>) and by three inscriptions (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret89">PPRET 89</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret90">90</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret91">91</ref>). However, some sources on his eponymous nephew (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret91">PPRET 91</ref>) have him residing in <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> in the first half of the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century (<ref type="source">Theoph., Chron., A.M. 5943, p. 104 De Boor</ref>; <ref type="source">Cedr., I, p. 603 Bekker</ref>; <ref type="source">Nic. Call., HE 15, 01, PG 147</ref>; <ref type="source">Zon. 13, 24, III, p. 245 Dindorf</ref>). It seems likely that at least one branch of the family came from this town and had properties in its territory.</p> 
<p>The characteristics of the double support on the front of a building, unfortunately gone, must be compared with the characteristics of the inscription. <persName ref="Tatianus">Tatianus</persName>’ inscription from <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> shows four peculiarities:</p> <p>
1) it is engraved on two distinct blocks and not on a single base as one would expect for a traditional and standard honorary inscription bearing the <foreign>cursus honorum</foreign> of the praised senator.</p> 
<p>2) the name of the prefect and consul <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> is perfectly intact in the nominative case; between 392 and 393 AD <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was tried and sentenced to exile by <persName ref="ruler">Theodosius I</persName>, but at <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> his name was not erased, unlike elsewhere (it is erased in: <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret82">PPRET 82</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret83">83</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret84">84</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret85">85</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret86">86</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret88">88</ref>; the only exception is the memory of hydraulic works in <placeName>Canopus</placeName> in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret90">PPRET 90</ref>; about the trial, see the critical commentary in <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret91">PPRET 91</ref>).</p>
                <p>3) The name (or names) of the dedicator was never inserted, since such an indication was clearly never intended: the first block is intact at the top and bottom edge; the second block is intact at the bottom edge, but not at the top one: in any case, it is impossible for the name of the dedicator to appear at the beginning of the second block.</p>
                <p>4) the second half of the inscription, ll. 13-26, celebrates the ordinary consulship of 391 AD granted by the Augusti (see CLRE, pp. 316-317).</p> 

<p>Scholars consider the <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> inscription to be an honorary dedication, and yet the site of the find, together with the traces on the facade of the building in which the two blocks were inserted, suggests a funerary monument.</p> 
<p>The space between the two blocks on which the inscription was chiselled marked the access to an <foreign>aedicula</foreign> in the middle of a valley, in a garden not far from the “the street of the Tombs” (Benndorf-Neuman 1884, p. 81: «Die Inschrift steht auf zwei grossen viereckigen Altären, die sich ziemlich in der Mitte der Thalebene in einem Garten unweit der Gräberstrasse befinden. Der eine steht allem Anscheine nach noch in situ und scheint mit dem andern eninige Schritte von ihm liegenden den Zugang eines kleinen Gebäudes oder Bezirkes flankirt zu haben». Kalinka in TAM 02, 186-187: «Media in convalle prope sepulcra in horto duae magnae arae quadratae marmoreae quae duos fere passus inter se distant instar postium portae»; Grégoire 1922, p. 100: «Sur deux grands autels quadrangulaires, qui se trouvent à peu près au milieu de la plaine dans un jardin non loin de la “voie des tombeaux”. Ils bordaient sans doute l’accès d’un édicule»). It seems possible that the two blocks inscribed in honour of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> that flank the <foreign>aedicula</foreign> near the “Street of the tombs” are the remains of the tomb or cenotaph of the praetorian prefect and consul. It is unlikely that the two blocks are fragments of funerary altars, or supports for a large sarcophagus, which was a common form of burial in <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> (Dardaine, Longepierre 1985; Schweyer 2002, pp. 11-34; for <placeName>Asia Minor</placeName> cf. Cormack 2004, pp. 18-22, 29-61, examples from <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> pp. 302-306). The distribution of the letters of the inscription along more than 26 narrow lines (no more than 25 letters per line, but the average is lower, cf. facsimile by Benndorf, Niemann 1884, p. 81) shows a vertical pattern, which is suggestive of the left and right pillars of the entrance door of a sepulchral building (on this type of tomb, cf. Dardaine, Longepierre 1985, p. 228; cf. Grabkammer in Benndorf-Niemann 1884, p. 79) or the entrance of a peribolos, surrounding a tomb or cenotaph. The “Street of the tombs” may originally have been outside the urban perimeter, before being swallowed up when the city expanded. At <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> the boundaries between the residential area and the necropolis are not clearly discernible to archaeologists. In the cities of <placeName>Lycia</placeName> and all of <placeName>Asia Minor</placeName> (western <placeName>Anatolia</placeName>), the situation was further complicated by the introduction of hybrid intra-urban burials, a custom that was popular throughout Hellenistic times and the Roman imperial age, particularly with civic aristocrats, benefactors, eminent citizens and their family members (cf. Berns 2013 with bibliography). On the topography of <placeName>Sidyma</placeName>, cf. Dardaine, Frézouls 1985; Hellenkemper, Hild 2004, II, pp. 845-847.</p> 
<p>Furthermore, in Greek epigraphy the name of the owner or recipient of the inscription in the nominative case is more common for sepulchral inscriptions than for honorary ones (cf. Guarducci 1987, pp. 155-156, 386-389; McLean 2002, pp. 236-244, 260-268; on the nominative case in honorary inscriptions, cf. Mednikarova 2003; Ma 2013, pp. 17-21). The silence of the authorities responsible for the monument would perhaps be justified had it been erected in a public space or building, in which case <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ name would almost certainly have been erased after his condemnation between 392 and 393 AD (below). The exaltation of the ordinary consulship would suggest that our dedication was made in the year 391 AD, a point upon which many scholars agree. Such a chronology would also fit with the conspiracy of <persName><name ref="gentilicium">Flavius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Rufinus</name></persName> (PLRE I, pp. 778-781) who plotted the downfall of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> and his son in the spring of 392 AD. However, if such an ostentatious double monument had been erected in 391 AD, it is hard to imagine how it could have remained so intact in 392 AD. One could cautiously conjecture that after 392/393 AD, the local civic authorities would not have had the courage to destroy it since the monument was protected by a powerful family. But there is another possibility. In 396 AD, after the assassination of <persName><name ref="gentilicium">Flavius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Rufinus</name></persName>, the memory of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was at least partly rehabilitated. In that year the emperor <persName type="ruler">Arcadius</persName> sent a constitution to <persName>Caesarius</persName>, the praetorian prefect of the East, in which he rehabilitated the reputation of the Lycians, which had been tainted by the disgrace of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (<ref type="source">CTh 09, 38, 09</ref>, on August 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 396 AD): “Emperors <persName type="ruler">Arcadius</persName> and <persName type="ruler">Honorius</persName> Augustuses to <persName>Caesarius</persName>, Praetorian Prefect. We decree that the former reputation and merit of the Province of <placeName>Lycia</placeName>, most devoted to Us, shall be restored among the other provinces and that Your Excellent Eminence shall make that fact known to all persons by posting edicts, in order that no person hereafter shall dare to injure a citizen of <placeName>Lycia</placeName> by an abusive name of insult. They shall hold the honours which they have received by their merits and labours and those which they shall obtain from Our Serenity. They shall have their former dignities, and they shall hope for others to come because of their devotion. For the temporary anger of a most disgraceful and hostile judge (= <persName><name ref="gentilicium">Fl.</name> <name ref="cognomen">Rufinus</name></persName>, killed on November 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 395 AD) against one man of Illustrious rank, <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, should not be of such weight that the disgrace should still remain for the Lycians, when in the case of the man himself the disgrace has already been extinguished by the absolution of time” (Pharr 1952, p. 254). It is also possible that the inscribed monument in <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> is in fact a reconstruction, carried out post 396 AD, after the first (391 AD) had been destroyed (392 AD). The consulate of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> in 391 AD was and remained a legitimate consulate since it had not been awarded by a usurper. The glory of the eponymy must have remained at the height of the Lycian senator’s career and memory.</p>
<p>Another solution to this problem is to simply consider the monument part of a funerary inscription. This would explain why the name of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> is in the nominative case and why there is no mention of a dedicator. The blocks close to the <foreign>aedicula</foreign> could be the individual tomb (or cenotaph) of the senator, that would have stood inside the families private property, near the “Street of the tombs”. The presumed location of the monument on the edge of the city supports the hypothesis that the blocks decorated the entrance to the senator’s sepulchrum. The two stone blocks could have supported two statues of the dignitary, one as praetorian prefect and one as ordinary consul, but it seems more probable that they could be a pair of pilars surmounted by an architrave, common in Lycian necropolis (for example an architrave with a horizontal inscription like the σωματοθήκη or τὸ μνημεῖον Εὐτολμίου Τατιανοῦ τοῦ λαμπροτάτου, or τοῦτο τὸ μνῆμα κατεσκεύασεν Εὐτόλμιος Τατιανὸς ὁ λαμπρότατος). The blocks would thus have been walled into the facade of the tomb on either side of the entrance door. If the inscription was indeed chiselled on a tomb – or possibly on a cenotaph – <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ name may well have escaped erasure by virtue of the fact that the monument was part a private inconspicuous building, under the protection of the senator’s relatives in his homeland. We do not know when <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> died (concerning his death cf. <ref type="source">Asterius, Hom. 04, 09, 01, p. 43 Datema</ref> [= PG 40, 224C-225A]). The constitution of <persName type="ruler">Arcadius</persName> of August 396 (<ref type="source">CTh 09, 38, 09</ref>, above) does not explicitly state that the senator was already dead. We can usually find in the imperial constitutions some periphrases that indicate the death of the dignitary at the time the imperial text was written (cf. <ref type="source">CTh 10, 20, 18</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 11, 01, 01</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 13, 05, 14</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 16, 05, 55</ref>). Our constitution does not use this type of formula. The <foreign>terminus post quem</foreign> for the preparation of the inscription of <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> is the year of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ consulate (391 AD). If the inscription is the epitaph of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, it might have been engraved after 396 AD, when the senator still seems to have been alive (<ref type="source">CTh 09, 38, 09</ref>, above). In this case, the failure to erase <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ name after 396 AD is perfectly understandable, particularly on a sepulchral (private) building on the outskirts of the city.</p>
<p>The insistence on the ordinary consulate for more than half a composition might have been an attempt to cover up the condemnation of the memory of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> whose deeds were annulled by <persName type="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> (<ref type="source">CTh 09, 42, 12</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 09, 42, 13</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 11, 01, 23</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 131</ref>). The association of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ name with the year 391 AD would remain as evidence of his glorious career. Despite being condemned, the senator would eventually be rehabilitated about 55 years later and his achievements commemorated in a public space in <placeName ref="Aphrodisias">Aphrodisias</placeName> (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret91">PPRET 91</ref>).</p>
                <p>The eulogy for the praetorian prefect <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> is not unique. For a bilingual epitaph in Greek and Latin hexameters of the praetorian prefect <persName>Maiorinus</persName> from <placeName>Buşr al-Hariri</placeName> (<placeName>Syria</placeName>), see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret26">PPRET 26</ref>. For a metric epitaph of the praetorian prefect <persName><name ref="gentilicium">Petronius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Probus</name></persName> with his career from <placeName>Rome</placeName>, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret64">PPRET 64</ref>; for an inscribed sepulchral altar in honour of the praetorian prefect <persName><name ref="praenomen">Vettius</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Agorius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Praetextatus</name></persName> with his career from <placeName>Rome</placeName>, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>. Praise for a prefect’s hard work as an administrator can be found in the inscriptions honouring <persName ref="Philippus">Philippus</persName> (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret28">PPRET 28</ref> and <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret31">31</ref>), <persName>Eugenius</persName> (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret48">PPRET 48</ref>), and both <persName ref="Flavianus1"><name ref="gentilicium">Nicomachus</name> <name ref="cognomen">Flavianus</name> senior</persName> and <persName ref="Flavianus2">junior</persName> (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret93">PPRET 93</ref>).</p>
                <p>Commentary on the text</p>
                <p>Regarding the Greek text of the <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> inscription, some specific remarks can be made. In lines 2-4 we accept the proposal of Feissel (2011-2012, p. 80) to integrate the numeral τρισίν (l. 2) in reference to the ἀρχαί, because it underlines the difference in rank with the numeral two (δυσίν l. 4) referring to the two prefectures which are higher in level. There is no contradiction in this climax: <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> has cooperated with three governors (<foreign>praeses</foreign>, <foreign>vicarius</foreign>, <foreign>proconsul</foreign>), then with two <foreign>praefecti</foreign> (maybe <foreign>Constantinopolis</foreign> and <foreign>Orientis</foreign>). In lines 7-8, we accept Feissel’s proposal (2011-2012, p. 80) to integrate ὅ<supplied reason="lost">λης</supplied> ἄρχος ἑῴας which is consistent with the development of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ assignments in the East (below). For the translation into Greek of <foreign>comes sacrarum largitionum</foreign> (l. 9), see Delmaire 1989b, pp. 18-21. In line 10 the formula ἔπαρχος μέγας for <foreign>praefectus praetorio</foreign> is first attested here (cf. ACO 02/01, 02, p. 23, year 451 AD; later Pouilloux, Roesch, Marcillet-Jaubert 1987, nr. 238); it is rare and the adjective μεγα- will be widespread in the title ὁ μεγαλοπρεπέστατος (καὶ ἐνδοξότατος ἔπαρχος τῶν ἱερῶν πραιτωρίων); in this inscription it is linked to the τιμήν μεγάλην in lines 21-22. In line 13 we uphold Merkelbach’s proposal (1978, p. 174) to integrate <supplied reason="lost">στέφανον</supplied> and not λάχος as previously proposed by scholars (since Schönbrun in CIG 4266e, in 1853): the (hypothesised) noun στέφανον of the first block is linked to the verb στέ<supplied reason="lost">ψαντ’</supplied> of the second block, and the nexus στέφω and στέφανον is usual in Greek. In line 17 θεῖοι βασιλεῖς could be a clue in favour of dating the inscription to the period post August 396 AD: the emperors who received apotheosis were very probably those who had granted <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> the consulship in the last months of 390 (cf. <ref type="source">Lib., Ep. 990</ref>), that is to say, <persName type="ruler">Valentinianus II</persName>, who died in May 392 AD, and <persName type="ruler">Theodosius I</persName>, who died in January 395 (for the evocation of the emperor’s favour towards his praetorian prefect, see the imperial documents in <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret28">PPRET 28</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret31">31</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret93">93</ref>). In lines 11ff., in particular 19-20, the ordinary consulship is exalted as the highest office, since it bestows eternity through eponymy: in the late empire, the ordinary consulship represented the pinnacle of a career within the service of the <foreign>res publica</foreign> (cf. CLRE, pp. 1-12, in part. pp. 7-8; Cecconi 2007; Sguaitamatti 2012; Petrini 2015). During the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century, the ordinary consulship was awarded to serving praetorian prefects 32 times  (that is to say from 285 to 395 AD; to this list we can also add two prefect-consuls appointed by usurpers). In the inscriptions of praetorian prefects in this period, the consulate is often extolled (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret10">PPRET 10</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret20">20</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret24">24</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret25">25</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret32">32</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret45">45</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret54">54</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret59">59</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret60">60</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret70">70</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret92">92</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret96">96</ref>, maybe <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret62">62</ref>; as ex-consule <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret58">PPRET 58</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret61">61</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret73">73</ref>; the consulate can also be held by the prefect’s relatives <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret63">PPRET 63</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret64">64</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret65">65</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret66">66</ref>), sometimes quite simply as in the case of designated consuls, who were never eponymous (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret20">PPRET 20</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret48">48</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">77</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret79">79</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret80">80</ref>). In lines 21-24, the author of the <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> inscription seems to exalt the union of the glory of the consulship (κῦδος) with the praetorian prefecture’s power, with the phrase “great honour” (τιμήν μεγάλην, cf. in line 10, the formula ἔπαρχος μέγας and the expression μεγάλην ἐξουσίαν of <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret44">PPRET 44</ref>). In line 25, an explanation accompanies this double honour: <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> endured the great labours (πόνους) of long prefectorial service and also obtained the consulship, bestowing visibility upon him for centuries to come (for the heavy burdens of the appointment, cf. Latin labor in <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret27">PPRET 27</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret28">28</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret31">31</ref>, likewise in <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret93">PPRET 93</ref>, ll. 21-24 and 31-32).</p>
                <p>Metrics</p>
                <p>If the metric of the verse was meant to be dactylic, it is incorrect. Since the 1853 edition by Franz (CIG 03, p. 146: «versus pessimi haud dubie») scholars have recomposed the lines of the inscription according to the dactylic rhythm, but the metric is always incorrect (so Kalinka in TAM 02, 186-187: «metrum ut enuclearem non mihi contigit»; Grégoire 1922, p. 100: «L’auteur [...] a cru faire des hexametres»). Merkelbach (1978) assumed that the verses are sotadei (no longer convinced in Merkelbach, Stauber 2002, p. 35). According to Livrea (1997, p. 44, nt. 7), the hypothesis that the the inscription was located in <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ family burial crypt does not hold true, since such a wealthy and cultured family would have never allowed a family member to be celebrated by such a bad poet. Recently Feissel (2011-2012, p. 80) suggested that the text is not metric, but rhythmic or poetic prose. We agree.</p>
                <p>Cursus honorum</p>
                <p>The inscription from <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> is the only one to retain the complete <foreign>cursus honorum</foreign> of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (on <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ career cf. Seeck 1906, pp. 285-288; Ensslin 1932, coll. 2463-2467; PLRE I, pp. 876-878; Delmaire 1989a, pp. 62-67; Petit 1994, pp. 240-243; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 394-407). In lines 11-14, the text of the inscription states that his career began thirty-three years before the ordinary consulate of 391 AD, that is to say in 358 AD. <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> had a solid legal and rhetorical education (classical and pagan) and came from the curial elite of <placeName>Lycia</placeName> (on <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ family, cf. Scharf 1991; Mratschek 2012; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 402-406; concerning the eastern civic elite, cf. Cabouret 2020, in part. pp. 67-93, 285-305, and for the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century, cf. Laniado 2002). His career began at the bottom and between 364 and 380 AD, due to meritorious service and the esteem of the Emperor <persName type="ruler">Valens</persName>, he benefitted from an exceptional number of promotions (Lenski 2002, pp. 62-63; Errington 2002, p. 74; Mratscheck 2012, pp. 261-266): <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was an ambitious man, an expert administrator and a skilled writer. <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ career in the East might best be summarised by citing and commenting on the <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> inscription itself.</p>
                <p>Line 1. <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was initially a lawyer in the administrative courts, an activity that did not place him at a level of high nobility. Since lawyers were not enrolled in the public administration (<foreign>militia</foreign>), it is possible that he was defending cases in the administrative courts before 358 AD, i.e. before the thirty-three years indicated in the inscription.</p>
                <p>Lines 2-4. <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was then an assistant and legal adviser to two provincial governors, a diocesan vicar and two prefects. Since the first assignment as governor (in <placeName>Thebais</placeName>) must have started in 364 AD (below), the five posts as aviser and adjutant to dignitaries must date to between 358 and 363 AD. The late Roman officers are listed in increasing order of importance according to the <foreign>ordo dignitatum</foreign>: <foreign>praeses</foreign>, <foreign>vicarius</foreign>, <foreign>proconsul</foreign>. Next come the two prefects, perhaps the prefect of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> and the praetorian prefect of the East. It is possible that the first one is <persName><name ref="gentilicium">Domitius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Modestus</name></persName>, skilled in law and prefect of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> in 362-363 AD (PLRE I, pp. 605-608; <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret67">PPRET 67</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret68">68</ref>), since Infantius, <persName><name ref="cognomen">Modestus</name></persName>’ son, was an understudy of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (<ref type="source">Lib., Ep. 987</ref>; Petit 1994, p. 242). It is possible that the second one could be Hermogenes (PLRE I, p. 423), Helpidius (PLRE I, p. 414) or <persName><name ref="cognomen">Secundus</name> <name ref="cognomen">Salutius</name></persName> (PLRE I, pp. 814-817; <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret50">PPRET 50</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret51">51</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret52">52</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret53">53</ref>), praetorian prefects of the East between 358 and 365 AD.</p>
                <p>Line 5. <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was <foreign>praeses <placeName>Thebaidis</placeName></foreign> in 364/366 AD. The last attestation of the governor preceding him, <persName><name ref="praenomen">Cerealis</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Telephius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Hierocles</name></persName> (PLRE I, p. 432; Agostini 2019, pp. 366-367), dates to April 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 363 AD (P. Lond. 05, 1651), while the first attestation of the governor following him, <persName><name>Flavius</name> <name>Heraclius</name></persName> (PLRE I, p. 419; Agostini 2019, pp. 367-369), is dated to February 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 368 AD (P. Oslo 03, 128). <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> ἡγεμὼν Θηβαΐδος had a number of Greek inscriptions engraved on the Tomb of <persName type="ruler">Ramses VI</persName>, in the King’s Valley, near <placeName>Thebes</placeName> (none of this evidence is datable; Baillet 1923, nr. 1380; 1118; 1512, cf. also nr. 1693, 1826, 1520, 1844, 1680; Bernand 1969, pp. 547-548, nr. 150. This short poem in iambic trimeter composed by <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> himself confirms his qualities as a poet and is joined by the evidence concerning his highly regarded Homeric-style poem on the fall of Ilion, cf. <ref type="source">Lib., Ep. 909</ref> with Pellizzari 2017, pp. 110-111).</p>
                <p>Line 6. <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was then <foreign>praefectus Aegypti</foreign> in 367-370 AD (cf. <ref type="source">CTh 12, 18, 01</ref>, on May 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 367 AD; P. Oxy. 63, 4376 on March 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 368 AD; P. Oxy. 63, 4377, on March 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-April 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 369 AD; P. Oxy. 17, 2110, on October 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 370 AD; P. Oxy. 08, 1101, 367/370 AD). Contemporary sources with or shortly after his term of office always refer to him as <foreign>praefectus <placeName>Aegypti</placeName></foreign> (ἔπαρχος τῆς Αἰγύπτου, see CTh, papyri and also Hist. Acephal. 12, p. 166 Martin-Albert; <ref type="source">Athan., Ep. Fest. 39-45, pp. 271-277 Martin-Albert</ref>; <ref type="source">Phot., Bibl. 08, 39 [Cod. 258, p. 484 Bekker]</ref>; on these documents and <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ titulature cf. Olszaniec 2013, pp. 395-397; Agostini 2019, pp. 270-277, with Appendices). The inscription of <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> indicates him as being “responsible for the whole of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>” (ἀρχήν ... λάχεν ... Αἰγύπτου πάσης), and the inscription of <placeName>Canopos</placeName> (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret90">PPRET 90</ref>, ll. 2-3) despite a <foreign>lacuna</foreign>, probably indicates him as <supplied reason="lost">ἀπὸ ἐπάρχων τῆς</supplied> Αἰγυπτιακῆς διοι<supplied reason="lost">κήσεως</supplied>. The two inscriptions of <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> and <placeName>Canopos</placeName> were written when <placeName>Egypt</placeName> (the whole <placeName ref="Aegyptus">Aegyptus</placeName>) was a diocese that was detached and distinct from the Eastern Diocese (<foreign><placeName ref="Oriens">Oriens</placeName></foreign>) and had its own diocesan governor, the <foreign>praefectus Augustalis</foreign> (since 380/382 AD). On the basis of the report of the anonymous Barbarus Scaligeri (the 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century <foreign>Excerpta Latina Barbari</foreign> – a Latin translation of a Greek 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century world chronicle – for the year 368 [<ref type="source">MGH AA 09, Chron. Min. 01, p. 295</ref>] states: <foreign>eo anno introvit <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> in <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> primus Augustalius VI kal. Februarias</foreign>), some scholars have assumed that <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> may have already been <foreign>praefectus Augustalis</foreign> of the diocese (hence the PLRE I, p. 876; list of scholars in Olszaniec 2013, p. 395 nt 2049). But the sources show that the creation of the autonomous diocese of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and of the first <foreign>praefectus Augustalis</foreign> date back to the years 380/382 AD (on the problem, see Vandersleyen 1962, pp. 19, nr. 41, 146-147; Lallemand 1964, pp. 55-56, 63, 247-248, 251; De Salvo 1979; Delmaire 1989a, pp. 64-64; Carrié 1998, pp. 108-109; Palme 1998, pp. 128-133; Errington 2002; Mratscheck 2012, pp. 262-264; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 396-397; see also <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret90">PPRET 90</ref>). The reform of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> by <persName type="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> which may have commenced in 380 AD, was intended to increase administrative efficiency at the time of the serious crisis following the defeat at <placeName>Hadrianopolis</placeName> (378 AD). It seems likely that the sources written after this reform (cf. already <ref type="source">Pallad., Hist. Laus. 46, 03</ref>) gave <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> an anachronistic title, because he had affectively ruled as prefect of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> (not <foreign>Augustalis</foreign>) an enlarged province of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, with an enhanced mandate during the Gothic campaign of <persName type="ruler">Valens</persName> in the years 367-370 AD (on these anachronisms, see Mratscheck 2012, pp. 263-264; on <persName type="ruler">Valens</persName>’ First Gothic War cf. Lenski 2002, pp. 127-152). The papyri found at Oxyrhynchus (above), concerning <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> prefect of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, reveal that the Heptanomia was in that period (367-370 AD) part of the province of <placeName ref="Aegyptus">Aegyptus</placeName>. The studies of B. Palme (1998) show how, from 374 to 381 AD, the province of <placeName ref="Aegyptus">Aegyptus</placeName> was expanded at the expense of the province of <placeName>Augustamnica</placeName>, containing the <placeName>Heptanomia</placeName>. The papyri concerning <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (above) bring forward Palme’s “2nd Phase” territorial enlargement of the province of <placeName ref="Aegyptus">Aegyptus</placeName> to 367 AD (similar conclusions by Errington 2002, pp. 72-73; Mratscheck 2012, p. 263). So it seems very likely that between 367 and 370 AD, <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was prefect of a province of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> that extended as far as the borders of <placeName>Lybia</placeName>, <placeName>Thebais</placeName> and <placeName>Augustamnica</placeName>; the latter was confined to the region East of the Nile Delta. Seventy years or so after <persName ref="ruler">Diocletian</persName>’s division of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> into more provinces, the reintegration of the territories on both sides of the Nile into the single province of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> was meant to appear as a restoration of “all of Egypt” (Αἰγύπτου πάσης).</p>
                <p>Lines 7-8. After the termination of his prefecture in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and at some point before his appointment to the imperial treasury, <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was made <foreign>consularis Syriae</foreign> and <foreign>comes Orientis</foreign>. The promotion must have taken place in the years 370-373 AD, although we have no evidence to prove it. Feissel (2011-2012, p. 80) has amended the appointment to cover the larger <foreign><placeName ref="Oriens">Oriens</placeName></foreign> diocese with <foreign>comes Orientis</foreign>: ὅ<supplied reason="lost">λης</supplied> ἄρχος ἐῴας (compatible with the curved letter visible on the stone: previous proposals, ὅ<supplied reason="lost">πλ</supplied>αρχος ἐῴας and <supplied reason="lost">ἔπ</supplied>αρχος ἐῴας are less satisfactory).</p>
                <p>The promotion of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> from <foreign>praeses <placeName>Thebaidis</placeName></foreign>, to <foreign>praefectus Aegypti</foreign> (province), to <foreign>consularis <placeName>Syriae</placeName></foreign>, then to <foreign>vicarius</foreign> of the <foreign><placeName ref="Oriens">Oriens</placeName></foreign> diocese as <foreign>comes Orientis</foreign>, is perfectly in keeping with a rapid career, adhering to the precepts of the <foreign>ordo dignitatum</foreign>. Scholars who think that <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was already responsible for the new dioecese of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> in 367-370 AD, suggest a double appointment of <foreign>consularis <placeName>Syriae</placeName></foreign> with <foreign>comes Orientis</foreign> in 370-374 AD (PLRE and Delmaire 1989a), but we believe that the positions were consecutive (Seeck 1906; Ensslin 1932; Errington 2002; Olszaniec 2013). Ecclesiastical writers place <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ anti-Nicene activity in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> after the death of Bishop <persName>Athanasius</persName> on May 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 373 AD (<ref type="source">Hist. Acephal. 12, p. 166 Martin-Albert</ref>; <ref type="source">Athan., Ep. Fest. 39-45, pp. 271-277 Martin-Albert</ref>; <ref type="source">Phot., Bibl. 08, 39 [Cod. 258, p. 484 Bekker]</ref>; <ref type="source">Rufin., HE 11, 02</ref>; <ref type="source">Joh. Nic., 82, 20</ref>; <ref type="source">Suidae, O 764 Adler</ref>). Some scholars think that the dates are wrong (Seeck 1906, 286; PLRE, I, 876-877), others that <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was already serving in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> as <foreign>comes sacrarum largitionum</foreign> (Ensslin 1932, col. 2465; Delmaire 1989a, 65). We agree with Olszaniec (2013, pp. 397-398) that <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> acted as <foreign>comes Orientis</foreign>, whose circonscription still included <placeName>Egypt</placeName> in 373 AD (for further discussion, see Woods 1995; Mratscheck 2012, pp. 261-266). <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was <foreign>consularis <foreign>Syriae</foreign></foreign> and <foreign>comes Orientis</foreign> when the emperor <persName type="ruler">Valens</persName> was in <placeName>Antioch</placeName> with his court, fighting against the Persians. The senator was involved in a major religious clash between Nicene and Arians that divided the entire East (on <persName type="ruler">Valens</persName> and the eastern frontier, cf. Lenski 2002, pp. 153-210, on religious schisms ibid. pp. 234-263). The friendship between <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> and the rhetor Libanius began during his stay in <placeName>Antioch</placeName> (judgements on the dignitary’s behaviour can be found in <ref type="source">Lib., Or. 46, 08</ref>; <ref type="source">Or. 10, 37</ref>; cf. Petit 1994 pp. 240-243).</p>
            <p>Line 9. In the years 374-380 AD, the emperors <persName type="ruler">Valens</persName>, followed by <persName type="ruler">Theodosius I</persName>, gave <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> a long mandate as <foreign>Comes Sacrarum Largitionum</foreign> in <placeName>Antioch</placeName> and then in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. The appointment is attested by six laws, the first one dated to February 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 374 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 10, 20, 08</ref>), the last one to June 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 380 AD (<ref type="source">CJ 08, 36, 03</ref>; sources discussed by PLRE I, p. 877; Delmaire 1989a, pp. 66-67; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 398-399). Even in the delicate period, following the defeat of <placeName>Hadrianopolis</placeName> (August 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 378 AD), <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> still managed to retain his prominent position as <foreign>comes sacrarum largitionum</foreign> in the eastern court. He remained in the service of the new emperor <persName type="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> during the first two years of the war against the Goths.</p>
<p>Line 10. After an intense and important career, lasting twenty-two years, eight years of otium followed (380-388 AD). When the powerful praetorian prefect of the East <persName><name ref="gentilicium">Maternus</name> <name ref="cognomen">Cynegius</name></persName> died, on March 388 AD (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret75">PPRET 75</ref>), <persName type="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> chose <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> as his successor (<ref type="source">Zos. 04, 45, 01</ref>). <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was in office from the Spring of 388 (<ref type="source">CTh 16, 04, 02</ref>, on June 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 388 AD) to mid 392 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 127</ref>, on June 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 392 AD). Soon thereafter, in April 388 AD, <persName type="ruler">Theodosius</persName> went to war against the usurper Maximus, defeated him on August 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> in <placeName>Aquileia</placeName> and stayed in <placeName>Italy</placeName> until July 391 AD, when he returned to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. For over three years (338-391 AD), Tatianus had remained the highest civil authority in the East. His activities as praetorian prefect were both important and far reaching. Not only is he generally accredited as the recipient of thirty-seven constitutions of the law Codes, he was also the recipient of thirteen letters from Libanius; he is, in fact, cited in another thirteen letters (all these documents are listed in Ensslin 1932, coll. 2465-2466; PLRE I, p. 877; Delmaire 1989a, pp. 66-67 nt. 62; Olszaniec 2013, p. 399 nt. 2072; for the letters, see Petit 1994, pp. 240-241; Pellizzari 2017). In 393 AD, his decision to cancel certain fiscal measures, demonstrates his autonomy in directing the administration of the great Eastern prefecture (<ref type="source">CTh 09, 42, 12</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 09, 42, 13</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 11, 01, 23</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 131</ref>). During his praetorian prefecture, <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> dedicated more honorary statues to the emperors (<persName type="ruler">Valentinianus II</persName>, <persName type="ruler">Theodosius I</persName>, <persName type="ruler">Arcadius</persName> Augusti and <persName type="ruler">Honorius</persName> <foreign>nobilissimus</foreign>) in some provincial capitals (<placeName ref="Aphrodisias">Aphrodisias</placeName> <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret82">PPRET 82</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret83">83</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret84">84</ref>; Side <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret85">PPRET 85</ref>; <placeName>Antinoupolis</placeName> <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret86">PPRET 86</ref>). His supervision of works along the Nile is testified by an inscription at <placeName>Canopus</placeName> (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret90">PPRET 90</ref>). The diffusion of standard capacity measures for the calculation of tax payments in the provincial <foreign>horrea</foreign> is attested by the inscription of <placeName ref="Myra">Myra</placeName> (<placeName>Andriakè</placeName> <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret88">PPRET 88</ref>). The testimonies are scattered and piecemeal, nevertheless they reveal something of the intensity and variety of the work he undertook. For the administrative activity of his son, <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName>, in this period, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret89">PPRET 89</ref>. During his absence from <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, it is likely that <persName type="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> wanted to entrust the eastern provinces to a couple of experienced dignitaries, who were part of the Lycian civic aristocracy. <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ policies as prefect appear to centre around protecting the less wealthy curials and defending traditional city life. His initiatives include a better distribution of liturgical and fiscal burdens, fighting against the flight from the curias and reducing the privileges of the clergy. Libanius’ appreciation of him (and later Eunapius/Zosimus) is explained by his support for civic life, no doubt inspired by the Emperor Julian (on urban life in the East, cf. Cabouret 2020, pp. 67-170; concerning the allocation of taxation in the cities, cf. Bransbourg 2008; on Libanius and the civic life, cf. Francesio 2004; Pellizzari 2011).</p> 
<p>Lines 13-23. In 391 AD <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ career was crowned by the ordinary consulate (next to <persName><name ref="praenomen">Q.</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Aur.</name> <name ref="cognomen">Symmachus</name></persName>, CLRE, pp. 316-317). The consulate was the most prestigious office of the late Roman <foreign>cursus honorum</foreign> and is celebrated at length in this inscription (regarding the prestige of the late roman consulate, see above).</p>
<p>When <persName type="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> returned to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> (July 391 AD), he appears to have deemed the policies of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> and <persName>Proculus</persName> as too self-centred and contrary to the process of administrative centralisation that aimed at limiting the autonomy of the <foreign>curiae</foreign>. The <foreign>magister officiorum</foreign> <persName><name ref="cognomen">Rufinus</name></persName> (PLRE I, pp. 778-781) used his extensive administrative powers to discredit the two prefects in the eyes of the emperor. As a result, the latter deprived both father and son of their offices and had them tried, it seems, for corruption or <foreign>crimen maiestatis</foreign>. Between June 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 392 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 127</ref> the last correctly dated constitution to the praetorian prefect <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>) and August 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 392 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 08, 06, 02</ref> the first constitution to his successor as praetorian prefect of the East, <persName><name ref="cognomen">Rufinus</name></persName>), <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was suddenly deposed. The trial led to his condemnation and exile in his homeland in <placeName>Lycia</placeName> (likely during the winter 392/393; see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret91">PPRET 91</ref>). While the father had his property confiscated, the son <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName> paid a heavier price and was executed in December 393 AD (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret89">PPRET 89</ref>; on these events, cf. Rebenich 1989, pp. 159-163; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 400-402; Mecella 2015, p. 55). Many of the laws passed by <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> and <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName>, during their terms of office were annulled by the Emperor <persName type="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> (<ref type="source">CTh 09, 42, 12</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 09, 42, 13</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 11, 01, 23</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 131</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh.14.17.12</ref>).  Their names were erased on inscriptions (for <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret82">PPRET 82</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret83">83</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret84">84</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret85">85</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret86">86</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret88">88</ref>; for <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName>, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret89">PPRET 89</ref>), but not on our inscription from <placeName>Sidyma</placeName>. Having executed the praetorian prefect <persName><name ref="cognomen">Rufinus</name></persName>, the emperor decreed in 396 AD that no infamy should befall the clients of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, many of whom had been drawn from the province of <placeName>Lycia</placeName> (<ref type="source">CTh 09, 38, 09</ref>, on August 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 396 AD, cited above, with Mecella 2015, in part. p. 58 nt. 26). Barely fifty years later, it appears that <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was rehabilitated, given that his omonymous grandson was able to erect an honorary inscription in <placeName ref="Aphrodisias">Aphrodisias</placeName> (<placeName>Caria</placeName>) in his memory (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret91">PPRET 91</ref>). The name of <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ son <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName> was also restored on the base of the obelisk of <persName type="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret89">PPRET 89</ref>). Several elements lead us to suggest that the <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> inscription is, in effect, an epitaph: the exaltation of the ordinary consulship, the lack of a dedicator, the presence of a <foreign>cursus honorum</foreign>, the fact that the name had not been erased etc.. As an epitaph the inscription would have been placed at the entrance to the senator’s tomb or cenotaph, most likely after 396 AD.
</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>CIG 03, 4266e</ref> (with diplomatic edition)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Kaibel 1878, nr. 919 </ref> (first transcription according to the verses)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Benndorf, Niemann 1884, p. 81, nr. 65-66</ref> (with fac-simile)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Cougny 1890, nr. 344</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>ILS 8844</ref> (inscription on the first block only)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>TAM 02, 186-187</ref> (with fac-simile from Benndorf)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Grégoire 1922, nr. 293 bis</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Merkelbach 1978, p. 174</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Delmaire 1989a, pp. 62-63</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Livrea 1997, p. 44</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Merkelbach, Stauber 2002 (SGO 04), nr. 17/08/03</ref></bibl>
                <bibl><ref>Olszaniec 2013, p. 394</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://inscriptions.packhum.org/text/284076">PH 284076</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/text/385604">TM 385604</ref></bibl>
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Agostini G., Prefetti e praesides nell'amministrazione giudiziaria dell'Egitto tardoantico: ambiti di competenza e prosopografia (284-397) [unpublished PhD Diss. Roma "Sapienza" 2019]</bibl>
                    <bibl>Baillet J., Inscriptions grecques et latines des toumbeaux des rois ou syringes à Thèbes, II, Le Caire 1923.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Benndorf O., Niemann G., Reisen im südwestlichen Kleinasien, I. Reisen in Lykien und Karien, Wien 1884.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bernand É., Inscriptions métriques de l’Égypte gréco-romaine. Recherches sur la poésie épigrammatique des Grecs en Égypte, Besançon 1969.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Berns C., The Tomb as a Node of public Representation. Intramural burials in Roman imperial Asia Minor, in Le Mort dans la ville. Pratiques, contextes et impacts des inhumations intra-muros en Anatolie, du début de l'Age du Bronze à l'époque romaine, dir. O. Henry, Istanbul 2013, pp. 231-242 (https://books.openedition.org/ifeagd/2057)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bransbourg G., Fiscalité impériale et finances municipales au IVe siècle, AntTard 16, 2008, 255-296.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cabouret B., La société de l'Empire romain d'Orient, IVe-VIe siècle, Rennes 2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Carrié J.-M., Séparation ou cumul ? Pouvoir civil et autorité militaire dans les provinces d’Égypte de Gallien à la conquête Arabe, AntTard 6, 1998, 105-121.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cecconi G.A., Lineamenti di storia del consolato tardoantico, in M. David (a cura di), Eburnea Diptycha. I dittici d’avorio tra Antichità e Medioevo, Bari 2007, 109-130.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cormack S., The Space of Death in Roman Asia Minor, Wien 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cougny E., Epigrammatum anthologia Palatina cum Planudeis et appendice nova, III, Paris 1890.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dardaine S., Frézouls E., Sidyma. Étude topographique, Ktèma 10, 1985, 211-217.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dardaine S., Longepierre D., Essai de typologie des monuments funéraires de Sidyma (époques lycienne et romaine), Ktèma 10, 1985, 219-232.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hellenkemper H., Hild F., Lykien und Pamphylien, Wien 2004. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Delmaire R., Les responsables des finances impériales au Bas-Empire romain (IVe-VIe s.). Études prosopographique, Bruxelles 1989a.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Delmaire R., Largesses sacrées et res privata l'aerarium impérial et son administration du IVe au VIe siècle, Roma 1989b.</bibl>
                    <bibl>de Salvo S., Ancora sull'istituzione della dioecesis Aegypti, RSA 9, 1979, 69-79. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Ensslin W., Tatianus 3, in RE IV A 2, Stuttgart 1932, coll. 2463-2467.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Errington R., A note on the Augustal Prefect of Egypt, Tyche 17, 2002, 69-77. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Feissel D., Sources documentaires et histoire administrative de l’Orient romain tardif, IVe-VIIe siècles, Annuaire de l'École pratique des hautes études (EPHE), Section des Sciences historiques et philologiques [Online], 144 (2011-2012) 2013 (online: http://ashp.revues.org/1471)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Francesio M., L’idea di Città in Libanio, Stuttgart 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grégoire H., Recueil des inscriptions grecques-chrétiennes d’Asie Mineure, Paris 1922.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Guarducci M., L'epigrafia greca dalle origini al tardo impero, Roma 1987. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Kaibel G., Epigrammata Graeca ex lapidibus conlecta, Berolini 1878.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lallemand J., L’administration civile de l’Égypte de l’avènement de Diocletién à la création du diocèse (284–382). Contribution à l’étude des rapportsentre l’Egypte et l’Empire à la fin du IIIe et au IVe siècle, Bruxelles 1964.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Laniado A., Recherches sur les notables municipaux dans l'empire protobyzantin, Paris 2002. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lenski N.E., Failure of Empire. Valens and the roman state in the fourth century A.D., Berkeley-Los Angeles-London 2002. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Livrea E., I due Taziani in un’iscrizione di Afrodisia, ZPE, 119, 1997, 43-49.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ma J., Statues and Cities. Honorific portraits and civic identity in the Hellenistic world, Oxford 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>McLean B.H., An introduction to Greek epigraphy of the Hellenistic and Roman periods from Alexander the Great down to the reign of Constantine (323 B.C.-A.D. 337), Ann Arbor (Mich.) 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mecella L., L’amministrazione di Taziano e Proculo e il destino dei Lici tra Teodosio e Arcadio, in Governare e riformare l’impero al momento della sua divisione: Oriente, Occidente, Illirico, a cura di U. Roberto, L. Mecella, Roma 2015, 51-84 (http://books.openedition.org/efr/2800).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mednikarova I., The Accusative of the Name of the Deceased in Latin and Greek Epitaphs, ZPE, 143, 2003, 117-134.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Merkelbach R., Das Epigramm aus Sidyma auf Tatianus, ZPE, 30, 1978, 173-174.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Merkelbach R., Stauber J., Steinepigramme aus dem griechischen Osten (SGO), IV. Die Südküste Kleinasiens, Syrien und Palaestina, München 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mratschek S., Melania and the Unknown Governor of Palestine, JLA 5/2, 2012, 250-268. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Olszaniec S., Prosopographical Studies on the Court Elite in the Roman Empire (4th Century AD), Toruń, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Palme B., Praesides and Correctores der Augustamnica, AntTard 6, 1998, 123-135. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Pellizzari A., «Salvare le città»: lessico e ideologia nell’opera di Libanio, Κοινωνία 35, 2011, 45-61.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pellizzari A., Maestro di retorica, maestro di vita. Le lettere teodosiane di Libanio di Antiochia, Roma 2017. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Petit P., Les fonctionnaires dans l’œuvre de Libanius. Analyse prosopographique, Besançon 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Petrini F.M., Cassiod., Var. VI, 1 (Formula consulatus), in Flavio Magno Aurelio Cassiodoro Senatore, Varie, dir. A. Giardina, a cura di A. Giardina, G.A. Cecconi, I. Tantillo, F. Oppedisano, III (Libri VI-VII), Roma 2015, 6-9 and 107-113.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pharr C., The Theodosian Code and Novels and the Sirmondian constitutions. A translation with commentary, glossary, and bibliography, Princeton 1952. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Pouilloux J., Roesch P., Marcillet-Jaubert J., Salamine de Chypre, XIII. Testimonia Salaminia, 2. Corpus épigraphique, Paris 1987.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rebenich S., Beobachtungen zum Sturz des Tatianus und des Proculus, ZPE, 76, 1989, 153-165.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scharf R., Die Familie des Fl. Eutolmius Tatianus, ZPE 85, 1991, 223-231.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schweyer A.-V., Les Lyciens et la mort. Une étude d’histoire sociale, Paris 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Seeck O., Die Briefe des Libanius zeitlich geördnet, Leipzig 1906.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sguaitamatti L., Der spätantike Konsulat, Fribourg 2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vanderslayen C., Chronologie des préfets d’Égypte de 284 à 395, Bruxelles 1962. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Woods D., Tatianus and the Basilica of Menas, Byzantion 65, 1995, 467-474.</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="2">
                    <p n="2.9">ἀπειρεσίους πόνους αἷσιν ἤνυσεν ἀρχαῖς</p>
                    <p n="2.10">[οἱ] θεῖοι βασιλεῖς τοῖς ἔρ[γοισιν αὐτοῦ] | χαίροντες | εἵνεκ’ ἀμοιβῆς ὑπατίᾳ στέ[ψαντ’] | (20) ἀφθάρτῳ | ὡς ἂν αὐτῷ κῦδος καὶ τι[μήν μεγά]|λην ὀπάσοιεν | πάντας ἐπ’ ἀνθρώπους ἅμα τ’ α[ὐτίκα] | καὶ μετέπειτα |
</p>
                    </div>
                <div type="commentary" n="3">
                    <p n="3"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">(λαμπρότατος)</p>
                    <p n="8.2">ἔπαρχος μέγας</p>
                    <p n="8.3"></p>
                    <p n="8.10"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>