<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Dionysus’ statue base from <foreign>Attideum</foreign> at Ostia (Rome) by the former praet. prefect C. Ceionius Rufius Volusianus <foreign>signo</foreign> Lampadius</title>
                <editor role="edition">Eleonora Angius</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Eleonora Angius</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="plre" corresp="pp. 978-980">40</idno>
                <date when="2020-03-27"/>
                <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Lampadius"><name type="praenomen">Caius</name>
                        <name type="gentilicium">Ceionius Rufius</name>
                        <name type="cognomen">Volusianus</name>
                        <name type="signum">Lampadius</name></persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#Ostia">Archaeological Museum of the Ancient Ostia, room II, Sc. ST. 299</repository>
                        <idno type="invNo">inv. 165</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#religious">Religious inscription</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#marble">Greek Marble</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>28</height>
                                        <width>40</width>
                                        <depth>8</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">yes</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">none</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One inscribed field (frons) on the plinth of the statue (field: high 4.7 cm; wide 32.5 cm).</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#undamaged">Undamaged.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#rustic_capitals">rustic capitals</term>
                                <height>3.5/2</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Roma</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Rome (Italy)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Urbs</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Italiciana</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Italia Illyricum Africa</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">public space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p7" notBefore="0365" notAfter="0377">365-377 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found"><placeName ref="#">Ostia</placeName>, found in May 1940 during the excavations of the temple of Attis (Reg. IV, I, 3) in the South-East side of the Magna Mater campus, near Porta Laurentina</provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"></provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="la">
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/>Volusianus <expan><abbr>v</abbr><ex>ir</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>c</abbr><ex>larissimus</ex></expan> ex <expan><abbr>pra<lb
                        break="no" n="2"/>efe</abbr><ex>c</ex>tis</expan> tauroboliatus <expan><abbr>d</abbr><ex>onum</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>d</abbr><ex>edit</ex></expan>.  
                    </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>Edition based on FTD VI, 1 (2019), p. 71.</p>
                <p>
                    <app loc="1-2"><note>pra/efetis: Calza 1943, p. 219, nr. 12; Bloch 1953, p. 272, nr. 34; Rieger 2004, p. 287, MMA 24</note></app>
                    <app loc="2"><note><expan><abbr>d</abbr><ex>ono</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>d</abbr><ex>edit</ex></expan>: Bloch 1953, p. 272, nr. 34; CCCA III, 366; <expan><abbr>d</abbr><ex>edit</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>d</abbr><ex>edicavit</ex></expan>: Duthoy 1969, p. 27, nr. 44; <expan><abbr>m</abbr><ex>atris</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>d</abbr><ex>eae</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>d</abbr><ex>edit</ex></expan>: Rieger 2004, p. 287, MMA 24</note></app>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“Volusianus, of clarissimus rank, a former prefect, who having performed the taurobolium, gave this as a gift.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>(from FTD VI, p. 71)</p>
                <p>“Volusianus, clarissime, ancien préfet, taurobolié, a offert ce don.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Volusianus, chiarissimo, ex prefetto, tauroboliato, offrì questo dono.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
<p>The statue and its plinth were discovered at Ostia on May 1940 in the <foreign>Attideum</foreign>, the little <foreign>sacellum</foreign> of Attis near the Porta Laurentina (Reg. IV, I, 3). The statue was lying among the 19 sculptures which were found either in the rectangular entrance or in the large apse of the sanctuary (Calza 1946, p. 207; on this collection of statues cf. Boin 2013, in part. pp. 260-261, 266-267). Near the <foreign>Attideum</foreign> lay the temple of Magna Mater, which, immediately after the Phrygianum Vaticanum, was the most important sanctuary for this cult in Latium (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret36">PPRET 36</ref>; on the campus of the Magna Mater at Ostia cf. Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018, pp. 383-386; Van Haeperen 2019b, chap. 4).</p>  
<p>The life-size statue (130 cm) appears rather damaged: the head, neck, right arm, left forearm, and left shin are missing. It wears a nebris diagonally across the upper body from the left shoulder to right waist. A chlamys is wrapped around the hip, thighs, and lower left arm and it wears soft decorated boots (see <ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail.php?record=2539">LSA 2539</ref>; Rieger 2004, p. 287, MMA 24). This unusual combination of attributes identifies the statue as a youthful Dionysus, a deity associated to the worship of Magna Mater.</p>   
<p>The plinth supporting the reused 1st Century AD statue, bears an abbreviated two-line inscription that was only added later. The inscription qualifies the statue as a gift of the former prefect Volusianus, who partook in a <foreign>taurobolium</foreign>, a renowned pagan ritual.</p>  
<p>The ritual of the <foreign>taurobolium</foreign> originated in Asia Minor and first appears in the West in 134 AD, where it was associated with the cult of <foreign>Venus Caelestis</foreign> (CIL X, 1596, dedication from Pozzuoli). Only later was the ceremony incorporated into the worship of Cybele, approximately under the Antonini, since the earliest known altar dedicated to the Magna Mater commemorating a <foreign>taurobolium</foreign>, carried out <foreign>pro salute imperatoris</foreign>, dates to 160 AD (CIL XIII, 1751). Unfortunately few literary sources mention the <foreign>taurobolium</foreign>; most are Christians and they describe it unanimously as a barbarous, bloody ritual. The Christian poet Prudentius in his <foreign>Peristephanon</foreign> (<ref type="source">Prud., Peristeph., 10, 1011-1050</ref>) furnishes us with the most detailed, bloody description, but there is also the anonymous author of the <foreign>Carmen contra Paganos</foreign> (vv. 57-61) and Firmicus Maternus (<ref type="source">Firm., Err., 27, 08</ref>). These interpretations need, however, much caution. Indeed, the numerous taurobolic inscriptions that have survived offer little evidence about the precise nature of the ceremony, that was so variously interpreted.</p> 
<p>Rutter (1968, pp. 226-249), Duthoy (1969, pp. 101-105) and Vermaresen (1977, p. 11, 102, 180) argued that the <foreign>taurobolium</foreign> underwent an evolution that could be divided into several phases. Although they differ slightly on the kind of ceremony carried out in the first stages, they do agree on the fact that the ritual evolved from a bull chase into something promoting the prosperity of its dedicator, generally the emperor (<foreign>pro salute imperatoris</foreign>), becoming in its late antique phase, a veritable “baptism of blood,” in accordance with Prudentius’ account, that is to say that the dedicator would descend into a pit and the bull would be slaughtered on a plank above, drenching the dedicator with blood.</p> 
<p>More recently, scholars have questioned the reliability of these bloody descriptions, Prudentius in particular, considering them a caricature aimed at promoting their own ideological standpoint (McLynn 1996, pp. 319-320; furthermore Borgeaud 1998; Alvar 2008, pp. 261-275; Cameron 2011, p. 160; Van Haeperen 2014; Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018, pp. 298-402; Van Haeperen 2019b, chap. 3). As McLynn (1996, p. 323) states, the main evolution that the <foreign>taurobolium</foreign> experienced was that it evolved from a public to a private rite and that it had remained «essentially the same ritual but had differed in their intended beneficiaries and the degree of publicity». Indeed, from the second half of the 2nd Century to the end of the 3rd Century (CIL VIII, 23401, the last recorded <foreign>taurobolium pro salute imperatoris</foreign> at Mactar in Africa during the Tetrarchy) the <foreign>taurobolium</foreign> had had the character of a public cult, performed on behalf of the emperor. Later, during the 4th Century, the rite developed into a private cult becoming a perquisite of the aristocracy alone. As a sign of social cohesiveness and distinction, the <foreign>clarissimi</foreign> performed the <foreign>taurobolia</foreign> collectively in the presence of the religious community and their family. The extant epigraphic data reveals that more than one person could perform the <foreign>taurobolium</foreign> on any given day: on May 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 376 AD Ulpius Egnatius Faventinus (CIL VI, 504), Sextilius Agesilaus Aedesius (CIL VI, 510) and an anonymous dedicant  performed it (CIL VI, 3118). On May 23<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 390 AD Lucius Ragonius Venustus (CIL VI, 503) and Lampadius’ son Ceionius Rufius Volusianus did the same (CIL VI, 512,) and on July 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 374 AD Alfenius Ceionius Julianus Kamenius (CIL VI, 1675) and Clodius Hermogenianus Caesarius did it as well (CIL VI, 499). From what we can see this ‘elite cult’ appears to experience a rebirth, becoming the religious emblem of the pagan aristocracy, some of whom attained the highest positions of the imperial administration, as Lampadius and his family did (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret36">PPRET 36</ref>). Among these powerful <foreign>clarissimi</foreign> there was our dedicant, whose identity has long been conjectured.</p> 
<p>First R. Calza (1946, p. 219) suggested that Volusianus <foreign>tauroboliatus</foreign>, who dedicated the statue of Dionysus, might actually be Gaius Ceionius Rufius Volusianus (PLRE I, p. 977), the praetorian prefect and urban prefect of the early 4th Century under the usurper Maxentius and then Constantine. Instead, Fuhrmann (1941, pp. 103-109) and others after him (PLRE I, pp. 978-980; McLynn 1996, pp. 326-328; Lizzi 2004, p. 73; Rieger 2004, p. 287; Boin 2013, pp. 260-261), indentified the <foreign>tauroboliatus</foreign> as Caeionius Rufius Volusianus <foreign>signo</foreign> Lampadius, praetorian prefect in 355 AD and urban prefect in 365 AD (about his complete career, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret36">PPRET 36</ref>). This identification is highly plausible given that at least three of his children performed the <foreign>taurobolium</foreign>, following what was the family religious belief. Indeed, multiple dedications from the Vatican Phrygianum demonstrate this (Rufia Volusiana, CIL VI, 509; Sabina, CIL VI, 30966 = IG XIV, 1019; Rufius Ceionius Volusianus, CIL VI, 512, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret36">PPRET 36</ref>). The theory is also supported by the involvement of Volusianus <foreign>signo</foreign> Lampadius in several pagan cults, as an inscription found on the Aventine hill suggests recording him as <foreign>pater</foreign>, hierophant, prophet of Isis and <foreign>pontifex Solis</foreign> (CIL VI, 846, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret36">PPRET 36</ref>). Concerning the identification of our dedicator with Lampadius, the use of the plural “<foreign>ex praefe(c)tis</foreign>” is important. In the second half of the 4th Century, no other Volusianus could boast two completed prefectures and Lampadius underlines his title of former prefect in five other inscriptions (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret36">PPRET 36</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret37">PPRET 37</ref>37, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret38">PPRET 38</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret39">PPRET 39</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret41">PPRET 41</ref>). In our inscription from the <foreign>Attideum</foreign> of Ostia the senator refers to the two prefectures he had already held, the praetorian one and urban one, in 355 and 365 AD respectively. This gives us quite a good <foreign>terminus post quem</foreign> for the monument, which can now be fixed at 365 AD. Volusianus underwent the <foreign>taurobolium</foreign> approximately in the same period of the other members of his family (370-377 AD, see above) or also together with one of them, as we have already said, even if we do not know which one.</p> 
<p>However, another discovery further attests his presence at Ostia and his connection with the port. In the courtyard of the Ostian temple of <foreign>Fabri Navales</foreign>, later re-used as a marble depository after it ceased functioning in the 4th Century AD, several semi-worked architectural elements destined to be employed in local constructions were found. All are virtually contemporary with the aforementioned inscription. Among them five columns preserve the carved name of a Rufius Volusianus, either in full, <foreign>Volusiani v(iri) c(larissimi)</foreign>, or only initialled, <foreign>Ru(fii) Bo(lusiani)</foreign> (see Bloch 1953, nr. 34 a-d; Cébeillac-Gervasoni-Caldelli 2010, p. 203, nr. 57. 1- 57.3). Suspecting that one of these inscribed columns was used in a so called Christian basilica nearby, Pensabene (1973, pp. 51-52; 2007, p. 408), and more recently Cébeillac-Gervasoni, Caldelli, Zevi (2010, p. 203) and also Romeo (2019, p. 20) argue that this particular Volusianus corresponds to a later member of the same renowned family of the <foreign>Ceionii</foreign>, Rufius Antonius Agrypnius Volusianus (urban prefect in 417/418 AD and praetorian prefect in 428-429 AD; PLRE II, pp. 1184-1185; Chastagnol 1956; Sbriglione 2010, pp. 179-182), who lived between the end of the 4th Century and the first half of the 5th Century and who himself converted to Christianity shortly before his death (437 AD).</p> 
<p>Of course the fact that his name had been inscribed on a column does not necessarily imply that he had been a Christian. A more recent and extensive study of the Late-Antique phases of the so called Christian Basilica has also revealed that during the 4th Century this structure was probably an aristocratic <foreign>domus</foreign>. Only in the early 5th Century did it became a Christian building, albeit with a plan that diverges from that of a basilica (Guidobaldi 1995, pp. 525-535; Lizzi 2004, pp. 72-73). Given the intense building activity carried out during his urban prefecture, this figure could also be identified with C. Ceionius Rufius Volusianus <foreign>signo</foreign> Lampadius.</p> 
<p>However it is still not clear what connection this man had with the marble depository. Pensabene (2007, p. 408) thought that this carved name was an abbreviation of the buyer of the shafts, but Lizzi (2004, pp. 73-74), on the other hand, assumes that Volusianus could have been the owner of the depository, as his name in the genitive case suggests. If so, it would explain the particular interest that the urban prefect displayed in restoring the monuments of his city.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>Fuhrmann 1941, p. 106</ref> = <bibl><ref>AE 1945, 55</ref></bibl></bibl>  
                    <bibl><ref>Calza 1943, p. 219, nr. 12</ref> (fig. 21) = <bibl><ref>AE 1948, 34</ref></bibl></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Bloch 1953, p. 272, nr. 34</ref> (fig. 25) = <bibl><ref>AE 1955, 180</ref></bibl></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Duthoy 1969, p. 27, nr. 44</ref></bibl>  
                    <bibl><ref>Meiggs 1973, p. 212</ref></bibl>  
                    <bibl><ref>CCCA III, 366</ref></bibl>  
                    <bibl><ref>Rieger 2004, p. 287, MMA 24</ref> (fig. 126)</bibl>  
                    <bibl><ref>Cébeillac-Gervasoni, Caldelli, Zevi 2010, p. 203, nr. 57.1</ref></bibl>  
                    <bibl><ref>Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018, p. 514, nr. 122</ref></bibl>  
                    <bibl><ref>FTD VI, 1 (2019), p. 71</ref> (fig. 21 a, b)</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p>
                   <bibl><ref>Calza 1943, p. 219, nr. 12 (fig. 21)</ref></bibl>
                   <bibl><ref>Bloch 1953, p. 272, nr. 34 (fig. 25)</ref></bibl>
                   <bibl><ref>Rieger 2004, p. 287, MMA 24 (fig. 126</ref>)</bibl>
                   <bibl><ref>Boin 2013, p. 262, fig. 6</ref></bibl>
                   <bibl><ref>Boin 2013, p. 187, fig. 48</ref></bibl>
                   <bibl><ref>FTD VI, 1 (2019), p. 71 (fig. 21 a, b)</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?id_nr=EDR073502">EDR 073502</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/edh/inschrift/HD019848">HD 019848</ref></bibl>  
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail.php?record=2539">LSA 2539</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
<bibl>Alvar J., Romanising Oriental Gods. Myth, salvation, and ethics in the cults of Cybele, Isis and Mithras, Leiden-Boston 2008</bibl> 
<bibl>Bloch H., Ostia. Iscrizioni rinvenute tra il 1930 e il 1939, NSc, 7, 1953, 272-273, nr. 34 (fig. 25)</bibl> 
<bibl>Boin D. R., A late antique statuary collection at Ostia’s sanctuary of Magna Mater: a case- study in late Roman religion and tradition, PBSR, 81, 2013, 260-263, fig. 6</bibl> 
<bibl>Boin D. R., Ostia in Late Antiquity, Cambridge 2013, 183-188, fig. 48</bibl> 
<bibl>Borgeaud P., Taurobolion, in Ansichten griechischer Rituale. Geburtstags-Symposium für W. Burkert, Castelen bei Basel, 15. bis 18. März 1996, Stuttgart 1998, 183-198</bibl> 
<bibl>Calza R., Sculture rinvenute nel santuario, MPAA, 6, 1943, 219-220, nr. 12, fig. 21</bibl> 
<bibl>Cameron A., The last pagans of Rome, New York 2011, 49-50, 144, 147, 154, 157, 224-225</bibl> 
<bibl>Cébeillac-Gervasoni M., Caldelli M.L., Zevi F., Epigrafia Latina Ostia. Cento iscrizioni in contesto, Roma 2010, 202-205, nr. 57.1</bibl> 
<bibl>Chastagnol A., Le sénateur Volusien et la conversion d’une famille de l’aristocratie romaine au Bas-Empire, REA, 58, 1956, 241-253</bibl> 
<bibl>Dubosson-Sbriglione L., Le culte de la Mère des dieux dans l’Empire romain, Stuttgart 2018, p. 514, nr. 122</bibl> 
<bibl>Duthoy R., The taurobolium. Its evolution and terminology, Leiden 1969, p. 27, nr. 44</bibl> 
<bibl>Fuhrmann H., C. Caeionius Rufus Volusianus Lampadius, Epigraphica 3, 1941, 103-108</bibl> 
<bibl>Gassman M. P., Worshippers of the Gods: Debating Paganism in the Fourth-Century Roman West, Oxford 2020, 83-105</bibl> 
<bibl>Guidobaldi F., Una domus tardoantica inedita ad Ostia ed i suoi pavimenti, in I. Bragantini-F. Guidobaldi (a cura di), Atti del II Colloquio dell’Associazione Italiana per lo Studio e la Conservazione del Mosaico (Roma 5-7 dic. 1994), Bordighera 1995, 525-535</bibl> 
<bibl>Lizzi Testa R., Senatori, popolo, papi. Il governo di Roma al tempo dei Valentiniani, Bari 2004, 61-89</bibl> 
<bibl>Martinez- Maza C.,  Devotas mistéricas en la Roma bajoimperial, Aevum, 77, 2003, 53-68</bibl> 
<bibl>McLynn N., The Fourth-Century “taurobolium”, Phoenix, 50, 1996, 312-330</bibl> 
<bibl>Pasqualini A., Garofalo P., Pasqua di sangue: Il ciclo metroaco, la condanna cristiana del taurobolio e la diffusione del rito pagano nel Lazio, Bibbia e Oriente, 58, 2016, 439-491</bibl> 
<bibl>Meiggs R., Roman Ostia, Oxford 1973, 212, 398, 401</bibl> 
<bibl>Pensabene P., I capitelli in Scavi di Ostia VII, Roma 1973, 51-52</bibl> 
<bibl>Pensabene P., Ostiensum marmorum decus et decor: Studi architettonici, decorativi e archeometrici, Roma 2007, 407-411</bibl> 
<bibl>Rieger A. K., Heiligtümer in Ostia, München 2004, 287, MMA 24 (fig. 126)</bibl> 
<bibl>Romeo I., Scavi di Ostia, 17, I ritratti, parte 3. I ritratti romani dal 250 circa al VI secolo D.C., Sesto Fiorentino 2019, 20</bibl> 
<bibl>Rutter J., The Three Phases of the Taurobolium, Phoenix, 22, 1968, 226-249</bibl> 
<bibl>Sbriglione L., La “gens” Caeionia: étude prosopographique et réflexions sur la conversion d’une famille aristocratique, Anc Soc, 40, 2010, 153-196</bibl> 
<bibl>Van Haeperen F., Prêtre(sses)s, tauroboles et mystères phrygiens, in Figures de dieux. Construire le divin en images, Rennes 2014, 99-118</bibl> 
<bibl>Van Haeperen F., Fana, templa, delubra: corpus dei luoghi di culto dell’Italia antica (FTD) 6 Regio 1 Ostie, Porto, Roma 2019 (a), 71, 126 (fig. 21)</bibl> 
<bibl>Van Haeperen F., Étrangère et ancestrale. La mère des dieux dans le monde romain, Paris 2019 (b)</bibl> 
<bibl>Vermaseren M. J., Corpus cultus Cybelae Attidisque (CCCA), Vol. III, Leiden 1977, 112-113, nr. 366</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"></p>
                </div>
                <div type="commentary" n="7">
                    <p n="7.8"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">(v)ir (c)larissimus</p>
                    <p n="8.2">ex pra/efe(c)tis</p>
                    <p n="8.5"></p>
                    <p n="8.10"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
