<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Monumental Greek inscription on the architrave of the Theatre of Hierapolis for its restoration supervised by the praet. prefect Flavius Philippus</title>
                <editor role="edition">Eleonora Angius</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Eleonora Angius</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="new">30</idno>
                <date when="2020-03-27"/>
                <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Philippus"><name type="gentilicium">Flavius</name>
                            <name type="cognomen">Philippus</name></persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#Hierapolis">Some blocks are sequentially arranged in front of the Theatre of Hierapolis, the smaller ones are in the reserve of the "MAIER" (Missione Archeologica Italiana a Hierapolis).</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#building">Building inscription commemorating the restoration of the Theatre of Hierapolis</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="grc">Greek</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#marble">marble</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#architectural_element">architectural element, 42 blocks of the architrave of the second order of the Theatre of Hierapolis</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>11 cm (only the superior section of the architrave where the inscription is carved); the entire architrave and the frieze measures 83.2</height>
                                        <width>unknown</width>
                                        <depth>20</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">none</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">yes (only block 19)</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One inscribed field. The inscription runs along a single line.</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#damaged">Some blocks are fragmentary (2, 6, 7, 8, 13, 15-16, 23, 31) and damaged (2, 4, 13, 17, 18, 21, 23, 25, 26, 28); the text on blocks 5 and 6 was obscured through <foreign>dealbatio</foreign> due to the <foreign>damnatio memoriae</foreign> of Constantius Gallus after 354 AD.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#serifs">letters with serifs</term>
                                <height>6.5/7.5</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Hierapolis</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Pamukkale (Turkey)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Phrygia Pacatiana</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Asiana</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">public space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p5" when="0352" precision="high">352 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found"><placeName ref="#">Hierapolis</placeName>, from the excavations of the theatre</provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"></provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="grc">
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1"/><g ref="hedera"/> Ἀγαθῇ Τύχῃ. Ἐπί τῆς εὐδα<supplied reason="lost">ίμον</supplied>ος καὶ θείας ἀληθῶς βασι<supplied reason="lost">λείας τ</supplied>οῦ τροπαιοφόρου καὶ γῆς καὶ θαλάττης ἀναδησαμένου τὸ κράτος Κωνστ<supplied reason="lost">αντίου</supplied> μεγάλου βασιλέως καὶ τοῦ θεοφιλεστάτου καὶ καλῶς ἡμεῖν ἐπιφανέντος Κωνσταντίου τοῦ Καίσαρος, τὸ θέατρον πτῶσιν ἀπειλοῦν καὶ τῷ πλείστῷ μέρι τῆς μητροπ<supplied reason="lost">όλεως</supplied> κίνδυνον ἐπαγγελλόμενον, καλάνδαις μὲν σεπτεμβρίαις τὴν λύσιν ἤρξατο λαμβάνειν, ἐπὶ τῆς ὑπατίας Σεργίου· τῆς δὲ κατασκευῆς ἀρχὴ γέγονεν ἀπὸ <expan><abbr>καλ</abbr><ex>ανδῶν</ex></expan> ἰουνίων ὑπατίας τῆς μετὰ Σέργιον, κ<supplied reason="lost" cert="low" >αὶ τέλ</supplied>ος ἔσχεν σὺν τῇ σκουτλώσει εἰς τὴν εὐτυχῆ καὶ μακαρίαν ὑπατίαν τῶν σεβασμείων αὐτοκρατόρων ἡμῶν Κωνσταντίου τὸ πέμπτον καὶ Κωνσταντίου Καί<supplied reason="lost">σαρος</supplied> τὸ πρῶτον, <expan><abbr>Φλ</abbr><ex>αουίου</ex></expan> Φιλίππου τοῦ θ<supplied reason="lost">α</supplied>υμασιωτάτου καὶ πάσης εὐφημίας ἀ<supplied reason="lost">ξίο</supplied>υ, καὶ τῶν ἱερῶν πρ<supplied reason="lost">α</supplied>ιτω<supplied reason="lost">ρ</supplied>ίων ἐπάρχου, προστάξαντος, ἐξ ἀναφορᾶς <expan><abbr>Φλ</abbr><ex>αουίου</ex></expan> Ἀντωνίου Ἰουλιανοῦ, τοῦ <expan><abbr>διασημ</abbr><ex>ωτάτου</ex></expan> ἡγεμόνος ἡμῶν· γέγονεν <supplied reason="lost">δὲ</supplied> τοῦ παντὸς ἔργου κατασκευαστής, μηδεμίας διαγραφῆς γενομένης, ὁ αὑτός Ἰουλιανός, ὁ φιλάνθρωπος καὶ σωτὴρ ἀληθῶς καὶ τῆς ἐπαρχείας πάσης κηδεμών, καὶ τ<supplied reason="lost">όδε τὸ ἔργον ἐτελεί</supplied>ωσεν, παντὸς τοῦ πολιτευτικοῦ καταλόγου προθυμῶς συνεργήσαντος διὰ χρημάτων εἰσκομιδῆς καὶ τῆς τῶν ἰδίων ἀγροίκων βοηθείας, <g ref="hedera"/> <supplied reason="lost" cert="low"><expan><abbr>T</abbr><ex>ίτου</ex></expan></supplied> <supplied reason="lost" cert="low"><expan><abbr>Αἰβ</abbr><ex>ουτίου</ex></expan></supplied> Εὐπολίδος Ἀπφιανοῦ καὶ <expan><abbr>Πο</abbr><ex>πλίου</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>Τρεβ</abbr><ex cert="low">ωνίου</ex></expan> <supplied reason="lost" cert="low">Παλλαδίου <expan><abbr>πο</abbr><ex>λιτευομένων</ex></expan>/ <expan><abbr>πολιτ</abbr><ex cert="low">ευομένων</ex></expan> έργεπιστατούντων</supplied>. 
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>Edition based on Ritti 2017, p. 416 with different readings of the blocks 35-37 by Feissel (BE 2018, 434)</p>
                <p>
                <app loc="Block 19"><note><supplied reason="lost" cert="low">Αὐτοκράτορα</supplied> Εὐσεβῆ... Εὐτυχῆ Μακαρίαν Ὑπατι<supplied reason="lost">κὴν</supplied>: Fellows 1841, pp. 425-426, nr. 200; τὴν εὐτυχῆ καὶ μακαρίαν ὑπατι<supplied reason="lost">κὴν</supplied>: CIG III, 3908 (b); <supplied reason="lost">σ</supplied>κουτλόσει εἰς τὴν εὐτυχῆ καὶ μακαρίαν ὑπατ<gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>: IGRRP IV, 808</note></app>
                <app loc="Block 34"><note><supplied reason="lost">καλὸς κἀγαθὸς ἄ</supplied>νθρωπος καὶ σωτὴρ ἀληθῶς: Judeich 1898, pp. 68-69, nr. 4 (d); IGRRP IV, 808</note></app>
                <app loc="Block 35-36"><note>τ<supplied reason="lost">ὸ πᾶν ἐτελεί</supplied>ωσεν or <supplied reason="lost">συνεπλήρ</supplied>ωσεν: Jones 2018, p. 925; τ<supplied reason="lost" cert="low">ὸ</supplied> <supplied reason="lost">ἀνενέ</supplied>ωσεν: Ritti 2017, p. 595</note></app>
                <app loc="Block 36-37"><note>κατὰ λόγου: Ritti 2017, p. 595</note></app>
                <app loc="Block 37-39"><note>γαλλόγου προθυμῶς συ<gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>: CIG III, 3908 (c); <supplied reason="lost">χορ</supplied>ηγήσαντος διὰ χρημάτων εἰς κ<supplied reason="lost" cert="low">ατασκευήν</supplied>: CIG III, 3908 (a); γαλλόγου προθυμῶς συ<supplied reason="lost" cert="low">μβοηθ</supplied>ήσαντος διὰ χρημάτων εἰσκ<supplied reason="lost" cert="low">ομισθέντων ὑπ'αὐτοῦ</supplied><supplied reason="lost"> καὶ διά τ</supplied>ῆς τῶν ἰδίων ἀγροίκων βοηθείας: Judeich 1898, pp. 68-69, nr. 4 (l; m; n); πρ<supplied reason="lost">ο</supplied>θυμῶς συ<supplied reason="lost">μβοηθ</supplied>ήσαντος διὰ χρημάτων εἰσκ[<supplied reason="lost" cert="low">ομισθέντων ὑπ'αὐτοῦ</supplied><supplied reason="lost"> αὶ διά τ</supplied>ῆς τῶν ἰδίων ἀγροίκων βοηθείας: IGRRP IV, 808</note></app>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“To good fortune. During the truly happy and divine reign of the great emperor Constantius, triumphant, surrounded by sovereignty over land and sea, and of Constantius Caesar, beloved of God, who manifested himself to us in a magnificent way, the theater, which threatened to collapse and revealed itself to be a danger for most of the metropolis, began to be demolished on the kalends of September, during the consulate of Sergius. The reconstruction began on the kalends of June, during the consulate following that of Sergius, and was completed, with the marble facing, during the fortunate and peaceful consulate of our venerable emperors, Constantius, for the fifth time, and Constantius Caesar, for the first time; in accordance with the dispositions of Flavius Philippus, a very admirable man worthy of all praise and prefect of the sacred praetoria, on the report of Flavius Antonius Iulianus, our governor of perfectissimus rank: the superintendent of all the work, without any extraordinary taxation, was the same Iulianus, benevolent and authentic savior and guardian of the whole province, and [he carried out this work], while all the register of the city’s ruling class, by means of spontaneous payments of money and by means of the contribution of his own farmers, cooperated with enthusiasm; [were supervisors of the work the curials (?) T(itus)?] Aeb(utius) Eupolis Apphianos and P(ublius) Treb(onius?) [Palladios?].”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>“A la bonne chance. Pendant le règne vraiment heureux et divin du grand empereur Constance, triomphateur, entouré de la souveraineté sur terre et sur mer, et de Constance César, bien-aimé de Dieu, qui s'est manifesté à nous de façon magnifique, le théâtre, qui menaçait de s'effondrer et s'annonçait comme un danger pour la plus grande partie de la métropole, a commencé à être démoli lors des kalendes de Septembre, pendant le consulat de Serge. La reconstruction a commencé aux kalends de Juin, au cours du consulat qui a suivi celui de Serge, et s'est achevée, avec le parement de marbre, au cours du consulat heureux et serein de nos vénérables empereurs Constance, pour la cinquième fois, et Constance César, pour la première fois ; à la disposition de Flavius Philippus, homme très admirable, digne de tous les éloges et préfet des prétoires sacrés, sur le rapport de Flavius Antonius Iulianus, notre parfait gouverneur : il était le surintendant de tous les travaux, sans imposer aucune imposition extraordinaire, le même Iulianus, bienveillant et authentique sauveur et gardien de toute la province, et [l'organisateur de toute la reconstruction], coopérant avec élan tout l'album de la classe dirigeante de la ville, par des versements spontanés d'argent et par la contribution de ses fermiers ; [étaient les surveillants des travaux les curiales ( ? ) T(ito) ?] Aeb(utius) Eupolis Apphianos et P(ublius) Treb(onius ?) [Palladios ?].”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Alla buona fortuna. Durante il regno invero felice e divino del grande imperatore Costanzo, trionfatore, circonfuso della sovranità sulla terra e sul mare, e di Costanzo Cesare, amatissimo da Dio, che si è manifestato a noi in modo magnifico, il teatro, che minacciava il crollo e si annunciava un pericolo per la maggior parte della metropoli, cominciò a essere demolito alle calende di settembre, durante il consolato di Sergio. L’inizio della ricostruzione avvenne a partire dalle calende di giugno, durante il consolato successivo a quello di Sergio, e giunse a termine, con il rivestimento in marmo, durante il fortunato e sereno consolato dei nostri venerabili imperatori Costanzo, per la quinta volta, e Costanzo Cesare, per la prima volta; per disposizione di Flavius Philippus, uomo assai mirabile e degno di ogni lode e prefetto dei sacri pretorii, su relazione di Flavius Antonius Iulianus, il perfettissimo governatore nostro: fu il sovrintendente di tutta l’opera, senza che intervenisse alcuna imposizione fiscale straordinaria, lo stesso Iulianus, benevolo e autentico salvatore e custode di tutta la provincia, e [portò a compimento quest’opera], cooperando con slancio tutto l’albo della classe dirigente cittadina, mediante versamenti spontanei di denaro e l’apporto dei propri agricoltori; [sono stati supervisori dell’opera i curiali (?) T(ito)?] Aeb(utius) Eupolis Apphianos e P(ublius) Treb(ellius?) [Palladios?].”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>This long inscription was carved in the mid 4th Century on forty-two blocks, making up the architrave of the second order of the <foreign>scaenae frons</foreign> of the Theatre of Hierapolis.</p>  
                <p>Some of these blocks had already been examined by other scholars during the 18th Century (see the critical edition.) However, the latter combined the blocks of our inscription with those of another (the severan inscription on the architrave of the first order, text by Ritti 2017, pp. 500-501), inadvertently uniting pieces of two different texts. Finally, Tullia Ritti working in conjuction with MAIER (<foreign>Missione Archeologica Italiana a Hierapolis</foreign>) re-assembled the forty-two blocks of the architrave correctly following the little guide letters sequentially carved on the extremity of each one (the letter on the right side of each block is the same on the left side of the following one). In such a way she successfuly able to restore almost the entire text (Ritti 2017, pp. 590-595).</p>  
                <p>Thanks to her reconstruction it was possible to explain where the different dedications of the Theatre of Hierapolis originally were. The architrave of the second order held two inscriptions: the earlier one in honour of Caracalla (Ritti 2017, pp. 514-515) was carved on the left side of the building in front of the <foreign>cavea</foreign>, while our later one in honour of Constantius II ran along the facade and the right side; there was also a third severan dedication on the architrave of the first order (Ritti 2017, pp. 498-506). The stone-cutter of our later inscription evidently tried to emulate the epigraphic appearence of its ancient counterparts, both with regard to writing and decorative elements in order to uphold the tradition.</p>   
                <p>Our inscription recorded building works on the Theatre of Hierapolis, whose structure (or part of it) was in danger of imminent collapse. Although the reasons for the intervention are not given, poor mantainance or the earthquakes at the end of the Severan age may well have been factors.</p>  
                <p>The text starts with an auspicious formula and the titles of the emperors Constantius II Augustus, as <foreign>triumphator</foreign> and <foreign>dominus</foreign> of land and sea (τοῦ τροπαιοφόρου καὶ γῆς καὶ θαλάττης ἀναδησαμένου τὸ κράτος Κωνστ[αντίου] μεγάλου βασιλέως), and Constantius Gallus Caesar, as dear to God and charitable to the subjects (τοῦ θεοφιλεστάτου καὶ καλῶς ἡμεῖν ἐπιφανέντος Κωνσταντίου τοῦ Καίσαρος), whose name was subject to <foreign>dealbatio</foreign> (escaping the erasure due to the high position of the text) when he suffered <foreign>damnatio memoriae</foreign> after his death in 354 AD.</p> 
                <p>The inscription then specifies, in exeptional detail, the beginning of each phase of restoration by refering to the consulate of the first consul (a post-consular formula due to the absence of consuls for the year 351 AD, see AE 2017, 1497), showing a clearly planned operation. First comes the demolition (λύσις), carried out by removing the damaged or precarious parts, which took place on the calends of September 350 AD (καλάνδαις μὲν σεπτεμβρίαις τὴν λύσιν ἤρξατο λαμβάνειν, ἐπὶ τῆς ὑπατίας Σεργίου), under the consulate of Sergius, (CLRE, pp. 234-235), up to the end of May 351 AD. Indeed, on the calends of June 351 AD (ἀπὸ καλ(ανδῶν) ἰουνίων ὑπατίας τῆς μετὰ Σέργιον) began the restoration proper (κατασκευή) of the theatre followed by final finishing works (σκούτλωσις), necessitating the application of the expensive marble covering. 
                    The restoration was completed in an unspecified moment of 352 AD, when Augustus Constantius II and his Caesar Constantius Gallus were consuls for the fifth and the first time respectively (εἰς τὴν εὐτυχῆ καὶ μακαρίαν ὑπατίαν τῶν σεβασμείων αὐτοκρατόρων ἡμῶν Κωνσταντίου τὸ πέμπτον καὶ Κωνσταντίου Καίσαρος τὸ πρῶτον; CLRE, pp. 238-239). The inscription was thus put up upon completion of the work (352 AD or later).</p>  
                <p>After mentioning the phases of the restoration and their duration, the inscription goes on. In order to exalt both the complexity and speed of the work, the illustrious officials involved in this project are listed by order of rank and their various roles are described with hyperbolic and eulogistic formulas. First in the list is our praetorian prefect Flavius Philippus (τοῦ θαυμασιωτάτου καὶ πάσης εὐφημίας ἀξίου, καὶ τῶν ἱερῶν πραιτωρίων ἐπάρχου), who dealt with the approval and the supervision of the building project. Next comes the provincial governor Antonius Iulianus (PLRE I, p. 471), who sent an <foreign>istantia</foreign> (ἀναφορά) to Philippus warning of the risk of the theatre’s collapse, including a project and an evaluation of the expenses, requiring the prefect’s consent (Ritti 2017, pp. 612-614). In order to avoid the leverage of an extraordinary tax (<foreign>superindictio</foreign>), as proposed by the <foreign>praeses</foreign>, Philippus also agreed to grant the project a fiscal exemption.</p> 
                <p>The provincial <foreign>praeses perfectissimus</foreign> of Phrygia Pacatiana Antonius Iulianus (PLRE I, p. 471, τοῦ διασημ(ωτάτου) ἡγεμόνος ἡμῶν) was the real promoter of this intervention (γέγονεν δὲ τοῦ παντὸς ἔργου κατασκευαστής) by evaluating, according to his official capacities, which buildings needed to be restored and running the theater. He was praised for his administrative ability (μηδεμίας διαγραφῆς γενομένης) and for having brought advantages to the entire province (ὁ φιλάνθρωπος καὶ σωτὴρ ἀληθῶς καὶ τῆς ἐπαρχείας πάσης κηδεμών). 
                    The funds used for building works came mostly from those managed by the provincial governor, but they were also voluntarily supplemented by the curial class (πολιτευτικόν) through economic and manual support, largely thanks to their farmers (Ritti 2017, pp. 617-619). The sequence of interventions in the case of a Latin inscription would probably have been: <foreign>disponente Fl(avio) Philippo v(iro) c(larissimo) praefecto praetorio, referente atque curante Antonio Iuliano v(iro) p(erfectissimo) praeside provinciae</foreign>, or <foreign>per instantiam Antonii Iuliani</foreign> etc.</p> 
                <p>Finally there are the names, partly lost, of certain members of two illustrious local families, the Aebutii and Trebonii who saw to the construction work (Ritti 2017, pp. 617-620).</p> 
                <p>Since Flavius Philippus was mentioned as praetorian prefect in this text, Ritti concluded that he was still in charge when the restoration was finished and the inscription carved on its architrave (Ritti 2017, pp. 645-650). According to this assumption, therefore, after his embassy to Magnentius’ camp in 351 AD and his concomitant imprisonment (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret27">PPRET 27</ref>), Flavius Philippus was not only freed, but was also still praetorian prefect of the East in 352 AD. Nevertheless, another scenario ought to be considered.</p>  
                <p>Although Zosimus (<ref type="source">Zos. 02, 46</ref>) attests to the presence of Flavius Philippus at the side of Constantius II in 351 AD during the Illyrian war against Magnentius, he does not indicate that he was the praetorian prefect (<ref type="source">Zos. 02, 46, 02</ref>: τῶν ἐν μεγίστοις ἀξιώμασιν ἄνδρα καὶ φρονήσει προέχοντα). 
                    He probably held the praetorian prefecture of the East until 350/351 AD (as already claimed by Moser 2018, p. 204), when he examined the report and approved the restoration project of the theatre. But this does not mean to say that he was in charge of the project until its completion. On the Hierapolis inscription the office of Philippus is separated from his name and comes after his eulogy (τοῦ θαυμασιωτάτου καὶ πάσης εὐφημίας ἀξίου, καὶ τῶν ἱερῶν πραιτωρίων ἐπάρχου).
                    As in other surviving inscriptions for the senator, the praise of Philippus precedes the office, the term of which would appear to be concluded (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret27">PPRET 27</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret28">PPRET 28</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret31">PPRET 31</ref>; not the case in <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret29">PPRET 29</ref> which however portrays him however as praetorian prefect). 
                    When Philippus accompanied Constantius II to Sirmium (Pannonia) in 351 AD during the Illyrian war and was sent as ambassador to the camp of the usurper, it is unlikely that he was still prefect of the East, since he would not have been able to carry out his functions. Philippus probably followed his master as a <foreign>comes</foreign>, implying that someone else must have immediately taken his place as praetorian prefect.</p>   
                <p>Once Philippus gets taken prisoner by Magnentius (<ref type="source">Zos. 02, 49</ref>; see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret27">PPRET 27</ref>), he disappears from our literary sources. Perhaps he was freed (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret27">PPRET 27</ref>), in any case the inscription on the Theater of Hierapolis confirms that he did not suffer any other misfortunes after that (as assumed by Jones 1955, p. 232; Vogler 1939, p. 137; PLRE I, p. 696; Kelly 2004, p. 189; Maraval 2013, p. 190; Deligiannakis 2018, pp. 33-34), because when Constantius Gallus’ name was removed due to <foreign>damnatio memoriae</foreign> in 354 AD, the name of Philippus was left intact. It was probably after the battle of Mursa (Speptember 351 AD) that the emperor Constantius II decided to honour his most loyal supporter and friend, Philippus, erecting gilded statues of him and portraying him in his most prestigious and powerful role, that of praetorian prefect (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret27">PPRET 27</ref> and <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret28">PPRET 28</ref>).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>Fellows 1841, pp. 425-426, nr. 200</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>CIG III, 3908</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Judeich 1898, pp. 68-69, nr. 4</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>IGRRP IV, 808</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Ritti 2007, p. 416</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>SEG 61, 1156</ref> = <bibl><ref>Ritti 2011, pp. 184-185</ref></bibl> = <bibl><ref>AE 2011, 1342</ref></bibl></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Ritti 2017, p. 595</ref></bibl> = <bibl><ref>BE 2018, 434</ref></bibl> = <bibl><ref>AE 2017, 1497</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>Ritti 2017, pp. 593-602</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Barnes T. D., Praetorian prefects 337-361, ZPE, 94, 1992, 251</bibl>  
                    <bibl>Böckh A., Corpus inscriptionum Graecarum, Vol. III, 1853, 31, nr. 3908</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Caggia M. P., La ricerca epigrafica: risultati dell’ultimo quadriennio e prospettive future, Hierapolis di Frigia, I. Le attività delle campagne di scavo e restauro 2000-2003, Istanbul 2007, 608-610</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Cagnat R., Inscriptiones graecae ad res romanas pertinentes, Vol. IV, Paris 1927, 282, nr. 808</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Castello M. G., Il quaestor Montius e il vicarius Fl. Magnus: alcune riflessioni sul reclutamento del funzionariato sotto Costanzo II, Historikà, 1, 2011, 145-185</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Deligiannakis G., The Last Pagans of Cyprus: Prolegomena to a History of Transition from Polytheism to Christianity, Church Building in Cyprus (Fourth to Seventh Centuries). A Mirror of Intercultural Contacts in the Eastern Mediterranean, Münster 2018, 33-34</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Fellows C., An Account of Discoveries in Lycia, being a journal kept during a second excursions in Asia Minor, London 1841, 425-426, nr. 200</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Jones A. H. M, The Career of Flavius Philippus, Historia, 4, 1955, 229-233</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jones C. P., The institutional history of Hierapolis, JRA, 31/2, 2018, 925</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kelly C., Ruling the later Roman Empire, Cambridge 2004, 189-190</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Judeich W., Altertümer von Hierapolis, Berlin 1898, pp. 68-69, nr. 4</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Maraval P., Les fils de Constantin: Constantin II (337-340), Constance II (337-361), Contant (337-350), Paris 2013, 190</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Moser M., Emperor and senators in the reign of Constantius II. Maintaining imperial rule between Rome and Constantinople in the fourth Century AD, Cambridge 2018, 202-205</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Ritti T., Iscrizioni pertinenti all’edificio teatrale di Hierapolis, in Il teatro di Hierapolis di Frigia. Restauro, erchitettura, epigrafia, eds D. De Bernardi Ferrero, G. Ciotta, P. Pensabene, Genova 2007, 416-417</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Ritti T., Andriantes kai eikones ... met’epigraphes oikeias. Contributi dell’epigrafia ieropolitana di età imperiale alla conoscenza delle opere figurative, in Roman Scuplture in Asia Minor, eds F. D’Andria, I. Romeo, Portsmouth 2011 (JRA int ser 80), 184-185</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Ritti T., Hierapolis di Frigia IX: Storia e istituzioni di Hierapolis, İstanbul 2017, 587- 621</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Trémaux P., Exploration archeologique en Asie mineure: comprenant les restes non connus de plus de quarante cites antiques, Paris 1858, tav. 8</bibl> 
                    <bibl>Vogler C., Constance II et l’administration impériale, Strasbourg 1979, 137-139</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="2">
                    <p n="2.1"></p>
                    <p n="2.9">τοῦ θ<supplied reason="lost">α</supplied>υμασιωτάτου καὶ πάσης εὐφημίας ἀ<supplied reason="lost">ξίο</supplied>υ</p>
                    <list n="2.11">
                        <item n="2.11.c"></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.2">τῶν ἱερῶν πρ<supplied reason="lost">α</supplied>ιτω<supplied reason="lost">ρ</supplied>ίων ἐπάρχου</p>
                    <p n="8.5"></p>
                    <p n="8.10"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>