<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Inscription in honour of the praet. prefect Probus from Capua made by the city <foreign>regiones</foreign> and <foreign>collegia</foreign></title>
                <editor role="edition">Pierfrancesco Porena</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Irene Vagionakis</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="rev" corresp="pp. 736-740">60</idno>
                <date when="2020-06-23"/>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Probus"><name type="praenomen">Sextus</name>
                        <name type="gentilicium">Claudius</name>
                        <name type="gentilicium">Petronius</name>
                        <name type="cognomen">Probus</name></persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#Capua">Museo Nazionale Campano di Capua (Palazzo Antignano)</repository>
                        <idno type="invNo">Cortile secondario, inv. nr. 5</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#honorary">Honorary inscription for the praetorian prefect Petronius Probus</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#limestone">limestone</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>111</height>
                                        <width>66</width>
                                        <depth>67</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">yes</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">uncertain</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One inscribed field (<foreign>frons</foreign>).</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#fragmentary">Fragmentary: the inscription is partially broken on the right side of the epigraphic field (lacuna on right-hand side of the first five lines).</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#square_capitals">late Roman monumental capitals</term>
                                <height>4.5 / 5</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Capua</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Santa Maria Capua Vetere (Caserta - Italy)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Campania</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Italiciana</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Italia Illyricum Africa</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">public space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p8" notBefore="0381" notAfter="0383">381/383 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found">found in 1955 in modern <placeName ref="#">Capua</placeName> (ancient Casilinum), along with another base for Anicius Paulinus, in a private house facing the Cathedral of Santa Maria Assunta (formerly Santi Stefano e Agata)</provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"></provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="la">
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/>Claudio Petronio Probo <expan><abbr>v</abbr><ex>iro</ex></expan> <supplied reason="lost"><expan><abbr>c</abbr><ex>larissimo</ex></expan></supplied>
                        <lb n="2"/>proconsuli Africae et <expan><abbr>s</abbr><ex>acra</ex></expan> <supplied reason="lost"><expan><abbr>v</abbr><ex>ice</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>i</abbr><ex>udicanti</ex></expan></supplied>,
                        <lb n="3"/>uno eodemque tempore <hi rend="supraline">I<unclear>I</unclear></hi> <supplied reason="lost">et <hi rend="supraline">III</hi></supplied>
                        <lb n="4"/>praetorio <sic>prefectura</sic> <expan><abbr>pol<supplied reason="lost">lent</supplied></abbr><supplied reason="lost"><ex>i</ex></supplied></expan>,
                        <lb n="5"/>consuli ordinario, nobilita<supplied reason="lost">te</supplied>
                        <lb n="6"/>munificentiaque <sic>praestante</sic>,
                        <lb n="7"/>originali patrono, regiones
                        <lb n="8"/><gap reason="lost" quantity="6" unit="character" precision="low"/> collegia posuerunt.
                    </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>Edition based on Porena 2020a, p. 111.</p>
                <p>
                    <app loc="1"><note><unclear>Cl</unclear>audio, Mazzarino 1974</note></app>
                    <app loc="2"><note>proconsuli Africae et s<supplied reason="lost">imul</supplied>, Barbieri 1971, LSA; proconsuli Africae et s(acra) <supplied reason="lost">v(ice) iud(icanti)</supplied>, Mazzarino 1974, Chastagnol 1982, Cameron 1985, EDR; et s<gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>, Chioffi 2005</note></app>
                    <app loc="3"><note>uno eodemque tempor(e) et<supplied reason="lost">iam</supplied>, Barbieri 1971, LSA, EDR; uno eodemque tempore (e)t <supplied reason="lost" cert="low">inde</supplied>, Mazzarino 1974; uno eodemque tempore et <supplied reason="lost">in</supplied>, Chastagnol 1982; uno eodemque tempore et<supplied reason="lost">iam</supplied>, Cameron 1985; uno eodemque tempor(e) et <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>, Chioffi 2005</note></app>
                    <app loc="4"><note>praetorio prefectura pol<supplied reason="lost">lenti</supplied>, Barbieri 1971, Mazzarino 1974, Giardina 1983; praetorio pr(a)efectura polle<supplied reason="lost">nti et</supplied>, Chastagnol 1982; praetorio pr(a)efectura pol<supplied reason="lost">lenti</supplied>, Chioffi 2005</note></app>
                    <app loc="6"><note>praestanti: Barbieri 1971, Mazzarino 1974, Chastagnol 1982, Cameron 1985, Chioffi 2005</note></app>
                    <app loc="8"><note><supplied reason="lost">?et omnia</supplied> collegia, Cameron 1985</note></app>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“To Claudius Petronius Probus, of clarissimus rank, proconsul of Africa with jurisdiction on behalf of the Emperor, holding the second and third praetorian prefecture both at the same time, ordinary consul, prominent for his nobility and munificence, patron since his family origin, the regions ... and the colleges set up”.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>“À Claudius Petronius Probus, clarissime proconsul d’Afrique avec juridiction en lieu et place de l’Empereur, tenant en même temps la deuxième et troisième préfecture du prétoire, consul ordinaire, supérieur en noblesse et munificence, patron lié par l’origine familiale, les régions .... les collèges ont dressé”.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Al chiarissimo Claudius Petronius Probus, proconsole d’Africa con giurisdizione in vece dell’imperatore, che riveste nello stesso momento la seconda e la terza prefettura del pretorio, console ordinario, superiore per nobiltà e per munificenza, patrono legato dall’origine familiare, le regioni ... i collegi posero”.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p><emph>The inscribed base for Probus</emph></p>
                <p>The base was found in 1955 in Capua (Caserta - Italy) during excavations of a house belonging to the Angeloni family. The property was situated in front of the entrance to the Duomo, the Cathedral of Santa Maria Assunta (formerly Saints Stephen and Agatha), but in the space that was once occupied by the Church of ‘San Giovanni dei Nobili Uomini’. The inscription was published in 1971 by G. Barbieri (1911-1985). It is currently kept in the Museo Nazionale Campano di Capua (Palazzo Antignano), Cortile secondario, inv. nr. 5.</p>
                <p>The inscription was chiselled onto a reused funerary altar. The dedication by the <foreign>regiones</foreign>, an uncertain civic entity and the <foreign>collegia</foreign> certainly belonging to the city of Capua suggests that in ancient times the base may have been in a public space in this Roman city (today Santa Maria Capua Vetere; on <foreign>regiones</foreign> and <foreign>collegia</foreign> see LSA 1936 sect. Further Discussion). 
                    However, the base appears to have been found in modern Capua (ancient Casilinum) which lies in the bend of the river Volturno 4.5 km. NorthWest of the ancient Roman city of Capua. The base was probably taken from the ruins of the Roman city, together with the base inscribed in honour of Anicius Paulinus (see below), and was reused in the construction of the new city of Capua by the river in the 10th Century. 
                    The presence of the <foreign>regiones</foreign> of the city among the dedicators, suggests that it was originally erected in a public space, although some other accessible space belonging to the <foreign>collegia</foreign> cannot be excluded.</p>
                <p>The limestone medium-sized parallelepiped base is made from a reworked and adapted funerary altar (<foreign>patera</foreign> on the left side, remains of the <foreign>pulvini</foreign> and a <foreign>focus</foreign> on the top).
                    The base is moulded at top and bottom, but the rear is heavily damaged, so that it is very difficult to establish whether the base is opisthographic. The editor of our inscription, Barbieri (1971, p. 298, see also LSA 1936) assumed that the base was opisthographic, since the <foreign>patera</foreign> on the left side and the lost <foreign>urceus</foreign> on the right side are the wrong way round. 
                    It is possible, therefore, that the present epigraphic field was in fact the back face of an altar that had been turned 180°. Furthermore, the ‘sister’ base for Anicius Paulinus is certainly opisthographic and it was engraved on the back face of a funerary altar (see below).</p>
                <p>On the upper surface of the base we find the housings for the statue’s feet. It was probably a bronze statue. 
                    Private individuals, dignitaries and public institutions all needed the emperor’s permission in order to put up a bronze statue in a public space. In our inscription from Capua the permission is not mentioned (see Feissel 1984, pp. 545-558; for bronze statues in honour of praetorian prefects with imperial permission, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret24">PPRET 24</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret54">54</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret58">58</ref>, without permission, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret57">PPRET 57</ref>. 
                    For references to gilded bronze statues in honour of praetorian prefects, erected in prestigious public spaces in this period [<foreign>sub auro</foreign>, <foreign>inaurata</foreign>, <foreign>auro condecorata</foreign>], see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret27">PPRET 27</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret28">28</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret31">31</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret46">46</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret48">48</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret51">51</ref>). 
                    It is not excluded that the monument could have been located in a private, but accessible space belonging to the <foreign>collegia</foreign>.</p>
                <p>The inscribed field (frons) is fragmentary: the inscription is partially broken on the right side of the epigraphic field. As we shall see, the lacuna on right-hand side of the first five lines is very important (see below).</p>
                
                <p><emph>The inscribed base for Paulinus</emph></p>
                <p>...</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>Barbieri 1971, p. 298</ref> (with photo: Tav. III, fig. 4; Tav. IV, fig. 5; Tav. V, fig. 6; Tav. VI, fig. 7) = <bibl><ref>AE 1972, 0076</ref></bibl></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Mazzarino 1974, p. 335</ref> (with photo: Tav. VII a-b)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Chastagnol 1982, p. 549</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Giardina 1983, p. 171</ref> (with photo: Tav. 1)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Cameron 1985, p. 164</ref> = <bibl><ref>AE 1985, 0273</ref></bibl></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Chioffi 2005, p. 110, nr. 111 bis</ref> (with photo: Fig. 107 bis, not legible)</bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Porena 2020a, p. 111 and p. 214, nr. 5</ref> (with photo: p. 109, fig. 66-67; p. 111, fig. 68; reconstructive drawing and relief p. 112, fig. 69; diplomatic edition p. 110)</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://db.edcs.eu/epigr/edcs_id.php?p_edcs_id=EDCS-09700055">EDCS 09700055</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?id_nr=EDR079706">EDR 079706</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/edh/inschrift/HD007080">HD 007080</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail-base.php?record=LSA-1936">LSA 1936</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/text/251339">TM 251339</ref></bibl>
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Barbieri G., Nuove iscrizioni di Capua, in Terza Miscellanea greca e romana, Roma 1971, 291-305</bibl>
                    <bibl>F. Bigi, I. Tantillo (a cura di), Senatori romani nel Pretorio di Gortina. Le statue di Asclepiodotus e la politica di Graziano dopo Adrianopoli, Pisa 2020</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cameron A., Polyonomy in the Late Roman Aristocracy: the Case of Petronius Probus, JRS, 75, 1985, 164-182</bibl>
                    <bibl>Camodeca G., Ricerche su Puteoli tardoromana (fine III-IV secolo), Puteoli, 4/5, 1980-1981, 59-128</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chastagnol A., Les fastes de la préfecture de Rome au Bas-Empire, Paris 1962</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chastagnol A., L’iscription de Petronius Probus à Capoue, in Epigrafia e ordine senatorio, I (Tituli 4), Roma 1982, 547-551</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chioffi L., Museo provinciale Campano di Capua. La raccolta epigrafica, Capua 2005, nr. 111a</bibl>
                    <bibl>Feissel D., Notes d’épigraphie chrétienne (VII), BCH, 108, 1984, 545-579</bibl>
                    <bibl>Giardina A., Lettura epigrafica e carriere aristocratiche. Il caso di Petronio Probo, RFIC, 111, 1983, 170-182</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mazzarino S., Sulla carriera prefettizia di Sex. Petronio Probo, in Id. Antico, tardoantico ed èra costantiniana, I, Bari 1974, 328-332</bibl>
                    <bibl>Olszaniec S., Prefektura praetorio Italii, Illyrikum i Afryki (312-425 n.e.), Toruń 2014</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Le iscrizioni del Pretorio di Gortyna e la carriera prefettizia di Sex. Petronius Probus, in F. Bigi, I. Tantillo (a cura di), Senatori romani nel Pretorio di Gortina. Le statue di Asclepiodotus e la politica di Graziano dopo Adrianopoli, Pisa 2020a, 87-141</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Ipotesi sull’istituzione di una prefettura del pretorio autonoma d’Illirico nel decennio 378-387, in F. Bigi, I. Tantillo (a cura di), Senatori romani nel Pretorio di Gortina. Le statue di Asclepiodotus e la politica di Graziano dopo Adrianopoli, Pisa 2020b, 143-166</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Appendice. Selezione di fonti sulla carriera prefettizia di Sex. Petronius Probus, in F. Bigi, I. Tantillo (a cura di), Senatori romani nel Pretorio di Gortina. Le statue di Asclepiodotus e la politica di Graziano dopo Adrianopoli, Pisa 2020c, 211-216</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="2">
                    <p n="2.a"></p>
                    <p n="2.1"></p>
                    <p n="2.9">nobilita[te] munificentiaque praestante (<foreign>sic</foreign>), originali patrono</p>
                    <p n="2.10">nobilita[te] munificentiaque praestante (<foreign>sic</foreign>), originali patrono</p>
                    <list n="2.11">
                        <item n="2.11.a"></item>
                        <item n="2.11.b"></item>
                        <item n="2.11.e"></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">vir clarissimus</p>
                    <p n="8.2">uno eodemque tempore I̅Ị̅ [et I̅I̅I̅] / praetorio prefectura (<foreign>sic</foreign>) pol[lent(i)]</p>
                    <p n="8.3"></p>
                    <p n="8.6">II et III</p>
                    <p n="8.9"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                    <p n="8.13"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
