<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Inscription of Fabia Aconia Paulina mentioning her father, the former praet. prefect Aconius Catullinus, and her husband, the praet. prefect Praetextatus</title>
                <editor role="edition">Pierfrancesco Porena</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Irene Vagionakis</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="plre" corresp="pp. 187-188, 722-724">20</idno>
                <date when="2020-06-23"/>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Catullinus"><name type="gentilicium">Aconius</name>
                        <name type="cognomen">Catullinus</name></persName>
                    </person>
                     <person>
                        <persName ref="#Praetextatus"><name type="gentilicium">Vettius</name>
                        <name type="gentilicium">Agorius</name>
                        <name type="cognomen">Praetextatus</name></persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#lost">lost</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#honorary">honorary inscription</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#marble">marble</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>unknown</height>
                                        <width>unknown</width>
                                        <depth>unknown</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">yes</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One inscribed field (frons).</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#undamaged">At the time of its transcription the text was undamaged. The text is known only from its manuscript tradition. The transcriptions preserve different line divisions: the layout of the lines of writing is not certain.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#unknown">unknown (no images available)</term>
                                <height>unknown</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Roma</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Rome (Italy)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Urbs</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Italiciana</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Italia Illyricum Africa</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#private">private space or building</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p5" notBefore="0384" notAfter="0387">384/387 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found"><placeName ref="#Roma">Rome</placeName>, first seen in the 15th Century in the church of the Santi XII Apostoli</provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="la">
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/>Fabiae Aconiae Paulinae, <expan><abbr>c</abbr><ex>larissimae</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>f</abbr><ex>eminae</ex></expan>,
                        <lb n="2"/>filiae Aconis (?) Catullini <expan><abbr>v</abbr><ex>iri</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>c</abbr><ex>larissimi</ex></expan> ex <expan><abbr>praef</abbr><ex>ecto</ex></expan> et consule <expan><abbr>ord</abbr><ex>inario</ex></expan>,
                        <lb n="3"/>uxori Vetti Praetextati <expan><abbr>v</abbr><ex>iri</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>c</abbr><ex>larissimi</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>praef</abbr><ex>ecti</ex></expan> et consulis designati,
                        <lb n="4"/>sacratae apud Eleusinam deo Iaccho Cereri et Corae,
                        <lb n="5"/>sacratae apud Laernam deo Libero et Cereri et Corae,
                        <lb n="6"/>sacratae apud Aeginam deabus, tauroboliatae, Isiacae,
                        <lb n="7"/>hierophantriae deae Hecatae, Gra<supplied reason="omitted">ia</supplied>e co<supplied reason="omitted">n</supplied>sacraneae deae Cereris.
                    </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>Edition based on CIL. For the many variants in the transcriptions of the MSS see CIL 06, 01780 apparatus.</p>
                <p>
                    <app loc="2"><note>MSS Aconis (Aconi, MS Alciatus and MS Pighius); Aconis, Vidman 1969, Vermaseren 1977, Bricault  2005, Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018, EDR; Aconi<supplied reason="omitted" cert="low">i</supplied>, Niquet 2000; Aconi, Kahlos 2002; Aconi<supplied reason="lost">i</supplied>, Martinez-Maza 2003; Aconii, LSA; ord(inarii), Martinez-Maza 2003</note></app>
    <app loc="3"><note>praef. <supplied reason="omitted">urbi</supplied>, Niquet 2000</note></app>
    <app loc="7"><note>Graeco sacraneae, CIL; hierophantriae deae Hecatae Graec<supplied reason="lost">ae</supplied> (vel Graiae), consacraneae deae Cereris, Mommsen (CIL 06, 01780 apparatus); hierophantriae Deae Cereris Graiae, consacraneae - vel co(n)sacraneae - Deae Hecatae, Mitthof in CIL 06, p. 4759; hirophantriae, Martinez-Maza; Graecosacraneae, ILS, Vidman 1969, Vermaseren 1977, Bricault 2005, LSA; Graeco (!) <supplied reason="omitted">con</supplied>sacraneae, Niquet 2000; Hecatae Graeco, sacfraneae, Kahlos 2002; graeco sacraneae, EDR, Martinez-Maza 2003; hierophantriae deae Hecatae Grae(cae) consacraneae deae Cereris EDCS; Hecatae Grae(cae) sacraneae, Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018; concerning our reconstruction of the text on line 7 see below (Commentary)</note></app>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“To Fabia Aconia Paulina, of clarissimus rank, daughter of Aconius Catullinus, of clarissimus rank, former prefect and ordinary consul, wife of Vettius Praetextatus, of clarissimus rank, prefect and consul designate, consecrated at Eleusis to the god Iacchus, Ceres and Cora, consecrated at Lerna to the god Liber, Ceres and Cora, consecrated to the goddesses at Aegina, tauroboliate, initiate of Isis, hierophant of the goddess Hecate, united to the worship of the Greek goddess Ceres”.</p>
                <p>(other engl. transl. by Croke, Harries 1982, pp. 105-106, nr. 65 = Erhart 2002, pp. 158-159, nr. 65, with notes; by Lefkowitz, Fant 1992 2nd ed., p. 306 = Kraemer 2004, p. 372)</p>
                </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>(Bricault 2005, p. 564)</p>
                <p>“Pour Fabia Aconia Paulina, clarissime, fille du clarissime Aconius Catullinus, ancien préfet et consul ordinaire, épouse du clarissime Vettius Praetextatus, préfet et consul désigné, consacrée à Éleusis au dieu Iacchos, à Cérès et à Corè, consacrée à Lerne au dieu Liber, à Cérès et à Corè, consacrée à Égine aux déesses, tauroboliée, isiaque, hiérophante de la déesse Hécate, Graecosacranea de la déesse Cérès”.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>(Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018, p. 508)</p>
                <p>“À Fabia Aconia Paulina, femme clarissime, fille d’Aconius Catullinus, clarissime, ancien préfet et consul ordinaire, épouse de Vettius Praetextatus, clarissime, préfet et consul désigné, consacrée à Éleusis au dieu Iacchos, à Cérès et à Coré, consacrée à Lerne au dieu Liber, à Cérès et à Coré, consacrée aux déesses qui sont à Égine, tauroboliée, isiaque, hiérophante de la déesse Hécate Grecque, prêtresse de la déesse Cérès”.</p>
                <p>l. 7 (Porena): “admise au culte de la déesse grecque Ceres”.</p>
                <p>(other French transl.: Chastagnol 1991, 2nd ed., p. 157, nr. 41B)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Per la chiarissima Fabia Aconia Paulina, figlia del chiarissimo Aconius Catullinus, già prefetto e console ordinario, moglie del chiarissimo Vettius Praetextatus, prefetto e console designato, consacrata a Eleusi al dio Iacchos, a Cerere e a Core, consacrata a Lerna al dio Libero, a Cerere e a Core, consacrata a Egina alle dee, tauroboliata, isiaca, ierofantria della dèa Ecate, ammessa al culto della dèa Cerere greca”.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>The critical edition and commentary of this inscription will be completed by the end of April 2022. We apologise for the delay.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>CIL 06, 01780</ref> (pp. 4759-4760) = <bibl><ref>CIL 06, 31930</ref></bibl> [by mistake indicated in Benevento and Ancona, <bibl><ref>CIL 09, *0223,6</ref></bibl> and <bibl><ref>CIL 09, *0641,3</ref></bibl>]</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>ILS 1260</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Duthoy 1969, p. 21, nr. 29</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Vidman 1969, p. 216, nr. 450</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Vermaseren 1977, p. 79, nr. 295</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Niquet 2000, p. 244</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Kahlos 2002, p. 223</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Martinez-Maza 2003, p. 67</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Bricault 2005, p. 564, nr. 501/0210</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018, pp. 507-508, nr. 109</ref></bibl> 
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://db.edcs.eu/epigr/edcs_id.php?p_edcs_id=EDCS-18100595">EDCS 18100595</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?id_nr=EDR138111">EDR 138111</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail-base.php?record=LSA-1474">LSA 1474</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/text/570243">TM 570243</ref></bibl>
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Alvar J., Romanising Oriental Gods. Myth, Salvation, and Ethics in the Cults of Cybele, Isis and Mithras, Leiden-Boston 2008</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barnes T.D., Regional Prefectures, in Bonner Historia-Augusta-Colloquium 1984-1985, Bonn 1987, 13-23</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barnes T.D., Praetorian Prefects, 337-361, ZPE, 94, 1992, 249-260</bibl>
                    <bibl>Berti F., Cecconi G.A., Vettio Agorio Pretestato in un’epigrafe inedita dal Valdarno, Ostraka, 6, 1997, 11-21</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bonnet C., Bricault L., Gomez C. (dir.), Les mille et une vies d’Isis. La réception des divinités du cercle isiaque de la fin de l’Antiquité à nos jours, Toulouse 2020</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bremmer J.N., Initiation into the Mysteries of the Ancient World, Berlin-Boston 2014</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bricault L., Receuil des inscriptions concernant les cultes Isiaques (RICIS), II, Corpus, Paris 2005</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bricault L., Les cultes isiaques dans le monde gréco-romain, Paris 2013</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bricault L., Gens Isiaca et identité polythéiste à Rome à la fin du IVe s. ap. J.-C., in L. Bricault, M.J. Versluys, J.-L. Podvin (eds), Power, Politics and the Cults of Isis, Leiden 2014 a, 326-359</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bricault L., Isis à Rome, in Ch. Méla, F. Möri (dir.), Alexandrie la divine, I, Genève 2014 b, 452-457</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bricault L., Les prêtres isiaques du monde romain, in V. Gasparini, R. Veymiers (eds), Individuals and materials in the Greco-Roman cults of Isis: agents, images, and practices, Leiden-Boston (Mass.) 2018, 155-197</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cagnat R., Note sur le praefectus urbi qu’on appelle à tort Aconius Catullinus et sur le proconsul d’Afrique du même nom, MEFR, 7, 1887, 258-267</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cameron Al., The last Pagans of Rome, Oxford-New York 2011</bibl>
                    <bibl>Campedelli C., Der Grabaltar von Praetextatus und Paulina: eine aristokratische Liebeserklärung über den Tod hinaus, Gymnasium, in print</bibl>
                    <bibl>Carucci M., The Sette Sale Domus - A Proposal of Reading, in P.F. Biehl, J.J. Rassamakin (eds), Import and Imitation in Archeology, Langenweißbach 2008, 213-221</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cecconi G.A., Commento storico al libro II dell’epistolario di Q. Aurelio Simmaco, Pisa 2002</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chastagnol A., Les fastes de la préfecture de Rome au Bas-empire, Paris 1962</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chastagnol A., Les préfets du prétoire de Constantin, REA, 70, 1968, 321-352</bibl>
                    <bibl>Clinton K., Epiphany in the Eleusinian Mysteries, ICS, 29, 2004, 85-109</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coarelli F., Isis Capitolina e Isis Campensis. Il culto ufficiale delle divinità egiziane a Roma, in The Iseum Campense from the Roman Empire to the Modern Age. Temple, monument, lieu de mémoire, Roma 2018, 61-77</bibl>
                    <bibl>Colin J., Cyriaque d’Ancône. Le voyageur, le marchand, l’humaniste, Paris 1981</bibl>
                    <bibl>Consolino F.E., Tradizionalismo e trasgressione nell’élite senatoria romana: ritratti di signore fra la fine del IV e l’inizio del V secolo, in R. Lizzi (a cura di), Le trasformazioni delle élites in età tardoantica, Roma 2006, 65-139</bibl>
                    <bibl>Conti S., Tra integrazione ed emarginazione: le ultime Vestali, SHHA, 21, 2003, 209-222</bibl>
                    <bibl>Croke B., Harries J., Religious Conflict in Fourth-Century Rome. A documentary study, Sidney 1982</bibl>
                    <bibl>Davenport C., The dynamics of imperial government: collegiality and regionalism, in N.J. Baker-Brian, S. Tougher (eds.), The sons of Constantine, AD 337-361: in the shadows of Constantine and Julian, Palgrave 2020, 223-254</bibl>
                    <bibl>Di Luzio M., All Call Me Blessed: the Magnificat in Paulina’s Poem to Praetextatus, JLA, 10/2, 2017, 432-453</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dubosson-Sbriglione L., Le culte de la Mère des dieux dans l’Empire romain, Stuttgart 2018</bibl>
                    <bibl>Duthoy R., The Taurobolium: its evolution and terminology, Leiden 1969</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ensoli S., I santuari di Iside e Serapide a Roma e la resistenza pagana in età tardoantica, in S. Ensoli, E. La Rocca (a cura di), Aurea Roma. Dalla città pagana alla città cristiana, Roma 2000, 267-287</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ensslin W., Praetextatus 1, in RE XXII/2, Stuttgart 1954, coll. 1575-1579</bibl>
                    <bibl>Erhart V., Inscriptions on Fabia Aconia Paulina, in L.J. Churchill, P.R. Brown, J.E. Jeffrey (eds), Women writing Latin. From Roman antiquity to early modern Europe, I. Women writing Latin in Roman antiquity, late antiquity, and the early modern Christian era, New York 2002, 151-163</bibl>
                    <bibl>Finocchi Ghersi L., Le residenze dei Colonna ai Santi Apostoli, in M. Chiabò et alii (a cura di), Alle origini della nuova Roma. Martino V (1417-1431), Roma 1992, 61-75</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fowden G., Polytheist religion and philosophy, in Av. Cameron, P. Garnsey (eds.), The Cambridge Ancient History, XIII2. The Late Empire, AD 337-425, Cambridge 1998, 538-560</bibl>
                    <bibl>R. Frei-Stolba, Coelia Concordia, la dernière Grand Vierge Vestale, et la partecipation des femmes au discours politique du IVe s. apr. J.-C., in R. Frei-Stolba, A. Bielman, O. Bianchi (édd.), Les femmes antiques entre sphère privée et sphère publique, Bern 2003, 281-315</bibl>
                    <bibl>Groag E., Die Reichsbeamten von Achaia in spätrömischer Zeit, Budapest 1946</bibl>
                    <bibl>Guidobaldi F., Domus: Vettius Agorius Praetextatus, in E.M. Steinby (a cura di), Lexicon Topographicum Urbis Romae, II, Roma 1995, 164</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jacques F., L’ordine senatorio attraverso la crisi del III secolo, in A. Giadrina (a cura di), Società romana e impero tardoantico, 1, Istituzioni, ceti, economie, Roma-Bari 1986, 81-225</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jiménez San Cristóbal A.I., Iacchus in Plutarch, in L. Roig Lanzillotta, I. Muñoz Gallarte (eds), Plutarch in the religious and philosophical discourse of late antiquity, Leiden-Boston (Mass.) 2012, 125-135</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kahlos M., Fabia Aconia Paulina and the death of Praetextatus: rhetoric and ideals in Late Antiquity (CIL VI 1779), Arctos, 28, 1994, 13-25</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kahlos M., Vettius Agorius Praetextatus. A senatorial life in between, Roma 2002</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kraemer R.S., Women’s Religions in the Graeco-Roman World. A Sourcebook, Oxford 2004</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kuhoff W., s.v. Vettius Agorius Praetextatus, in Biographisch-Bibliographisches Kirchenlexikon, XII, Herzberg 1997, 1297-1309</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lefkowitz M.R., Fant M.B., Women’s life in Greece &amp; Rome. A source book in translation, London 1992 (2nd ed.)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lizzi Testa R., Senatori, popolo, papi. Il governo di Roma al tempo dei Valentiniani, Bari 2004</bibl>
                    <bibl>MacRae D., Ludibrium Paulinae: Historiography, Anti-Pagan Polemic, and Aristocratic Marriage in De excidio Hierosolymitano 2.4, JLA, 14/2, 2021, 229-256</bibl>
                    <bibl>Magister S., La collezione di antichità del cardinale Giuliano della Rovere. Anteprima di studio, Xenia Antiqua, 9, 2000, 47-50</bibl>
                    <bibl>Magister S., Arte e politica: la collezione di antichità del Cardinale Giuliano della Rovere nei palazzi ai Santi Apostoli, Atti dell’Accademia Nazionale dei Lincei, ser. IX, 14/4, 2002, 385-631</bibl>
                    <bibl>Martínez-Maza C., Devotas mistéricas en la Roma bajoimperial, Aevum, 77, 2003, 53-68</bibl>
                    <bibl>Massa F., Vettio Agorio Pretestato: aristocrazia romana, “culti orientali” e cristianesimo, in C. Bonnet, E. Sanzi (a cura di), Roma città degli dèi. La capitale dell’impero come laboratorio religioso, Roma 2018, 63-76</bibl>
                    <bibl>Massa F., Éleusis-Rome aller / retour: mobilités religieuses autour des mystères éleusiniens à l’époque impériale, in A. Bassir (dir.), Migrations et mobilité religieuse: espaces, contacts, dynamiques et interférences, Besançon 2020, 271-293</bibl>
                    <bibl>McLynn N., The Fourth-Century “taurobolium”, Phoenix, 50, 1996, 312-330</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mitchell C., Bodnar E.W., Foss C. (eds), Cyriac of Ancona: Life and Early Travels, Cambridge Mass.-London 2015</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mustakallio K., The Ties That Bind, in K. Klaiber Hersch (ed.), Cultural History of Marriage in Antiquity, New York 2021, 77-88</bibl>
                    <bibl>Niquet H., Monumenta virtutum titulique. Senatorische Selbstdarstellung im spätantiken Rom im Spiegel der epigraphischen Denkmäler, Stuttgart 2000</bibl>
                    <bibl>North J., Gender and Cult in the Roman West: Mithras, Isis, Attis, in E.A. Hemelrijk, G. Woolf (eds), Women and the Roman city in the Latin West, Leiden-Boston (Mass.) 2013, 109-127</bibl>
                    <bibl>Piérart M., Le grand-père de Symmaque, la femme de Prétextat et les prêtres d’Argos ou les derniers feux du paganisme, in D. Knoepfler (éd.), Nomen Latinum. Mélanges de langue, de littérature et de civilisation latines offerts au professeur André Schneider à l’occasion de son départ à la retraite, Genève 1997, 149-157</bibl>
                    <bibl>Plassart A., Inscriptions de Thespies, BCH, 50, 1926, 383-462</bibl>
                    <bibl>Polara G., Iscrizioni e propaganda. Il cippo tombale di Pretestato, in F.E. Consolino (a cura di), Letteratura e propaganda nell’Occidente latino da Augusto ai regni romanobarbarici, Roma 2000, 107-126</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Le iscrizioni del Pretorio di Gortyna e la carriera prefettizia di Sex. Petronius Probus, in F. Bigi, I. Tantillo (a cura di), Senatori romani nel Pretorio di Gortina. Le statue di Asclepiodotus e la politica di Graziano dopo Adrianopoli, Pisa 2020a, 87-141</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Ipotesi sull’istituzione di una prefettura del pretorio autonoma d’Illirico nel decennio 378-387, in F. Bigi, I. Tantillo (a cura di), Senatori romani nel Pretorio di Gortina. Le statue di Asclepiodotus e la politica di Graziano dopo Adrianopoli, Pisa 2020b, 143-166</bibl>
                    <bibl>Raepsaet-Charlier M.-Th., La place des femmes dans la religion romaine: marginalisation ou complémentarité ? L’apport de la théologie, in P. Pavon (ed.), Marginación y mujer en el Imperio romano (siglos I-III), Roma 2018, 201-222</bibl>
                    <bibl>Reutter U., Damasus, Bischof von Rom (366-384): Leben und Werk, Tübingen 2009</bibl>
                    <bibl>Roesch P., Les Inscriptions de Thespies, VII, Inscriptions honorifiques (première partie). Ėdition électronique mise en forme par G. Argoud, A. Schachter, G. Vottéro, Lyon 2007, https://www.hisoma.mom.fr/sites/hisoma.mom.fr/files/img/production-scientifique/IT%20VII%20%282009%29.pdf</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rüpke J., Fasti Sacerdotum. Die Mitglieder der Priesterschaften und das sakrale Funktionspersonal römischer, griechischer, orientalischer und jüdisch-christlicher Kulte in der Stadt Rom von 300 v. Chr. bis 499 n. Chr., 3 voll., Stuttgart 2005</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scheid J., D’indispensables ‘étrangères’. Les rôles religieux des femmes à Rome, in G. Duby, M. Perrot (éd.), Histoire des femmes en Occident (dir. par P. Schmitt-Pantel), I. L’Antiquité, Paris 1991, 405-437</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scheid J., Les rôles religieux des femmes à Rome. Un complément, in R. Frei-Stolba, A. Bielman, O. Bianchi, Les femmes antiques entre sphère privée et sphère publique, Bern 2003, 137-151</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scheid J., Le statut du culte d’Isis à Rome sous le Haut-Empire, in Les Religions orientales dans le monde grec et romain: cent ans après Cumont (1906-2006), Turnhout-Bruxelles 2009, 173-186</bibl>
                    <bibl>Selter B., Astral immortality in the Carmina Latina Epigraphica of the City of Rome: a comparison between pagan and Christian views, Sacris erudiri, 45, 2006, 47-106</bibl>
                    <bibl>Serafini N., Sacrés liens ou non-liens sacrés ? Hécate, les mortels et les lieux de passage en Grèce ancienne, Euphrosyne, N.S., 43, 2015, 147-155</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sfameni C., Isis, Cybele and Other Oriental Gods in Rome in Late Antiquity: “Private” Contexts and the Role of Senatorial Aristocracy, in C. Giuffrè Scibona, A. Mastrocinque (eds), Demeter, Isis, Vesta, and Cybele : studies in Greek and Roman religion in honour of Giulia Sfameni Gasparro, Stuttgart 2012, 119-138</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sfameni Gasparro G., Soteriology and mystic aspects in the cult of Cybele and Attis, Leiden 1985</bibl>
                    <bibl>Smolak K., «Me beatam, me piam celebrant»: (Überlegungen zu CIL VI 1779), in H. Heftner, K. Tomaschitz (hrsg.), Ad fontes ! Festschrift für Gerhard Dobesch zum 65. Geburtstag am 15. September 2004, dargebracht von Kollegen, Schülern und Freunden, Wien 2004, 811-817</bibl>
                    <bibl>Swetnam-Burland M., Egypt in Italy. Visions of Egypt in Roman Imperial culture, Cambridge-New York 2015</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Haeperen Fr., Grand-prêtre ou hiérophante: les traductions grecques du terme «pontifex», AC, 73, 2004, 149-163</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Haeperen F., Prêtre(sses)s, tauroboles et mystères phrygiens, in Estienne S., Huet V., Lissarrague F., Prost F. (éd.), Figures de dieux. Construire le divin en images, Rennes 2014, 99-118</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Haeperen F., Étrangère et ancestrale. La mère des dieux dans le monde romain, Paris 2019</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vera D., Lotta politica e antagonismi religiosi nella Roma tardoantica: la vittoria sarmatica di Valentiniano II, Koinonia, 7, 1983, 133-155</bibl>
                    <bibl>Versluys M.J., Isis Capitolina and the Egyptian cults in late Republican Rome, in Isis en Occident. Actes du 2ème Colloque international sur les études isiaques, Lyon III, 16-17 mai 2002), Leiden 2004, 421-448</bibl>
                    <bibl>Versluys M.J., Aegyptiaca Romana: the widening Debate, in L. Bricault, M.J. Versluys, P.G.P. Meyboom (eds), Nile into Tiber. Egypt in the Roman World, Leiden 2007, 1-14</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vermaseren M.J., Corpus cultus Cybelae Attidisque (CCCA), III, Italia-Latium, Leiden 1977</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vidman L., Sylloge inscriptionum religionis Isiacae et Sarapiacae (SIRIS), Berlin 1969</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.2"></p>
                    <p n="1.4">father and husband of the woman to whom the monument is dedicated</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">v(iri) c(larissimi)</p>
                    <p n="8.2">praef(ecti), ex praef(ecto)</p>
                    <p n="8.4"></p>
                    <p n="8.10"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
