<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Inscription in honour of the emperor Julian from Ancyra by the praet. prefect Salutius</title>
                <editor role="edition">Andrea Bernier, Irene Vagionakis</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Irene Vagionakis</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="plre" corresp="pp. 814-817">50</idno>
                <date when="2020-05-08"/>
                <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Salutius"><name type="gentilicium">Saturninius</name>
                            <name type="cognomen">Secundus</name>
                            <name type="signum">Salutius</name></persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#Ankara">Byzantine fortification wall of Ankara, Bastion B</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#honorary">Honorary inscription for the emperor Julian</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#limestone">limestone</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>visible part of the stone 46</height>
                                        <width>59</width>
                                        <depth>unknown</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">yes; the base was built into the Byzantine fortification wall of Ankara</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One inscribed field (frons).</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#damaged">Damaged: the bottom left corner of the inscription is ruined.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#square_capitals">late Roman monumental capitals</term>
                                <height>4 / 5</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Ancyra</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Ankara (Turkey)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Galatia</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Pontica</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">public space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p6" when="0362" precision="high">362 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found">Byzantine fortification wall of <placeName ref="#">Ankara</placeName>, Bastion B</provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"></provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="la">
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1"/>Domino totius orbis
                    <lb n="2"/>Iuliano Augusto
                    <lb n="3"/>ex Oceano Bri<lb 
                        break="no" n="4"/>tannico <sic>vis</sic> per
                    <lb n="5"/>barbaras gentes
                    <lb n="6"/>strage resistenti<lb 
                        break="no" n="7"/>um patefactis adus<lb 
                            break="no" n="8"/>que Tigridem una
                    <lb n="9"/><g ref="hedera"/> aestate transvec<lb 
                        break="no" n="10"/>to, Saturninius
                    <lb n="11"/>Secundus <expan><abbr>v</abbr><ex>ir</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>c</abbr><ex>larissimus</ex></expan> <expan><abbr><unclear>praef</unclear></abbr><ex>ectus</ex></expan>
                    <lb n="12"/><expan><abbr>praet</abbr><ex>orio</ex></expan> <supplied reason="lost"><expan><abbr>d</abbr><ex>evotus</ex></expan></supplied> <expan><abbr>n</abbr><ex>umini</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>m</abbr><ex>aiestati</ex><abbr>q</abbr><ex>ue</ex></expan> <supplied reason="lost"><expan><abbr>ei</abbr><ex>us</ex></expan></supplied>.
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>Edition based on GLIA II, 332.</p>
                <p>
                    <app loc="4"><note>viis</note></app>
                    <app loc="11"><note>Secundus (Salutius): EDAK</note></app>
                    <app loc="12"><note>praet(orio Orientis): EDAK</note></app>
                    <app loc="12"><note>[d(edit)]: EDAK</note></app>
                    <app loc="12"><note>m(aiestati) [q(ue)]: EDAK</note></app></p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“To the master of the entire world Julian Augustus, who travelled from the Britannic Ocean to the Tigris in one summer, opening roads through barbarian peoples, massacring those who resisted, Saturninus Secundus, praetorian prefect of clarissimus rank, devoted to his divine spirit and majesty.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>“Au seigneur du monde entier Julien Auguste, qui a voyagé de l’Océan britannique au Tigre en un seul été, ouvrant des routes au milieu de peuples barbares, faisant des massacres de ceux qui résistaient, Saturninus Secundus, clarissime préfet du prétoire, dévoué à sa divinité et à sa majesté.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Al signore del mondo intero Giuliano Augusto, che ha viaggiato dall’Oceano Britannico fino al Tigri in una sola estate, aprendo strade in mezzo a genti barbare, facendo strage di coloro che resistevano, Saturninus Secundus, chiarissimo prefetto del pretorio, devoto al nume e alla maestà sue.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>The inscription was chiseled on a base for a statue of emperor Julian in Ancyra, and was dedicated by Saturninius Secundus (Salutius: on his name see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret52">PPRET 52</ref>), <foreign>praef(ectus) praet(orio)</foreign>. The text praises the emperor. The prefect celebrates the adventus of Julian in the East, focusing on the extraordinary speed of his movements: in just one summer he travelled from one border of the empire to another, i.e. from the shore of Britannia to the Tigris, creating new roads among the barbarian peoples along the way (on this topic, see Tantillo 2012; Mitchell-French 2019, pp. 75-78; cf. Wirbelauer-Fleer 1995; Dietz 2000; Conti 2006-2007; Salway 2012). 
                    The reaching of the Tigris (which would appear to be a precursor to the future Persian expedition) is celebrated before it was even achieved because the inscription was probably dedicated in May-June 362 AD, when the imperial <foreign>comitatus</foreign> stayed in Ancyra during its transfer from Constantinople to Antioch (<ref type="source">Amm. 22, 09, 08</ref>; see den Boeft et alii 1995). Ancyra was already a seat of a praetorian prefect in 325/327 AD (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret12">PPRET 12</ref> and <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret13">13</ref>).</p>
                <p>The passage of Julian and Salutius in the city features in the martyrdom of the priest Basil of Ancyra. According to an undated and anonymous Passion (<ref type="source">BHG 242</ref>), Basil was interrogated and condemned to death for his strong opposition to idolatry by the emperor Julian himself in the metropolis of Galatia. 
                    In this source, Basil’s trial is led by a certain Σατορνῖνος whom D. Woods (1992) proposes to identify as our praetorian prefect, although the character is qualified with the title of governor (ἡγεμών) instead of prefect (ἔπαρχος). However, a recent study has refuted the historical reliability of this text and showed how the Passion was concocted by mixing the history of ecclesiastical historians with local traditions and documents (Busine 2019; cf. Teitler 1996). In the city of Ancyra another inscription is preserved (GLIA I, 36) dedicated to a Ἰούλιος Σατορνεῖνος, styled ἡγεμών, who was the governor of the province in the 2nd Century AD and who probably gave to the anonymous hagiographer the name of the character for his Passion.</p>
                <p>Salutius was one of Julian Augustus’ most trusted officials. Their close relationship had started some years before when Salutius was sent by Constantius II to attend the young Caesar in Gaul (<ref type="source">Zos. 03, 02, 02</ref>; perhaps he was the quaestor of Julian, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret51">PPRET 51</ref>). After the death of Constantius (November 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> 361 AD), Julian immediately appointed Salutius praetorian prefect and entrusted him with the direction of the Commission of Chalcedon (<ref type="source">Amm. 22, 03, 01</ref>). We find Salutius at the Emperor’s side on the Persian expedition and, after the death of Julian, he was offered the imperial purple. But because of his advanced age, the prefect refused (for the career of Salutius in the following years see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret51">PPRET 51</ref>).</p>
                <p>According to T.D. Barnes, Salutius was an “old-style praetorian prefect”. In the years 361-363 AD, the latter acted as a deputy to the emperor and supported him in civil and military affairs (Barnes 1987; 1992; cf. Coşkun 2004; Olszaniec 2013). 
                    This interpretation is supported by the testimony of Ammianus who, while describing the beginning of the Persian expedition, styled Salutius, now on the campaign, <foreign>praefectus praesens</foreign> (<ref type="source">Amm. 23, 05, 04</ref>). Only later, during the reign of Valentinian and Valens, Salutius would become a “regional prefect” (<ref type="source">Amm. 26, 05, 05</ref>). 
                    Julian and Salutius were close friends and the importance of Salutius’ advice in the ruling of the empire is documented not only by plenty of ancient sources, but by the the emperor himself (cf. Penella 2006). Salutius also took part in the war against Sapor and fought on the field. But perhaps to consider Salutius an old-style prefect is going a bit too far. The evidence of <ref type="source">CTh 11, 39, 05</ref> shows that Salutius was not part of the Imperial Consistory, at least not in March 362 AD. 
                    The law preserves part of the proceedings that were held before Julian «at which were standing the Most Noble Jovius, Quaestor, Anatolius, Master of Offices, and Felix, Count of the Sacred Imperial Largesses. Etc.» (transl. Pharr): Salutius was not there. Given his rank, he ought to have been listed first. Ammianus’ evidence may also depend on context.
                    The historian is writing about the beginning of the campaign against the Persians: a few lines before the words <foreign>Salutius praefectus praesens</foreign> (<ref type="source">Amm. 23, 05, 06</ref>) Ammianus describes the letter that <foreign>Sallustius, Galliarum praefectus</foreign>, had sent to Julian trying to dissuade him from invading Persia (<ref type="source">Amm. 23, 05, 04</ref>). 
                    We know that the similarities in the names of the two officials, who also held the same office of praetorian prefect at the same time, caused confusion in the ancient sources (and in modern studies too, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret52">PPRET 52</ref>; <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret54">PPRET 54</ref> for Flavius Sallustius). 
                    But not in Ammianus. Probably with the words <foreign>praefectus praesens</foreign>, he simply wanted to distinguish Salutius, who joined the expedition, from Sallustius, who tried to stop it. Regional praetorian prefectures had existed since the time of Constantine (so Porena 2003). Salutius is the eastern praetorian prefect who, as always in these circumstances, accompanied Augustus in the military campaign when it took place in the area that was administered by the prefect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>CIL III, 247</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>ILS 754</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Conti 2004, nr. 20</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Tomlin 2018, nr. 14.17</ref> (with photo)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>GLIA II, 332</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.epigraphik.uni-hamburg.de/receive/skeleton_simpledoc_000960">EDAK 000960</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail-base.php?record=LSA-2846">LSA 2846</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Arce J., Estudios sobre el Emperador Fl. Cl. Juliano. Fuentes literarias. Epigrafía. Numismática, Madrid 1984, 111, 162-163, nr. 111</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barnes T.D., Regional Prefectures, in Straub J., Bonner Historia Augusta Colloquium 1984-1985, Bonn 1987, 13-23</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barnes T.D., Praetorian Prefects, 337-361, ZPE 1992, 249-260</bibl>
                    <bibl>Busine A., Basil and Basilissa at Ancyra: Local Legends, Hagiography, and Cult, GRBS, 59, 2019, 262-286</bibl>
                    <bibl>Caltabiano M., La comunità degli Elleni: cultura e potere alla corte dell’imperatore Giuliano, AntTard, 17, 2009, 137-149</bibl>
                    <bibl>Conti S., Un aspetto della propaganda imperiale tardo-antica: la titolatura di Giuliano nelle fonti letterarie ed epigrafiche, Koinonia, 30-31, 2006-2007, 29-44</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coşkun A., Die Praefecti praesent(al)es und die Regionalisierung der Praetorianerpraefecturen im vierten Jahrhundert, Millenium, 1, 2004, 279-328</bibl>
                    <bibl>De Bonfils G., Il comes et quaestor nell’età della dinastia costantiniana, Napoli 1981, 164-190</bibl>
                    <bibl>De Jerphanion G., Mélanges d’archeologie anatolienne, Beyrouth 1928, 234-235, nr. 8</bibl>
                    <bibl>Den Boeft J., Drijvers J.W., den Hengst D., Teitler H.C., Philological and Historical Commentary on Ammianus Marcellinus XXII, Groningen 1995, 148-183</bibl>
                    <bibl>Desnier J.-L., Salutius – Salustius, REA, 85, 1983, 53-65</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dietz K., Kaiser Julian in Phönizien, Chiron, 30, 2000, 807-855</bibl>
                    <bibl>Étienne R., Flavius Sallustius et Secundus Salutius, REA, 65, 1963, 104-113</bibl>
                    <bibl>García Ruiz M.P., Amiano y los juicios de Calcedonia: contradicciones y paradojas, Faventia, 29.2, 2007, 47-60</bibl>
                    <bibl>Marcone A., Giuliano, Roma 2019, 118-123</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mitchell S., French D., The Greek and Latin Inscriptions of Ankara (Ancyra). Vol. II: Late Roman, Byzantine and other texts, München 2019, 75-78 (= GLIA II, 332)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Olszianec S., Prosopographical Studies on the Court Elite in the Roman Empire (4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century AD), Toruń 2013, 356-372</bibl>
                    <bibl>Penella R., Himerius and the Praetorian Prefect Secundus Salutius, Prometheus, 32, 2006, 85-90</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Le origini della prefettura del pretorio tardoantica, Roma 2003</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rinaldi G., Sull’identificazione dell’autore del Περι θεῶν και κόσμου, Koinonia, 2, 1978, 117-152</bibl>
                    <bibl>Salway B., Words and Deeds: Julian in the Epigraphic Records, in Baker-Brian N. Tougher S. (eds.), Emperor and Author: The Writings of Julian the Apostate, Swansea 2012, 137-157</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tantillo I., Panegirici e altri ‘elogi’ nelle città tardoantiche, in «Dicere laudes»: elogio, comunicazione, creazione del consenso: atti del convegno internazionale, Cividale del Friuli, 23-25 settembre 2010, Pisa 2011, 337-357</bibl>
                    <bibl>Teitler H.C., History and Hagiography the Passio of Basil of Ancyra as a Historical Source, VChr, 50.1, 1996, 73-80</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tomlin R.S.O., Britannia Romana. Roman inscriptions and Roman Britain, Oxford 2018, 427-428</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wirbelauer E, Fleer C., Totius Orbis Augustus. Claudius Mamertinus als Praefectus Praetorio der Kaiser Julian und Valentinian, in Weinmann-Walser M. (ed.), Historische Interpretationen. Gerold Walser zum 75. Geburtstag dargebracht von Freunden, Kollegen und Schülern, Stuttgart 1995, 191-201</bibl>
                    <bibl>Woods D., The Martyrdom of the Priest Basil of Ancyra, VChr, 46.1, 1992, 31-39</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="7">
                    <p n="7.2"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">v(ir) c(larissimus)</p>
                    <p n="8.2">praef(ectus) praet(orio)</p>
                    <p n="8.5"></p>
                    <p n="8.9"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
