<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Greek verse inscription in honour of Tatianus praet. prefect from Aphrodisias by a descendant of the same name (rehabilitation)</title>
                <editor role="edition">Giordana Franceschini</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Giordana Franceschini</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="plre" corresp="pp. 876-878">91</idno>
                <date when="2021-05-14"/>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name type="praenomen">Flavius</name>
                            <name type="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name>
                            <name type="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#Aphrodisias">Findspot</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#honorary">Honorary inscription for Tatianus praetorian prefect</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#poetry">poetry (nine hexameters)</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="grc">Greek</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#marble">marble</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>122</height>
                                        <width>58</width>
                                        <depth>49</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#undamaged">The base was inscribed on one field and is 18 lines long.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#square_capitals">squared letters with serifs</term>
                                <height>3 / 4,5</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Aphrodisias</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Geyre (Turkey)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Caria</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Asiana</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">Public building (Hadrianic Baths)</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p8" notBefore="0430" notAfter="0450">430/450 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found">The inscription was found in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, in the eastern forecourt of the Hadrianic Baths, slightly North of the southern colonnade.</provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"></provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="grc">
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1-2"/>1-2 <note>Verse 1</note> τίς; πόθεν; ἐκ Λυκίης μέ<supplied reason="lost">ν</supplied>, | ἀριστεύσας δ’ ἐνὶ θώκοις | 
                    <lb n="3-4"/>3-4 <note>Verse 2</note> Τατιανὸς θεσμοῖς τε δίκης | πτολίεθρα σαώσας· <space extent="unknown" unit="character"/>| 
                    <lb n="5-6"/>5-6 <note>Verse 3</note> ἀλλά με πανδαμάτωρ χρόν<supplied reason="lost">ος</supplied> | ὤλλυεν, εἰ μὴ ἐμὸς παῖς <space extent="unknown" unit="character"/> | 
                    <lb n="7-8"/>7-8 <note>Verse 4</note> ἐξ ἐμέθεν τρίτατος καὶ | ὁμώνυμος ἔργα θ’ ὅμοιο̣<supplied reason="lost">ς</supplied>
                <lb n="9-10"/>9-10 <note>Verse 5</note> ἐκ δαπέδων ἀνελὼν <space extent="unknown" unit="character"/> | στήλης ἔπι θῆκεν ὁρᾶσ<supplied reason="lost">θαι</supplied> | 
                    <lb n="11-12"/>11-12 <note>Verse 6</note> πᾶσιν ἀρίζηλον ναέταις | ξ<supplied reason="omitted">ε</supplied>ίνοισει θ’ ὁμοίως  <space extent="unknown" unit="character"/> | 
                    <lb n="13-14"/>13-14 <note>Verse 7</note> Καρῶν ἐκ γέης ὃς ἀπήλασε | λοίγιον ἄτην  <space extent="unknown" unit="character"/> | 
                    <lb n="15-16"/>15-16 <note>Verse 8</note> τὴν δὲ δίκην μερόπε<supplied reason="omitted">σ</supplied>σιν | ὁμέστιον ὤπασ’ ἐπεῖναι | 
                    <lb n="17-18"/>17-18 <note>Verse 9</note> πεμφθεὶς ἐκ βασιλῆος <space extent="unknown" unit="character"/> | ἔθ’ ἁδομένοισιν ἀρωγός. 
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>Edition based on the text edited by Merkelbach, Stauber 1998 (SGO 01), nr. 02/09/24 and Iaph2007 5.218 (with photo)</p>
                <p>
                    <app loc="1"><note>μέν Merkelbach-Stauber 1998</note></app>
                    <app loc="4"><note>ξαώσας Iaph2007 5.218, LSA, Liverani 2015</note></app>
                    <app loc="5"><note>χρόνος Merkelbach-Stauber 1998</note></app>
                    <app loc="8"><note>τ’ὅμοιος Merkelbach 1970, Merkelbach-Stauber 1998</note></app>
                    <app loc="10"><note>στήλῃς Merkelbach 1970; στήλαις ἐπέθηκεν Livrea 1997; ἐπίθηκεν Robert 1948, AE 1949, Roueché 1989, Hedrick 2000; ὁρᾶσ<unclear>θ</unclear><supplied reason="lost">αι</supplied> Roueché 1989, Iaph2007 5.218, Agosti 2010; ὁρᾶσθ<supplied reason="lost">αι</supplied> Livrea 1997, Liverani 2015, ALA2004 37, LSA, Wueste 2019</note></app>
                    <app loc="12"><note>ξίνοισει Robert 1948, AE 1949, SEG 15, Merkelbach 1970, Roueché 1989, Hedrick 2000, ALA2004 37, Agosti 2010, Liverani 2015, LSA, Wueste 2019; ξείνοισί Livrea 1997</note></app>
                    <app loc="13"><note>γαίης Livrea 1997</note></app>
                <app loc="15"><note>μερόπεσιν Robert 1948, AE 1949, Roueché 1989, Hedrick 2000, ALA2004 37, LSA, Wueste 2019; μερόπε<supplied reason="omitted">σ</supplied>σιν Peek 1954, SEG 15; μερόπεσσιν Livrea 1997</note></app>
                    <app loc="16"><note>ὤπασε πείνᾳ Robert 1948, AE 1949, SEG 15, Livrea 1997; ὤπας ALA2004 37, Iaph2007 5.218, Liverani 2015, LSA, Wueste 2019; ποίνᾳ Merkelbach 1970; ἐπεῖνα<unclear>ι</unclear> Roueché 1989, Agosti 2010</note></app>
                    <app loc="17"><note>βασιλὴος Roueché 1989</note></app>
                    <app loc="18"><note>ἐελδομένοισιν Peek 1954, SEG 15, Merkelbach 1970</note></app>
</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Chi sono ? Da dove vengo ? Sono Tatianus, dalla Licia, che ha primeggiato sui seggi dei dignitari, e che ha salvato le città per mezzo delle leggi della Giustizia. Ma il tempo che domina tutte le cose mi avrebbe distrutto se il mio rampollo, la terza generazione dopo di me, che porta il mio nome e che mi è simile nell’agire, non mi avesse sollevato da terra e non mi avesse posto su un monumento, in modo che potessi essere visto e ammirato da tutti, abitanti del luogo e stranieri allo stesso modo; egli che allontanò la rovina fatale dalla terra dei Cari e che ha portato la Giustizia a dimorare fra i mortali, quando fu inviato dall’imperatore come difensore alle persone che ancora gioiscono.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>(based on Roueché 1989)</p>
            <p>“Who am I ? Where am I from ? I am Tatianus, from Lycia, who excelled in the seats of high officials, who saved cities through the laws of Justice. But the time which dominates all things would have destroyed me if my progeny, the third generation after me, who bears my name and who is similar to me in her deeds, had not lifted me up from the ground and placed me on a base, so that I might be seen and admired by all, local citizens and strangers alike; he who drove fatal decay away from the land of the Carians and who brought Justice to dwell among mortal men, when he was sent by the emperor as a protector to the people who still rejoice.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>“Qui suis-je ? D’où est-ce que je viens ? Je suis Tatianus, de Lycie, qui excellait dans les sièges des dignitaires, et qui a sauvé des villes grâce aux lois de la Justice. Mais le temps qui domine toutes choses m’aurait détruit si mon descendant, la troisième génération après moi, qui porte mon nom et qui me ressemble par ses actions, ne m’avait pas soulevé de terre et placé sur un monument, afin que je sois vu et admiré de tous, locaux et étrangers; lui qui a chassé les ruines fatales du pays des Cariens et qui a fait régner la Justice parmi les mortels, lorsqu’il a été envoyé par l’empereur comme défenseur du peuple qui se réjouit encore.”</p>
            <p>(German translations by Merkelbach, Stauber 1998, p. 246, and Liverani 2015, pp. 107-108)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>The inscription was found in 1905 in the ancient city of <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, <placeName>Caria</placeName> (today near the modern village of <placeName>Geyre</placeName>, <placeName>Turkey</placeName>) by G. Mendel (1873-1938), who was responsible for the french archaeological mission in <placeName>Turkey</placeName> (1904-1914). The inscription, chiselled onto the central moulded panel of a statue-base, was discovered in the southern side of the East forecourt (the so called Palaestra Court) of the <placeName>Hadrianic Baths</placeName> (on the findspot of the base see http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/ala2004/iPlans/0001/03.html; Smith 2007, fig. 42, B 42), where the monument is currently located (so <ref type="inscription">Iaph2007 5.218</ref> and <ref type="inscription">LSA 0193</ref> J. Lenaghan 2011; on the honorary statuary and inscriptions in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> and in the Hadrianic Baths, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret82">PPRET 82</ref>).</p> 
<p>The inscription was copied by A. Boulanger (1886-1958) in 1913, and his copy – and copies of other aphrodisian inscriptions transcribed in Boulanger’s notebook, yet unpublished – was offered to L. Robert (1904-1985). In 1946 Mr and Mrs Robert carried out an autopsy of the inscription at <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, and after comparing their reading with Boulanger’s transcription, the greek text was  published in 1948 in “Hellenica” IV (pp. 47-49).  However, the best autoptic edition of the inscription, complete with translation, commentary, photographs was published by Ch. Roueché (1989, pp. 63-67).</p> 
<p>The inscription is complete and consists of 9 hexameters, which in the epigraphic field are well arranged in 18 hemistichs (only in l. 15 does the last letter overhang the moulded edge). The second hemistich of each verse (at the beginning of the even-numbered lines) recedes to the right from the edge of the epigraphic field (for further information on the layout and the metric system of this type of verse inscription, see Agosti 2010; also Roueché 2006). This layout was perhaps intended to favour the reading and perhaps a loud recitation (declamation) of the epigram. According to custom, quite common in late antique Greek epigraphy, the inscription contains a monologue attributed to the statue itself, the vertibable ‘talking statue’ (on the relationship between editor, inscribed text and reader in late Greek and Latin epigraphy, cf. Liverani 2014 and 2015; concerning the difficulties of a late antique reader actually understanding the inscription, cf. Wueste 2019, pp. 238-243; regarding the popularity of Greek epigrams in the later eastern Empire, see Agosti 2019).</p>  
<p>The verse inscription is in honour of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="praenomen">Flavius</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, who held the post of praetorian prefect of the East from 388 AD and 392 AD, and who crowned his career with the ordinary consulship in 391 AD. As we shall see, in 392/393 AD <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> had his property confiscated, endured <foreign>damnatio memoriae</foreign> and was sent into exile. Relating the rise and fall of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, this inscription was aimed at rehabilitating his memory, perhaps more than fifty years after his demise (on <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, see PLRE I, pp. 876-878; for the inscritpions concerning his prefecture, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret82">PPRET 82</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret83">83</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret84">84</ref> the three from <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>; <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret85">85</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret86">86</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret87">87</ref> listing his <foreign>cursus honorum</foreign>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret88">88</ref> and <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret90">90</ref> on his prefectural activity. For the inscription in honour of his son <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName>, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret89">PPRET 89</ref>). Although our inscription from <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> does not explicitly mention the praetorian prefecture of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, it is also true that late antique metrical inscriptions in Greek do not list the single steps of a whole <foreign>cursus honorum</foreign> (on late antique epigraphic habit in <placeName>Asia Minor</placeName>, cf. Mitchell 2017, pp. 276-277). The monument was put up by a descendant with the intention of celebrating the career of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> in a high style epigram. The descendant was, in fact, the governor of <placeName>Caria</placeName> and he put up the monument in the provincial capital, <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>. For simplicity we shall refer to him as <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> iunior.</p>
                
                <p>The inscription is divided into three parts. In the first part (ll. 1-4) the text declares the identity, origin and merits of the personage being honoured, namely <persName ref="Tatianus">(<name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name>) <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, who is portrayed in the statue above the base. In the second part (ll. 5-12) the text describes the rebuilding of the honorary monument to <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> by his homonymous descendant (<persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> iunior) in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, after the original monument had been demolished at the time of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ <foreign>damnatio</foreign>. In the third part (ll. 13-18) the text celebrates the merits of the dedicator, <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (iunior) governor of <placeName>Caria</placeName>. The transition between the first and second and between the second and third parts is marked by a visible blank space on the right-hand side of lines 4 and 12.</p>
                <p></p>
                <p>The first part</p>
                <p>In l. 1, after a rhetorical question, the statue declares the identity and origin of the honoured personage, <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> the Lycian. The importance of this noble family in <placeName>Lycia</placeName> was still evident in 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century <placeName>Caria</placeName> (an explicit reference to the Lycian origin of <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> and his son can also be found in <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret89">PPRET 89</ref> and <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret90">90</ref>; a list of the literary sources citing his Lycian origin can be found in <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret87">PPRET 87</ref>, which also pertains to a monument erected in honour of the praetorian prefect from <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> in <placeName>Lycia</placeName>). The condemnation of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> and his son <persName>Proculus</persName> in 392/393 AD did not eliminate the family nor diminish its standing within the eastern aristocracy: members of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ family had close ties with the future emperor Marcianus in 422 AD, one became a prefect of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> in 450-452 AD, another formed part of a patrician embassy in 464 AD, while another obtained the ordinary consulship in 466 AD (see below; sources in PLRE II, pp. 1053-1054 and CLRE, pp. 466-467; on this family cf. Scharf 1991; Watts 2017; on the imperial aristocracy of the East cf. Cabouret 2020, pp. 41-66). It seems likely that the compression of the power of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ family (senior) to the confines of a single region (<placeName>Lycia</placeName>) after 392 AD was followed in the first half of the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century by a period of stasis. However, it would appear that after the death of emperor <persName ref="ruler">Theodosius II</persName> and the rise of <persName ref="ruler">Marcianus</persName>, they gained new ground, a bounce back that was marked by their return to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>.</p>
                
                <p>In ll. 2-4, <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> is declared to be a man who had held the highest offices and a savior of cities. With regard to <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ administration saving cities (πτολίεθρα σαώσας, l. 4), this juxtaposition effectively echoes a quote by Libanius (<ref type="source">Lib., Decl. 38, 04</ref>): τοῖς ἀριστεύουσι, παρ’ὧν ἡ σωτηρία τῇ πόλει. Libanius speaks extensively in his letters of what he believes should be the goal of a good prefect, that is to say, to be a savior for the cities he governs. The salvation of cities ought to be the desirable goal of prefects like <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, whose qualities should be guaged not only in their ability to choose the right staff for the provincial administration (cf. Tantillo 2012), but also in their political activity (see <ref type="source">Lib., Ep. 0872</ref>, <ref type="source">Lib., Ep. 0990</ref> and <ref type="source">Lib., Ep. 0992</ref>, with Pellizzari 2017, pp. 58-60, 244-250; see also Pellizzari 2011; Cassia 2016). Another inscription from <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, made by the provincial council, celebrates the praetorian prefect of the East <persName><name ref="cognomen">Anthemius</name></persName> (405-414 AD, see PLRE II, pp. 93-95) for saving the cities and the whole province (cf. Roueché 1989, nr. 36 = LSA 0224: [σ]ῴζων γὰρ ὁμοῦ δήμους τε πόλεις τε | ῥύσαο καὶ Καρῶν τάξιν ἀπολλυμένην, from the eastern Gate of the South Agora).</p>
                <p>In ll. 2-3, the periphrasis on <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ excellence in the seats of high officials alludes to a successful career spanning thirty-four years. Between 358 and 364 AD he worked as a lawyer and counselor, then from around 364 to 392 AD, he served as a high ranking official. <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ <foreign>cursus honorem</foreign> included being appointed <foreign>praeses <placeName>Thebaidos</placeName></foreign> (364-366 AD), <foreign>praefectus <placeName>Aegypti</placeName></foreign> (367-370 AD), <foreign>consularis <placeName>Syriae</placeName></foreign> (370-373?), <foreign>comes Orientis</foreign> (before 374 AD), <foreign>comes sacrarum largitionum</foreign> at court (374-380 AD), then praetorian prefect of the East (388-392 AD). In 391 AD <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> received the highest appointment of all, that of consul (CLRE, pp. 316-317) while he was still in office as praetorian prefect (in an inscription from <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> in <placeName>Lycia</placeName>, likely his homeland, his entire career is recorded in ascending order of importance from <foreign>praeses</foreign>/ἡγεμών to <foreign>praefectus praetorio</foreign>/ἔπαρχος; His career are analysed in <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret87">PPRET 87</ref>; for a synthesis of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ career, see Seeck 1906, pp. 285-288; Ensslin 1932a; PLRE I, pp. 876-878; Delmaire 1989, pp. 62-67; Petit 1994, pp. 240-243; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 394-407). In 388 AD, <persName ref="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> recalled <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> from retirement and appointed him praetorian prefect of the East (<ref type="source">Zos. 04, 45, 01</ref>). <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ policies as praetorian prefecture can be assertained from thirty-seven laws of the Theodosian Code. Furthermore, Libanius makes thirty references to him in his letters and speeches (concerning the politics of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, see Mecella 2015). In 388 AD, shortly before leaving for the campaign against the usurper <persName>Magnus Maximus</persName>, the emperor appointed <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ son, <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName>, urban prefect of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName> enjoyed an exceptionally long urban prefecture, lasting four years (388-392 AD), when the average tended to be just one to two (PLRE I, pp. 746-747 Proculus 6; see also <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret89">PPRET 89</ref>). <persName ref="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> remained in the West until July 391 AD, when he returned to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. At this point the emperor’s attitude changed radically, which takes us to the second part of the <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>’ epigram.</p>
                <p></p>
                <p>The second part</p>
                
                <p>In ll. 5-6 and 9-10, the inscription attributes to the oblivion of time the decision of <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (iunior), governor of <placeName>Caria</placeName>, to pick <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ (senior) statue up off the ground (ἐκ δαπέδων ἀνελὼν) and place it well in view on an inscribed base (στήλης ἔπι θῆκεν ὁρᾶσθαι). These neutral expressions conceal or cautiously suggest a very serious affair: the trial and conviction of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, former praetorian prefect and former consul, in 392/393 AD.</p>
                <p>About one year after <persName ref="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> returned to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> (July 391 AD), the <foreign>magister officiorum</foreign> <persName><name>Rufinus</name></persName> (PLRE I, 778-781) used administrative documents to discredit the two prefects, in the eyes of the emperor. Both father and son were removed from office and tried, it seems, for corruption or <foreign>crimen maiestatis</foreign>. Rebenich (1989) has reconstructed the chronology of events, basing his analysis on <ref type="source">Zos. 04, 52</ref> (Paschoud 1979, pp. 321-322, 449-452; Engl. transl. by Ridley 1982, p. 95), the most detailed source. Between June 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 392 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 127</ref> the last correctly dated constitution of the praetorian prefect <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>) and August 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 392 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 08, 06, 02</ref> the first constitution of his successor as praetorian prefect of the East, <persName><name>Rufinus</name></persName>), <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was suddenly deposed as praetorian prefect of the East and replaced by <persName><name>Rufinus</name></persName>. Before <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ trial began, <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName> fled. Probably in the Autumn of 392 AD (or in September ?) proceedings against <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> began: false promises induced <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (perhaps deceived by <persName><name>Rufinus</name></persName>) to persuade by letter his son to return. We are uncertain whether the proceedings against <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> were suspended. Promised safety, <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName> was persuaded to return to <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. Maybe in the Winter of 392/393 AD, <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName> was arrested and the trial against <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> resumed. His trail ended in early 393 AD with a death sentence that was commuted to exile in <placeName>Lycia</placeName> and confiscation of property (in addition to Zosimus, see <ref type="source">Eun. fr. 59 Müller = 57 Blockley</ref>). At the same time, <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName> was imprisoned and tried; in the Autumn of 393 AD, he was sentenced to death. He was executed on December 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> 393 AD at <placeName>Sykai</placeName> near <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> and his father was obliged to attend (<ref type="source">Chron. Pasch. A. 393, p. 565 Dindorf </ref>= <ref type="source">MGH AA 09, Chron. Min. 01, p. 245</ref>; Christian authors dwell on the sorrow of the fall of the pagan <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, cf. <ref type="source">Asterius, Hom. 04, 09, 01, p. 43 Datema</ref> [= PG 40, 224C-225A]; <ref type="source">Phot., Cod. 258, p. 484 Bekker</ref>. On these events, cf. Rebenich 1989, pp. 159-163; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 400-402; Mecella 2015, p. 55). Many measures issued by <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> and <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName> during their terms of office were annulled by the Emperor <persName ref="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> (<ref type="source">CTh 09, 42, 12</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 09, 42, 13</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 11, 01, 23</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 131</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 14, 17, 12</ref>, June/November 393 AD). The sudden fall of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> and <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName> and the long trials against them led to their names being erased from many inscriptions (for those of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret82">PPRET 82</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret83">83</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret84">84</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret85">85</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret86">86</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret88">88</ref>, but not on <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ inscription from <placeName>Sidyma</placeName>, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret87">PPRET 87</ref>, and <placeName>Canopus</placeName>, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret90">PPRET 90</ref>). In 396 AD, having killed the praetorian prefect Rufinus, the emperor decreed that no infamy should befall the clients of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, recruited mainly in the province of <placeName>Lycia</placeName> (<ref type="source">CTh 09, 38, 09</ref>, on August 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 396 AD, cited above, with Mecella 2015, in part. p. 58 nt. 26). Only fifty years later <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> appears to be rehabilitated in an honorary inscription from <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> (<placeName>Caria</placeName>) made by his omonymous grandson in his memory (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret91">PPRET 91</ref>). Also the name of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ son, <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName>, was restored on the base of the obelisk of <persName ref="ruler">Theodosius I</persName> in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> after having suffered a <foreign>damnatio memoriae</foreign>. The inscription from <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> suggests that besides erased inscriptions, the condemnation of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> and <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName> also involved the removal and destruction or reuse of individual monuments raised to the former praetorian prefect and probably to his son. C. Roueché (1989, p. 64) rightly points out that our epigram recalls the ‘restoration’ of a monument in honour of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, perhaps erected in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> by the city or the provincial council and then removed when the former prefect was sentenced in 393 AD at the latest (on the provincial Council of <placeName>Caria</placeName> cf. Filippini 2016). On the other hand, it seems very difficult for the expression in ll. 9-10 about the restoration of a base and a statue that had fallen to the ground to be true. Wherever the first monument to <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was erected in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, it could not have remained on the ground in a public space for long (concerning the reuse of <foreign>spolia</foreign> in late antique <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, cf. Öğüş 2018). The base and the statue erected by <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (iunior) must have been new productions, made to order and placed in the East forecourt of the <placeName>Hadrianic Baths</placeName>. To speak of the restoration of an honorary monument is incorrect. This is a new monument to replace the previous one that had been removed for political reasons, made by a descendant of the honoured personage (concerning official monuments to praetorian prefects that were removed from their public places and then put back, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret46">PPRET 46</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret48">48</ref>; the posthumous rehabilitation of a praetorian prefect condemned by <foreign>damnatio</foreign> can be found in <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret93">PPRET 93</ref>. Concerning inscriptions from <placeName>Ephesus</placeName> that deal with the restoration of statues, cf. Rendina 2020, pp. 58-59).</p>
                <p>In ll. 6-8, the inscription provides the first three important pieces of information about the identity of the author of the new monument: a) his name was <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (ὁμώνυμος); b) he was a third generation descendant of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior, the honoured man), or a third generation descendant including <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior, the honoured man), or a third generation descendant to bear that name since <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ depiction in the statue (ἐξ ἐμέθεν τρίτατος; on the third generation’s importance in the degree of Roman nobility, cf. Cabouret 2020, p. 45); c) he performed actions similar (ἔργα θ’ ὅμοιος) to those of his eponymous ancestor portrayed in the statue: it is unlikely that the actions refer to a career similar to that of the honoured personage (the senior former praetorian prefect and consul), who was indeed exceptional, while the awarder (iunior) seems only to have been the governor of <placeName>Caria</placeName> at the time the inscription was written. The similarity between the actions of the ancestor and the descendant relates to justice and effectiveness (common themes when praising governors in late antique epigraphy, see Robert 1948, cf. Hoster 1998, p. 40; on governors’ virtues in verse inscriptions, cf. Gehn 2012, pp. 243-274). These themes characterise the third part of the epigram.</p>
                <p></p>
                <p>The third part</p>
                <p>In l. 13, at the beginning of the third part (ll. 13-18), the inscription provides the fourth piece of information about the awarder, <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (iunior): he was the governor of the province of <placeName>Caria</placeName> (Καρῶν ἐκ γέης), probably when the monument to <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was dedicated in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, which was the capital of that province. As said, this part celebrates the justice (δίκη, l. 15) of the governor (a subject typical of Greek epigraphy in honour of dignitaries, see above). Recently, Rendina (2020, pp. 54-56) has noted the similarities in the structure, family links and exaltation of justice between our epigram of <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> and the epigram of <placeName>Hypaipa</placeName> in <placeName>Lydia</placeName> in honour of <persName><name ref="praenomen">Fl.</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Anthemius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Isidorus</name></persName> <foreign>proconsul <placeName>Asiae</placeName></foreign> in 405/410 AD  (PLRE II, pp. 631-633), son of the powerful praetorian prefect of the East <persName><name>Anthemius</name></persName> (PLRE II, pp. 93-95; see <ref type="inscription">IK 17.02, Ephesus 07/02, nr. 3820 </ref>= <ref type="inscription">SGO 01, 03/04/01 </ref>= <ref type="inscription">LSA 0240</ref>); the son, proconsul, imitates the qualities and style of government of his father, the praetorian prefect. But another important inscription has more striking similarities, because it was composed in the context of the posthumous rehabilitation of a praetorian prefect (of <placeName ref="Italia_Illyricum_Africa">Italy-Illyricum-Africa</placeName>) also struck by <foreign>damnatio</foreign>. An interesting parallel can thus be drawn with the inscription relating to the rehabilitation of <persName ref="Flavianus1"><name ref="praenomen">Virius</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Nicomachus</name> <name ref="cognomen">Flavianus</name></persName> senior (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret93">PPRET 93</ref>). In 431 AD, thirty-seven years after the senator’s suicide (following the battle of the Frigidus River in September 394 AD), a new monument was erected in Rome in <placeName ref="TrajanForum">Trajan’s Forum</placeName> to rehabilitate the memory of <persName ref="Flavianus1"><name ref="praenomen">Virius</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Nicomachus</name> <name ref="cognomen">Flavianus</name></persName> senior.  Again, the dedicator was a grandson of the honoured person, <persName><name ref="praenomen">Appius</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Nicomachus</name> <name ref="cognomen">Dexter</name></persName> (PLRE II, pp. 357-358), and the honorary inscription also celebrated the son of <persName ref="Flavianus"><name ref="cognomen">Flavianus</name></persName> senior, the homonymous and at that time elderly <persName><name ref="gentilicium">Nicomachus</name> <name ref="cognomen">Flavianus</name></persName> iunior (PLRE I, pp. 345-347). In <placeName>Rome</placeName>, as in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> in the first half of the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century AD, the descendants of a praetorian prefect subject to <foreign>damnatio</foreign> were deep engaged for the full public and official rehabilitation of the career of their ancestors, whose monuments had been removed. In the inscription for <placeName ref="Flavianus1"><name>Flavianus</name></placeName> senior in <placeName>Rome</placeName>, the emperor <persName ref="ruler">Valentinianus III</persName>’s letter to the senate was engraved below the honorary dedication, bestowing praise upon both <persName ref="Flavianus1"><name ref="cognomen">Flavianus</name></persName> senior and his son <persName ref="Flavianus2"><name ref="cognomen">Flavianus</name></persName> iunior. Similarly in the more modest monument in honour of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> senior at <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, the third part of the inscription also praises the descendant of the honoured personage. In these posthumous monuments created decades after the death of senators, who, for whatever reason had fallen into disgrace, their descendants associated praise for their ancestor with praise for themselves.</p>
                
                <p>Scholars do not agree on the identity of <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (iunior), governor of <placeName>Caria</placeName>, and his relationship to the <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior) honoured at <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Libanius (Ep. 899, cf. Pellizzari 2017, pp. 94-95) clearly states that the son of the (anonymous) daughter of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior, i.e. the former praetorian prefect of 388-392 AD and consul of 391 AD, later honoured in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>) was named <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, and that in 388 AD, he was a pupil of Libanius in <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. Proculus (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret89">PPRET 89</ref>) was thus not the only child of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior), since he also had a daughter and an omonymous grandson through her. A further complication is that a conspicuous number of 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century (years 450/466 AD) sources refer to a <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, but the references are never explicitly linked to each other, nor are they associable with the same man. Some scholars have ascribed all these sources to the same <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>. According to them he was the grandson of the former praetorian prefect and consul of 391 AD and also the author of the inscription from <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>. His career would be reconstructed as follows (cf. Seeck 1906, p. 288; Ensslin 1932b; PLRE II, pp. 1053-1054; Livrea 1997, p. 43; Begass 2018, pp. 238-240, nr. 198. Robert 1948, pp. 53-53 merely identifies <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, author of the <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> inscription with his grandson, son of a daughter of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> senior, when he was governor of <placeName>Caria</placeName> without indicating career and chronology).</p>
                <p>Born around 370/375 AD, in 422 AD <persName ref="Tatianus"><name>Tatianus</name></persName> (iunior) and his brother <persName>Iulius</persName> (PLRE II, p. 642) engratiated themselves with the future emperor <persName ref="ruler">Marcianus</persName>, who had fallen ill in <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> (<placeName>Lycia</placeName>), while returning from the Persian campaign. By taking care of the young officer in their homeland, the two brothers benefitted from the former’s rise to power (<ref type="source">Theoph., Chron., A.M. 5943, p. 104 De Boor</ref>; <ref type="source">Cedr., I, p. 603 Bekker</ref>; <ref type="source">Nic. Call., HE 15, 01, PG 147</ref>; <ref type="source">Zon. 13, 24, III, p. 245 Dindorf</ref>; cf. Brodka 2012). As soon as <persName ref="ruler">Marcianus</persName> ascended the throne after the death of <persName ref="ruler">Theodosius II</persName> in 450 AD, he married Pulcheria and appointed <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> urban prefect in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> (up to at least August 452 AD; the sources can be found in PLRE II, pp. 1053-1054; cf. Dagron 1974, pp. 272-273; Iulius was appointed <foreign>praeses <placeName>Lyciae</placeName></foreign>, or, according to Scharf 1991, p. 228, <foreign>praetorian prefect</foreign> of <placeName>Illyricum</placeName>). If this <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was the author of our inscription, then its <foreign>terminus ante quem</foreign> has to be 450 AD, since <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (iunior) had to be governor of <placeName>Caria</placeName> before becoming prefect of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. In this case, the expression in line 7 of the inscription of <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> (ἐξ ἐμέθεν τρίτατος) must refer to the third generation including <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior). According to these scholars, in 464/466 AD, Emperor <persName ref="ruler">Leo I</persName> sent the same <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, now promoted patrician, as an ambassador to the Vandals (<ref type="source">Prisc., fr. 31 Müller = 31 Blockley</ref>). Then, in 466 AD, according to  the western sources, he was made consul (cf. CLRE, pp. 466-467); probably around the same period the emperor <persName ref="ruler">Leo I</persName> came into conflict with Ardabur Aspar (PLRE II, pp. 164-169) over <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> and Vivianus, praetorian prefect of the East and consul of 463 AD (Candidus, p. 135 Müller = fr. 1 Blockey, from <ref type="source">Phot., Cod. 79, p. 55 Bekker</ref>). Either the consul <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> fell into disgrace, or, as Scharf argues (1991, p. 229), he was appointed consul during an embassy to the emperor <persName ref="ruler">Libius Severus</persName> in the West, only for a dispute to arise about it on his return in 466 AD.</p>
                <p>This reconstruction that recognises only one acting senator is invalidated by the biological age of this <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>: if he was a pupil of Libanius in 388 AD, then he must have been born around 375 AD. If he attained the governorship of <placeName>Caria</placeName> around the age of fifty-five/sixty and no earlier, then he must have been prefect of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> around the age of seventy-five, ambassador at eighty-five and consul around ninety.</p>
                
                <p>Other scholars have proposed more balanced reconstructions. Roueché (1989, pp. 64-66) thinks that the pupil of Libanius in 388 AD was the prefect of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> in 450-452 AD and was also the father of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> governor of <placeName>Caria</placeName>, author of the monument to <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior) in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>. The <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, awarder of the monument at <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, would be the great-grandson of the omonymous senator honoured in the Hadrianic Baths; he could, then, be the patrician and ambassador to the Vandals in 464/466 AD. Similarly Scharf (1991, pp. 226-229) agrees that the author of the monument in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> could be the great-grandson of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior), i.e. the son of the prefect of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, while the ambassador and patricius of 464/466 AD could be the former city prefect of the year 450/452 AD, who most likely was also the consul of 466 AD (appointed by the emperor <persName ref="ruler">Liberius Severus</persName> in the West). Recently, Olszaniec (2013, pp. 403-405) also opined that the son of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> prefect of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, also called <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, the great-grandson of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior), could have been governor of <placeName>Caria</placeName> and thus the man behind the monument at <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> for his great-grandfather <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="praenomen">Fl.</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>. However, Olszaniec leaves open the question of the identity of the patricius and ambassador in 464/465 AD as that of the consul of 466 AD.</p>
                <p>According to a second group of scholars, it is proposed that <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (iunior), awarder of the monument to <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior) in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> was the son of the prefect of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> and the great-grandson of the senator honoured in the <placeName>Hadrianic Baths</placeName> (the praetorian prefect of the East and consul of 391 AD). So, the expression in line 7 of the <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> inscription  (ἐξ ἐμέθεν τρίτατος) signifies that <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (iunior) was the third generation after <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior), i.e. son, grandson, great-grandson of the honoured man.</p>
                <p>The date of the inscription remains uncertain. It is possible that <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (iunior) was governor of <placeName>Caria</placeName> when his father obtained the prefecture of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> in 450 AD; he must have been at least forty to fifty years old at that time. If one assumes an eclipse of the family during the Theodosian dynasty, the appointments could not have been made by the emperor <persName ref="ruler">Marcianus</persName> before 450 AD. However, it is not impossible that <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, grandson of the consul of 391 AD, and future prefect of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, together with his brother <persName>Iulius</persName>, future praetorian prefect of <placeName>Illyricum</placeName>, and the young <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, who dedicated the monument to his great-grandfather in <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, all attained provincial governorships in <placeName>Asia Minor</placeName> before 450 AD, and that they all attained the high prefectures only in 450 AD, thanks to the new emperor, <persName ref="ruler">Marcianus</persName>. For the sake of caution, we propose to date the inscription from <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> between 430 and 450 AD. Public rehabilitation in a province devoted to the family of the former eastern praetorian prefect of 388-392 AD, <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, would have taken place at least thirty-five to forty years after the senator’s sentence (similarly for <persName ref="Flavianus1"><name ref="gentilicium">Nicomachus</name> <name ref="cognomen">Flavianus</name></persName> senior at <placeName>Rome</placeName> in 431 AD, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret93">PPRET 93</ref>).</p>
                <p>Two final notes concerning the inscription of <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Livrea (1997) thinks that in 450/452 AD the empress <persName ref="ruler">Eudocia</persName> made an allusion to one of the (pagan) Tatiani in the preface to Patricius Bishop’s Ὁμηρόκεντρα / Homerocentones (Praef. l. 19, pp. 83-86 Ludwich = pp. 1-2 Usher; cf. Usher 1997, in part. p. 314; on this literary genre cf. Polara 1990; on Eudocia, cf. now Motta 2016). In his opinion, the two Tatiani, the one honoured, the other awarder in the <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName> inscription, are well known mid 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century poets: <persName><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (iunior) would be the actual author of the verse inscription from <placeName>Aphrodisias</placeName>, continuing the tradition of the Homeric centons of his grandfather <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (senior; cf. <ref type="source">Lib., Ep. 0990</ref>), while the latter could be the author of four epigrams of the <foreign>Anthologia Graeca</foreign>, attributed to a Ευτολμίου σχολαστικοῦ ἰλλουστρίου (<ref type="source">AP 06, 086</ref>; <ref type="source">AP 07, 608</ref>; <ref type="source">AP 07, 611</ref>; <ref type="source">AP 09, 587</ref>).</p>
                <p>A problem in the reading and of interpretation in l. 16: Robert (1948) reads ὤπασε πείνᾳ, as does Livrea (1997). The latter think that a reference to “hunger” recalls the topos of justice and privation: the absolute poverty of the administrator appears to guarantee his probity. Christian sources say that <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> ended his life whilst still in disfavor and in deprivation. Indeed, Photios writes that he spent his last years as a blind beggar (<ref type="source">Phot., Cod. 258, p. 484 Bekker</ref>; cf. <ref type="source">Asterius, Hom. 04, 09, 01, p. 43 Datema</ref> [= PG 40, 224C-225A]). Merkelbach (1970) suggested that πείνᾳ stood for ποινᾷ, with the meaning of punishment. Following this interpretation the verse could be translated: “he gave justice to mortals, which is the companion of punishment”, because, according to Merkelbach, one of the most important virtues for a governor was the μισοπονηρία, i.e. hatred of evil. Peek (1954) conjectured ὤπασ’ ἐπεῖναι, which seems to be the most plausible hypothesis: “he gave justice to live among mortals”.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>Robert 1948, pp. 47-48</ref> (with photo Pl. VII) = <bibl><ref>AE 1949, 0219</ref></bibl> = <bibl><ref>BE 1949, 178</ref></bibl></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Peek 1954, pp. 217-218</ref> (limited revision of the Robert edition) = <bibl><ref>SEG 15 (1958), 0661</ref></bibl></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Merkelbach 1970, p. 132</ref> = <bibl><ref>BE 1971, 616</ref></bibl></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Roueché 1989, nr. 37</ref> (with photo Pl. X)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Livrea 1997, p. 43</ref> = <bibl><ref>BE 1998, 646</ref></bibl> = <bibl><ref>SEG 47 (1997), 1555</ref></bibl></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>SGO 01, 02/09/24</ref></bibl>
                <bibl><ref>Hedrick 2000, p. 129</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Agosti 2010, p. 81</ref> (with photo tav. 5a)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Liverani 2015, p. 107</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Wueste 2019, p. 238</ref> (with photo, Fig. 3)</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/ala2004/inscription/eAla037.html">ALA2004 37</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/iaph2007/iAph050218.html">IAph2007 5.218</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail.php?record=193">LSA 193</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://inscriptions.packhum.org/text/257612">PH 257612</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/text/856033">TM 856033</ref></bibl>
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Agosti G., Eisthesis, divisione dei versi, percezione dei cola negli epigrammi epigrafici in età tardoantica, Segno e Testo, 8, 2010, 81-82</bibl>
                    <bibl>Agosti G., Greek Epigram in Late Antiquity, in A Companion of Ancient Epigram, ed. C. Henriksén, Blackwell 2019, 597-614</bibl>
                    <bibl>Begass C., Die Senatsaristokratie des oströmischen Reiches, ca. 457-518. Prosopographische und sozialgeschichtliche Untersuchungen, München 2018</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brodka D., Priskos von Panion und Kaiser Marcian. Eine Quellenuntersuchung zu Procop. 3,4,1-11, Evagr. HE 2,1, Theoph. AM 5943 und Nic. Kall. HE 15, 1, Millennium, 9, 2012, 145-162</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cabouret B., La société de l'Empire romain d'Orient, IVe-VIe siècle, Rennes 2020</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cassia M., Una città da “curare”. Antiochia nell’epistolario di Libanio, Historikà, 4, 2016, 243-266</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dagron G., Naissance d’une capitale. Constantinople et ses institutions de 330 à 451, Paris 1974</bibl>
                    <bibl>Delmaire R., Les responsables des finances impériales au Bas-Empire romain (IVe-VIe s.). Études prosopographique, Bruxelles 1989</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ensslin W., Tatianus 3, in RE IV A 2, Stuttgart 1932a, coll. 2463-2467</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ensslin W., Tatianus 4, in RE IV A 2, Stuttgart 1932b, coll. 2467-2468</bibl>
                    <bibl>Filippini A., Fossili e contraddizioni dell’«èra costantiniana»: i dignitari del culto imperiale nella Tarda Antichità e il loro ruolo nelle ‘riforme religiose’ di Massimino Daia e Giuliano, in Kaiserkult in den Provinzen des Römischen Reiches. Organisation, Kommunikation und Repräsentation, hrsg. A. Kolb, M. Vitale, Berlin-Boston 2016, 409-475</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gehn U., Ehrenstatuen in der Spätantike. Chlamydati und togati, Wiebaden 2012</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hedrick C.W., History and Silence: Purge and Rehabilitation of Memory in Late Antiquity, Austin 2000</bibl>
                    <bibl>Horster M., Ehrungen spatantiker Statthalter, Ant Tard, 6, 1998, 37-59</bibl>
                    <bibl>Liverani P., Chi parla a chi ? Epigrafia monumentale e immagine pubblica in epoca tardoantica, Using Images in Late Antiquity, Oxford-Philadelphia 2014, 3-32</bibl>
                    <bibl>Liverani P., Spätantike Ehrenstatuen zwischen Distanz und Dialog, in Leibhafte Kunst. Statuen und kulturelle Identität, hrsg. D. Boschung, C. Vorster, W. Fink, Paderborn 2015, 93-122. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Livrea E., I due Taziani in un’iscrizione di Afrodisia, ZPE, 119, 1997, 43-49</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mecella M., L’amministrazione di Taziano e Proculo e il destino dei Lici tra Teodosio e Arcadio, in Governare e riformare l’impero al momento della sua divisione: Oriente, Occidente, Illirico Roma, 2015, 51-84</bibl>
                    <bibl>Merkelbach R., Epigramm aus Aphrodisias, ZPE, 6, 1970, 132</bibl>
                    <bibl>Merkelbach R., Stauber J., Steinepigramme aus dem griechischen Osten, I, Die Westküste Kleinasiens von Knidos bis Ilion, Stuttgart-Leipzig 1998</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mitchell S., The Christian Epigraphy of Asia Minor in Late Antiquity, in The Epigraphic Culture of Late Antiquity, Stuttgart 2017, 271-286</bibl>
                    <bibl>Motta D., Eudocia Augusta: fra leggenda, politica e religione, in Donne, istituzioni e società fra tardo antico e alto medioevo, a cura di F. Cenerini, I.G. Mastrorosa, Lecce 2016, 115-145</bibl>
                    <bibl>Öğüş E., Urban Transformations at Aphrodisias in Late Antiquity: Destruction or Intentional Preservation ?, in Reuse and Renovation in Roman Material Culture. Functions, Aesthetics, Interpretations, eds D.Y. Ng M. Swetnam-Burland, Cambridge 2018, 160-185</bibl>
                    <bibl>Olszaniec S., Prosopographical Studies on the Court Elite in the Roman Empire (4th Century AD), Toruń, 2013</bibl>
                    <bibl>Paschoud F., Zosime, Histoire nouvelle, II/2 (Livre IV), Paris 1979</bibl>
                    <bibl>Peek 1954-1955: W. Peek, Πείρατα τέχνης. Grundsätzliches und Kritisches zu neuen Büchern über griechische Epigramme. IV, Halle – Wittenberg 1954-1955</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pellizzari A., «Salvare le città»: lessico e ideologia nell’opera di Libanio, Κοινωνία, 35, 2011, 45-61</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pellizzari A., Maestro di retorica, maestro di vita. Le lettere teodosiane di Libanio di Antiochia, Roma 2017. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Petit P., Les fonctionnaires dans l’œuvre de Libanius. Analyse prosopographique, Besançon 1994</bibl>
                    <bibl>Polara G., I centoni, in Lo spazio letterario di Roma antica, III, La ricezione del testo, a cura di G. Cavallo, P. Fedeli, A. Giardina, Roma 1990, 245-275</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rebenich S., Beobachtungen zum Sturz des Tatianus und des Proculus, ZPE, 76, 1989, 153-165</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rendina S., L’inarrestabile ascesa di una famiglia orientale, in Procopio Antemio, imperatore di Roma, a cura di F. Oppedisano, Bari 2020, 45-71</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ridley R.T., Zosimus, New History. A translation with commentary, Canberra 1982</bibl>
                    <bibl>Robert L., Hellenica. Recueil d’épigraphie, de numismatique et d’antiquités grecques, IV, Epigrammes du Bas-Empire, Paris 1948</bibl>
                    <bibl>Roueché Ch., Aphrodisias in Late Antiquity, London 1989</bibl>
                    <bibl> Roueché Ch. Written Display in the Late Antique and Byzantine City, in Proceedings of the 21st International Congress of Byzantine Studies, ed. E. Jeffreys, Aldershot 2006, 235-254</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scharf R., Die Familie des Fl. Eutolmius Tatianus, ZPE, 85, 1991, 223-231</bibl>
                    <bibl>Seeck O., Die Briefe des Libanius zeitlich geördnet, Leipzig 1906</bibl>
                    <bibl>Smith R.R.R., Statue life in the Hadrianic Baths at Aphrodisias, AD 100-600: local context and historical meaning, in F.A. Bauer, C. Witschel (eds), Statuen und Statuensammlungen in der Spätantike - Funktion und Kontext (Spätantike, Frühes Christentum, Byzanz: Kunst im ersten Jahrtausend), Wiesbaden 2007, 203-236</bibl>
                <bibl>Tantillo I., “Dispensatore di governatori”: a proposito di una dedica a un prefetto del pretorio di Gortina (IC IV 323), Riv. Filol. Istr. Class., 140, 2012, 407-424</bibl>
                    <bibl>Usher M.D., Prolegomenon to the Homeric Centos, AJPh, 118, 1997, 305-321. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Watts E., The Lycians are coming: the career of Patricius, the Father of Proclus, in Proclus and his Legacy, eds D.A. Layne, D.D. Butorac, Berlin-New York 2017, 137-145</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wueste E. Managing multiple conversations:  the multileveled communication of Late Antique Honorific Monuments and Epigraphy, in Communicating through the Material in the Ancient World, eds E. Cole, A. Mandell, Rolling Hills Estates (CA) 2019, 229-251</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="2">
                    <p n="2.2"></p>
                    <p n="2.3"></p>
                    <p n="2.5"></p>
                    <p n="2.9"></p>
                    <p n="2.10">ἀριστεύσας δ’ ἐνὶ θώκοις Τατιανὸς θεσμοῖς τε δίκης πτολίεθρα ξαώσας</p>
                    <list n="2.11">
                        <item n="2.11.h"></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.5"></p>
                    <p n="8.15"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>