<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Inscription of Fabia Aconia Paulina mentioning her father, the former praet. prefect Aconius Catullinus, and her husband, the praet. prefect Praetextatus</title>
                <editor role="edition">Pierfrancesco Porena</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Irene Vagionakis</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="plre" corresp="pp. 187-188, 722-724">20</idno>
                <date when="2020-06-23"/>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Catullinus"><name type="gentilicium">Aconius</name>
                        <name type="cognomen">Catullinus</name></persName>
                    </person>
                     <person>
                        <persName ref="#Praetextatus"><name type="gentilicium">Vettius</name>
                        <name type="gentilicium">Agorius</name>
                        <name type="cognomen">Praetextatus</name></persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#lost">lost</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#honorary">honorary inscription</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#marble">marble</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>unknown</height>
                                        <width>unknown</width>
                                        <depth>unknown</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">yes</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One inscribed field (frons).</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#undamaged">At the time of its transcription the text was undamaged. The text is known only from its manuscript tradition. The transcriptions preserve different line divisions: the layout of the lines of writing is not certain.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#unknown">unknown (no images available)</term>
                                <height>unknown</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Roma</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Rome (Italy)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Urbs</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Italiciana</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Italia Illyricum Africa</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#private">private space or building</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p5" notBefore="0384" notAfter="0387">384/387 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found"><placeName ref="#Roma">Rome</placeName>, first seen in the 15th Century in the church of the Santi XII Apostoli</provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="la">
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/>Fabiae Aconiae Paulinae, <expan><abbr>c</abbr><ex>larissimae</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>f</abbr><ex>eminae</ex></expan>,
                        <lb n="2"/>filiae Aconis (?) Catullini <expan><abbr>v</abbr><ex>iri</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>c</abbr><ex>larissimi</ex></expan> ex <expan><abbr>praef</abbr><ex>ecto</ex></expan> et consule <expan><abbr>ord</abbr><ex>inario</ex></expan>,
                        <lb n="3"/>uxori Vetti Praetextati <expan><abbr>v</abbr><ex>iri</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>c</abbr><ex>larissimi</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>praef</abbr><ex>ecti</ex></expan> et consulis designati,
                        <lb n="4"/>sacratae apud Eleusinam deo Iaccho Cereri et Corae,
                        <lb n="5"/>sacratae apud Laernam deo Libero et Cereri et Corae,
                        <lb n="6"/>sacratae apud Aeginam deabus, tauroboliatae, Isiacae,
                        <lb n="7"/>hierophantriae deae Hecatae, Gra<supplied reason="omitted">ia</supplied>e co<supplied reason="omitted">n</supplied>sacraneae deae Cereris.
                    </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>Edition based on CIL. For the many variants in the transcriptions of the MSS see CIL 06, 01780 apparatus.</p>
                <p>
                    <app loc="2"><note>MSS Aconis (Aconi, MS Alciatus and MS Pighius); Aconis, Vidman 1969, Vermaseren 1977, Bricault  2005, Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018, EDR; Aconi<supplied reason="omitted" cert="low">i</supplied>, Niquet 2000; Aconi, Kahlos 2002; Aconi<supplied reason="lost">i</supplied>, Martinez-Maza 2003; Aconii, LSA; ord(inarii), Martinez-Maza 2003</note></app>
    <app loc="3"><note>praef. <supplied reason="omitted">urbi</supplied>, Niquet 2000</note></app>
    <app loc="7"><note>Graeco sacraneae, CIL; hierophantriae deae Hecatae Graec<supplied reason="lost">ae</supplied> (vel Graiae), consacraneae deae Cereris, Mommsen (CIL 06, 01780 apparatus); hierophantriae Deae Cereris Graiae, consacraneae - vel co(n)sacraneae - Deae Hecatae, Mitthof in CIL 06, p. 4759; hirophantriae, Martinez-Maza; Graecosacraneae, ILS, Vidman 1969, Vermaseren 1977, Bricault 2005, LSA; Graeco (!) <supplied reason="omitted">con</supplied>sacraneae, Niquet 2000; Hecatae Graeco, sacfraneae, Kahlos 2002; graeco sacraneae, EDR, Martinez-Maza 2003; hierophantriae deae Hecatae Grae(cae) consacraneae deae Cereris EDCS; Hecatae Grae(cae) sacraneae, Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018; concerning our reconstruction of the text on line 7 see below (Commentary)</note></app>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“To Fabia Aconia Paulina, of clarissimus rank, daughter of Aconius Catullinus, of clarissimus rank, former prefect and ordinary consul, wife of Vettius Praetextatus, of clarissimus rank, prefect and consul designate, consecrated at Eleusis to the god Iacchus, Ceres and Cora, consecrated at Lerna to the god Liber, Ceres and Cora, consecrated to the goddesses at Aegina, tauroboliate, initiate of Isis, hierophant of the goddess Hecate, united to the worship of the Greek goddess Ceres”.</p>
                <p>(other engl. transl. by Croke, Harries 1982, pp. 105-106, nr. 65 = Erhart 2002, pp. 158-159, nr. 65, with notes; by Lefkowitz, Fant 1992 2nd ed., p. 306 = Kraemer 2004, p. 372)</p>
                </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>(Bricault 2005, p. 564)</p>
                <p>“Pour Fabia Aconia Paulina, clarissime, fille du clarissime Aconius Catullinus, ancien préfet et consul ordinaire, épouse du clarissime Vettius Praetextatus, préfet et consul désigné, consacrée à Éleusis au dieu Iacchos, à Cérès et à Corè, consacrée à Lerne au dieu Liber, à Cérès et à Corè, consacrée à Égine aux déesses, tauroboliée, isiaque, hiérophante de la déesse Hécate, Graecosacranea de la déesse Cérès”.</p>
                <p> </p>
                <p>(Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018, p. 508)</p>
                <p>“À Fabia Aconia Paulina, femme clarissime, fille d’Aconius Catullinus, clarissime, ancien préfet et consul ordinaire, épouse de Vettius Praetextatus, clarissime, préfet et consul désigné, consacrée à Éleusis au dieu Iacchos, à Cérès et à Coré, consacrée à Lerne au dieu Liber, à Cérès et à Coré, consacrée aux déesses qui sont à Égine, tauroboliée, isiaque, hiérophante de la déesse Hécate Grecque, prêtresse de la déesse Cérès”.</p>
                <p>l. 7 (Porena): “admise au culte de la déesse grecque Ceres”.</p>
                <p>(other French transl.: Chastagnol 1991, 2nd ed., p. 157, nr. 41B)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Per la chiarissima Fabia Aconia Paulina, figlia del chiarissimo Aconius Catullinus, già prefetto e console ordinario, moglie del chiarissimo Vettius Praetextatus, prefetto e console designato, consacrata a Eleusi al dio Iacchos, a Cerere e a Core, consacrata a Lerna al dio Libero, a Cerere e a Core, consacrata a Egina alle dee, tauroboliata, isiaca, ierofantria della dèa Ecate, ammessa al culto della dèa Cerere greca”.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>The inscription was copied in Rome in 1424 in the Basilica dei Santi XII Apostoli on the hillside of the Quirinale by the Italian merchant and traveller Ciriaco Pizzicolli (1391-1452) (see Parma, Biblioteca Palatina, ms. Parmensis 1191, f. 93v; Rome, Biblioteca Angelica, ms. Angelicanus 430, f. 25v; concerning Pizzicolli’s visit to Rome, see Scalamonti, V. Cyriaci 55-59, pp. 46-57 Mitchell Bodnar Foss; cfr. Colin 1981, pp. 39-40, 115). The basilica was damaged in the earthquake of 1348. Perhaps the inscribed support had been reused inside the church, or perhaps it was found during the restoration work, which began in 1417 at the behest of Pope Martin V (1417-1431). The basilica was restored upon the initiative of a pope belonging to the Colonna family, who, from 1424 to 1431, often resided in the palaces surrounding the church (see Finocchi Ghersi 1992). Later, the inscription in honour of Paulina was placed in the collection of Cardinal Giuliano Della Rovere (1443-1513), who became Pope Julius II in 1503 (see S. Magister 2000, p. 48; 2002, pp. 391-400, 487-488, 504-532, especially p. 521). Since 1471 the Cardinal had the ‘commenda’ of the basilica of the Santi XII Apostoli, around which he had the palaces restored (they became the property of the Colonna family in 1513): he lived in these palaces from 1474 and placed his collection of antiquities there. We do not know why in 1508 the monument inscribed for Paulina was not transferred to the nucleus of the future Vatican Museum collection by Pope Julius II (i.e. the same Giuliano Della Rovere who became pope). No one seems to have copied the inscription when it was in the Della Rovere collection. Pizzicolli’s Latin text seems to be the only text copied by autopsy and it soon found its way into numerous epigraphic repertories and publications written by learned Renaissance humanists (see CIL 06, 1780 apparatus). The inscription may have disappeared before the transfer of the Della Rovere collection to the future Vatican Museums. It should be noted that as many as 19 of the 30 inscriptions attributed to this collection by S. Magister (2002, pp. 504-532) are lost.</p>
                <p>The text, at the time of its transcription, was undamaged, but the layout of the seven written lines of is not certain: perhaps Pizzicolli has transcribed in six lines (ll. 2-7) a Latin text that had been chiselled on twelve (cf. Mitthof in CIL 06, p. 4759). The letters of the first line containing the onomastics of the honoree appear to be larger than in the others lines.</p>
                <p>The inscription begins with the name of the honoured woman, Fabia Aconia Paulina (l.1). This is followed by the patronymic and the name of her husband: Aconius Catullinus and Vettius Agorius Praetextatus, two famous senators who both reached the highest prefectures and the consulship, both of whom were dead when the inscription was written (ll. 2-3) (see below); finally, the list of the woman’s pagan consecrations and priesthoods has been included (ll. 4-7). The name of the dedicator(s) does not appear to have been added at the end of the inscription, while the pagan cults of the devout Paulina are emphasised. The silence about the dedicator(s), the exaltation of the father and husband, both high dignitaries, and the mention of pagan cults suggest that the text was engraved on the base of a statue in honour of the woman and that the monument was located in a Roman <foreign>domus</foreign> belonging to the couple (so Niquet 2000, p. 246). F. Mitthof and H. Niquet (CIL 06, p. 4759) think that Paulina’s base may have been placed next to the large base in honour of Praetextatus, now exhibited at Palazzo Altemps in Rome (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret79">PPRET 79</ref>). It too lacks a dedicator. However, the inscription for Praetextatus seems to have been discovered in the Mattei families <foreign>horti</foreign> on the Caelian Hill, which is a mile away from the basilica of the Santi XII Apostoli on the Quirinal Hill, where Paulina’s inscription was seen and copied. That Paulina’s monument was erected in a private room is confirmed by other surviving inscriptions in honour of Praetextatus and Paulina: their funerary altar comes from the family tomb (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>); the large base exhibited at Palazzo Altemps in Rome, was seen among the ruins of the late antique <foreign>domus</foreign> on the Caelian Hill (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret79">PPRET 79</ref>). Not only does the inscription exhibited in Palazzo Massimo alle Colonne declare that the monument was located in a <foreign>domus</foreign>, it was indeed found in a residential area atop the Aventine Hill (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret80">PPRET 80</ref>, l. 10). The <foreign>tabula ansata</foreign> (<ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 01781</ref>, cf. p. 4760 = <ref type="inscription">EDR 111561</ref>) and two <foreign>fistulae</foreign> (<ref type="inscription">CIL 15, 07563</ref> = <ref type="inscription">EDR 149417</ref>), bearing Praetextatus and Paulina’s names, which were found on the Esquiline Hill in the 19th Century, almost certainly come from their urban <foreign>domus</foreign> (concerning the <foreign>domus</foreign> of Praetextatus and Paulina see Guidobaldi 1995; Kahlos 2002, p. 25; for the <foreign>domus</foreign> that was probably inherited by Paulina on the Esquiline Hill, see Ensoli 2000, pp. 279-280; Carucci 2008; concerning the inscriptions of Praetextatus and Paulina that have been found in Rome, see Niquet 2000, pp. 237-252; a probable epigraphic eulogy of Praetextatus was found in a <foreign>villa</foreign> in Tuscia, see Berti, Cecconi 1997 = <ref type="inscription">AE 1997, 0526</ref>). In 4th Century AD Rome the aristocratic wives of praetorian prefects were often celebrated by inscribed monuments both in their own homes and in those of their relatives (see the inscription in honour of Tyrrania Anicia Iuliana, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret70">PPRET 70</ref>). The adult children of Sex. Petronius Probus and Anicia Faltonia Proba celebrated both their father and mother with individual inscribed monuments in their <foreign>domus</foreign>: they had (at least) five elegant monuments built for their illustrious parents, all of which must have been erected sometime after the beginning of 395 AD (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret65">PPRET 65</ref> and <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret66">66</ref>). There are further comparisons between the epigraphy of the pagan Fabia Aconia Paulina and the christian Anicia Faltonia Proba. In similar periods (resp. 384/385 AD and 388/395 AD) the two noble women organised the funerals and epitaphs of their husbands; both were then buried in the same sarcophagus (Paulina in a cinerary urn ?) with their respective husbands. Paulina composed or commissioned the long epitaph in verse which appears on the funerary altar, that commemorates both her and her beloved husband Praetextatus (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>); Proba certainly played a role in the composition of the double epitaph of her husband Probus (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret64">PPRET 64</ref>). In the second half of the 4th Century AD women of senatorial rank had inscriptions carved and received them in the great houses and sumptuous tombs of their families in Rome.</p>
                
                <p><emph>The lady, her father and her husband</emph></p>
                <p>Fabia Aconia Paulina (or Aconia Fabia Paulina in <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side a, l. 19; or Fabia Paulina in <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 02145</ref> = <ref type="inscription">LSA 1510</ref> = <ref type="inscription">EDR 151259</ref>) was a noble lady belonging to the pagan high aristocracy of Rome. She was the daughter of Aconius Catullinus (l. 2; see PLRE I, pp. 187-188, and below); she was probably born between 320 and 328 AD if she married in 344 AD the nobleman Vettius Agorius Praetextatus, who seems to have had no other wives (l. 3; see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side a, l. 23, see Mustakallio 2021, pp. 84-85). The couple had children (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side d, l. 35), whose names we do not know, but the family onomastics are still attested in the 6th Century (see PLRE II, pp. 736-737, 848, 901-904, 908). After 40 years of what was apparently happily married bliss, in which all pagan religious activities, both public and private, were shared, in December 384 AD, Paulina solemnly celebrated  the funeral of her husband. It is not known how much longer she lived for (on the epitaph she composed, or commissioned to celebrate their marriage and the sharing of the sepulchre, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>) (concerning Paulina, see PLRE I, p. 675; Kahlos 1994 and 2002, pp. 23-27, 62, 71-78, 81-82, 146-150, 155-157; Piérart 1997; Polara 2000, pp. 110-124; Martínez-Maza 2003; Smolak 2004; Consolino 2006, pp. 118-134, 137-138; Cameron 2011, pp. 150, 153, 158, 301-307, 387, 478-480, 725; Di Luzio 2017; Massa 2018, pp. 72-74; Campedelli in print). Symmachus recalls an illness that struck her while she was at her <foreign>villa</foreign> in Baiae (<ref type="source">Symm., Ep. 01, 48</ref>). In 385 AD, immediately after the death of her husband Praetextatus, Paulina supported the decision of the chief Vestal (<foreign>Virgo Vestalis Maxima</foreign>), Coelia Concordia (PLRE I, pp. 218-219; Frei-Stolba 2003; Conti 2003, p. 217; Rüpke 2005, 02, p. 901; Lizzi Testa 2007, pp. 256-257), to erect a monument to Praetextatus in Rome on behalf of the college of the Vestal Virgins. Since the monument’s erection was a novelty that did not adhere to the <foreign>mos</foreign>, Symmachus objected to it, but his protests were in vain (<ref type="source">Symm., Ep. 02, 36</ref>, with Cecconi 2002, pp. 266-281). While the senate was petitioning the emperor Valentinianus II for monuments to be put up in honour of Praetextatus, the chief Vestal erected one herself to him in a public place. (<ref type="source">Symm., Rel. 12 and 24</ref>). Paulina thanked the chief Vestal, Concordia, dedicating a monument to her in turn, the inscription of which was found on the Esquiline hill (<ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 02145</ref> = <ref type="inscription">ILS 1261</ref> = <ref type="inscription">LSA 1510</ref> = <ref type="inscription">EDR 151259</ref>). In the same period, Jerome polemically ridiculed the claim made by the widow Paulina that her dead husband Praetextatus had ascended to the stars, stating that if the pagan senator was anywhere, he was in hell (<ref type="source">Hier., Ep. 023, 03</ref> and <ref type="source">Hier., Ep. 039, 03</ref>; for this polemic, see McRae 2021; concerning the notion of astral ascension in late antique thought, see Selter 2006). Paulina’s public glorification of her husband had clearly stirred up passions in Rome, not just with her fellow pagans, but with the Christians as well.</p>
                <p>In ll. 1-2, Pizzicolli’s transcription shows a difference between the gentilicium of the daughter Paulina, Aconia and that of her father Catullinus, Aconis, which seems to be the genitive of Aco. In 1887, R. Cagnat stated that Aco (genitive Aconis) was the family name of two men named Catullinus: the proconsul of Africa in 317/318 AD (PLRE I, p. 187 Catullinus 2, based on <ref type="inscription">CIL 08, 14453</ref>, l. 2: [procon]sulatu Aconis Cat[ullini]), who is Paulina’s grandfather, and his son, the praetorian prefect of 341 AD and consul of 349 AD, who is Paulina’s father (PLRE I, p. 187 Catullinus signo Philomatius 3, based on <ref type="inscription">CIL 02, 02635</ref>, and on Chron. 354, <ref type="source">MGH AA 09, Chron. Min. 01, p. 68</ref>: Aco Catulinus with his signum Philomatius; the possibility of Aco being a signum is of course excluded). Cagnat’s interpretation is by no means certain. The family name Aconius /-ia is attested over sixty times in Latin epigraphy, while Aco after the first name is rare. Paulina’s family name is Aconia, and it is excluded that her father might have been an Aco / Aconis, an anomalous family name without the suffix -ius (an Aco perhaps father of an Aconia in <ref type="inscription">Suppl.It. 23, 2006, p. 376, nr. 31</ref> = <ref type="inscription">AE 2007, 00503</ref>, 1st Century AD). Documents issued by the imperial chancellery use the family name Aconius for Paulina’s grandfather and father during their public offices (<ref type="source">CTh 08, 12, 02</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 06, 22, 02</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 24</ref>). In our opinion Aco must be an abbreviation of the gentilicium Aconius (so also Jacques 1986, pp. 155-156).</p>
                <p>Aconius Catullinus (PLRE I, p. 187), father of Paulina (l. 2), was praeses Gallaeciae before 338 AD, vicarius Africae at least between July 27th 338 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 15, 01, 05</ref>) and August 29th 339 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 11, 36, 04</ref>). He is attested as praetorian prefect by only one constitution, <ref type="source">CTh 08, 02, 01</ref> = <ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 31</ref>, of June 24th 341 AD. 
                    He became prefect of Rome between July 6th 342 AD and April 11th 344 AD (Chron. 354 above, see Chastagnol 1962, pp. 121-123) and ordinary consul in 349 AD (CLRE, pp. 232-233). With regard to Catullinus’s praetorian prefecture, A. Chastagnol (1968, pp. 335-336, 352) and later PLRE consider that he was the successor of Antonius Marcellinus (PLRE I, pp. 545 and 548-549) in the prefecture of Italia Illyricum Africa (Crete is a province of the prefecture of Marcellinus, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret21">PPRET 21</ref>). 
                    If Catullinus was prefect of Italia Illyricum Africa, the prefectural inscription of Traiana in honour of Constans Augustus (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret22">PPRET 22</ref>), made by three prefects, in order Antonius Marcellinus (Italia Illyricum Africa), Domitius Leontius (Oriens) and Fabius Titianus (Galliae), must be dated to between February 25th and June 24th 341 AD. 
                    According to Chastagnol and PLRE, after February 25th Titianus left the urban prefecture to become the prefect of Gaul; the prefect Catullinus, who is not among the prefect dedicators of the monument in Traiana, is attested on June 24th as praetorian prefect and would have succeeded Marcellinus. 
                    This hypothesis is weakened by two elements: Marcellinus was praetorian prefect and ordinary consul in 341 AD (CLRE, pp. 216-217) and it is unlikely that he would have been dismissed from the prefecture in the first months of his consulship; there is no anniversary of the Emperor Constans in the first half of 341 AD to justify the prefectorial monument of Traiana. 
                    As also assumed by Barnes (1987, p. 18; 1992, p. 256; Davenport 2020, pp. 226-227), Catullinus in our opinion was praetorian prefect of Gaul in 340/341 AD, before Fabius Titianus (who is first attested on June 30th 343 AD in <ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 36</ref>). Catullinus took office sometime after August 29th 339 AD, when he was still vicarius Africae; he may have been appointed praetorian prefect of Gaul by Constans after his victory over his brother Constantinus II in April 340 AD or by the latter. Catullinus later obtained the prefecture of Rome on July 6th 342 AD. 
                    At the time of the creation of the Traiana inscription in honour of emperor Constans, Catullinus had been dismissed and replaced by Titianus at the head of the prefecture of Gaul: the Traiana inscription can thus be dated to between the Summer of 341, after Catullinus’ dismissal, and the end of 342 AD. In this period, on December 25th 342 AD the <foreign>Decennalia</foreign> of Constans began, and on September 9th 341 / 342 AD, both his and his brother Constantius’ <foreign>Quinquennalia</foreign> as Augusti were celebrated.</p>
                <p>In l. 3 Paulina’s famous husband, Vettius Praetextatus, is mentioned with the gentilicium and cognomen, without the signum Agorius. The pagan senator was probably born between 310 and 320 AD, married Paulina in 344 AD, and enjoyed a long and full career, albeit a slow one. After having held the traditional magistracies of Rome in his youth, <foreign>quaestor candidatus</foreign> and <foreign>praetor urbanus</foreign>, he was <foreign>corrector Tusciae et Umbriae</foreign>, then <foreign>consularis Lusitaniae</foreign> in the decade 350/360 AD, before 362 AD. Between 362 and 364 AD, he held a long proconsulate of Achaia at the behest of the emperor Julian (Groag 1946, pp. 45-48); he became prefect of Rome between the Summer 367 and the Summer 368 AD (Chastagnol 1962, pp. 171-178), governing the city with impartiality even during the clashes between the christian supporters of Damasus and Ursinus (Kahlos 2002, pp. 115-123; Lizzi Testa 2004, pp. 159-169; Reutter 2009, pp. 31-56).
                    Fifteen years of <foreign>otium</foreign> then followed, years which were steeped in cultural and religious activity, during which he carried out numerous ambassadorships on behalf of the Senate of Rome to the courts of the emperors Valentinianus I and Gratianus. The senator and his wife became a shining model of traditional behaviour for the western aristocracy. In 383 or 384 AD, shortly before or after the assassination of the emperor Gratianus, Praetextatus was appointed praetorian prefect. 
                    Scholars believe that his prefecture was that of Italia Illyricum Africa (on the possibility that his prefecture consisted of two separate posts, see Porena 2020a, pp. 113-117 and Porena 2020b, p. 156, and see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>). In the Autumn of 384 AD Praetextatus left the praetorian prefecture and was appointed consul for the following year (CLRE, pp. 304-305), but he died suddenly in December 384 AD (the senator is remembered as the appointed consul in all inscriptions made in his honour after his death, because it was the most prestigious honour of his career; on Praetextatus and his career, see in brief Seeck 1883, pp. LXXXIII-XC; Nistler 1910; Ensslin 1954; PLRE I, pp. 722-724; Kuhoff 1997; extensively Kalhos 2002; see also <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>). 
                    His death shook the inhabitants of Rome, arousing conflicting manifestations of obsessive exaltation of the deceased, or condemnation by Christians (on Praetextatus’ death see Vera 1983, pp. 140-142, who dates the death between December 8th and 10th 384 AD; Cecconi 2002, pp. 266-281, who dates it to between October and the first half of November 384 AD; see also Kahlos 2002, pp. 151-171). The inscription in honour of Paulina lists the cults practised by the woman, but it highlights only her husband’s (and father’s) civil career, not her public priesthoods and the practice of foreign and initiatic cults, because the centre-figure of the monument is Paulina. </p>
                <p>The reconstruction of Praetextatus’ career allows us to date the inscription. The senator died as <foreign>consul designates</foreign> and the inscription remembers him thus: the terminus post quem of the base is the end of 384 AD. There are two possibilities: either Praetextatus was still alive when the inscription was prepared, i.e. between September and November 384 AD, or more likely that the inscription was made after the senator’s death, not before 385 AD. The terminus ante quem is difficult to establish, and could be placed before or after the death of the widow, Paulina. As mentioned, F. Mitthof and H. Niquet (<ref type="inscription">CIL 06, p. 4760</ref>) suggest the year 387 AD, because they deem Praetextatus’ base in Palazzo Altemps (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret79">PPRET 79</ref>), dated in February 387 AD, to be simultaneous, even though the creation of the two monuments at the same time is not certain.</p>
                <p>The reference to the prefectures (both Roman and praetorian) and to the ordinary consulship, which were held by Paulina’s father and her husband alike, underlines the equal prestige of the two families. It therefore explains why Paulina was not inferior in rank to her husband (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side d, l. 1: <foreign>[Sple]ndor parentum</foreign>). There is a well-chosen and deliberate parallelism between the synthesis of the two cursus honorum, of the father Catullinus and of the husband Praetextatus: both are remembered in the function of <foreign>praefectus</foreign>, without the specification <foreign>praetorio</foreign> or <foreign>urbi</foreign>, and of <foreign>consul ordinarius</foreign> (the first effective, the second designated). However, the offices of <foreign>praefectus</foreign> are indicated with different formulas: <foreign>ex praef(ecto)</foreign> for Catullinus, <foreign>praef(ecti)</foreign> for Praetextatus. The <foreign>ex praefectis praetorio</foreign> attested in the 4th Century inscriptions were actually prefects, not honorary ones (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret36">PPRET 36</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret37">37</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret38">38</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret39">39</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret40">40</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret41">41</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret48">48</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret55">55</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret61">61</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret73">73</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret74">74</ref>). While in Greek epigraphy the formula ἀπὸ ἐπάρχων (πραιτωρίου/-ων) only indicates that the prefectorial mandate had ended when the inscription was written (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret52">PPRET 52</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret61">61</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret73">73</ref>), in Latin epigraphy the formula “ex praefecto praetorio” is not used when the senator has simply been dismissed from the praetorian prefecture, nor when the senator has died (for inscriptions written after dismissal from the praetorian prefecture, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret10">PPRET 10</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret59">59</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret70">70</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">77</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret79">79</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret80">80</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret92">92</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret93">93</ref>; for those written after the death of the senator, see PPRET 10, 26, 64, 65, 66, 77; these texts give the title as <foreign>praefectus praetorio</foreign>). Moreover, in the inscription in honour of Paulina, the formulas <foreign>ex praef(ecto)</foreign> and <foreign>praef(ecti)</foreign> seems irrational. In our opinion, the formula “ex praefecto praetorio”, common to private and public inscriptions, seems to be used after a political crisis or an usurpation, because some senators were affected by infamy and their rank in the <foreign>ordo</foreign> dignitatum was downgraded (see above all <ref type="source">CTh 15, 14</ref>, ‘De infirmandis suo quae sub tyrannis aut barbaris gesta sunt’). Senators who had not sided with the usurpers, or who had been downgraded in the <foreign>ordo</foreign> by usurpers and had been rehabilitated in the rank obtained by the previous legitimate emperor, signalled this by inserting the indication of the legitimate praetorian prefecture they had held as “ex praefecto praetorio” (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret48">PPRET 48</ref>). Perhaps Aconius Catullinus was appointed praetorian prefect by Constantinus II, or by Constans and retained the rank after the war in April 340 AD; or, more probably, he retained his rank after the usurpation of Magnentius in 350/353 AD at the behest of Constans (in 349 AD Catullinus was consul). Preatextatus, who was appointed praetorian prefect by Gratianus before August 383 AD or shortly thereafter by Valentinianus II, died before Italy and its aristocracy were embroiled in the usurpation of Maximus (it is also possible that the inscription in honour of Paulina was engraved before Maximus invaded Italy, as <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret79">PPRET 79</ref>).</p>
                
                <p><emph>Initiations into the mysteries</emph></p>
                <p>In ll. 4-7 – more than half of the inscription – Paulina’s intense religious life is glorified.  Unlike her husband, she was excluded from the priesthood and from active participation in the public cults of the city of Rome (the exclusion was based on her sex, see Scheid 1991 and 2003; Raepsaet-Charlier 2018). However, she appears to be intimately associated with initiatic cults at the behest and under the guidance of Praetextatus, an expert in <foreign>religio</foreign> and also an initiate (see Kahlos 2002, pp. 62-90; concerning the late cults and mysteries in Rome see Alvar 2008; Cameron 2011, pp. 132-172; Sfameni 2012; Bremmer 2014, pp. 154-165). The pagan couple projects a sense of harmony and concord, while at the same time obtaining visibility and social consensus, by carrying out their religious duties together. In these mystery cult practices Praetextatus is the master and Paulina his devoted disciple (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side b, l. 4; side d, ll. 16-17; 13-17; 22-32). This constructive relationship overcomes any male/female contradictions within the religious sphere (see North 2013). The inscription from the basilica of Santi XII Apostoli and the funerary altar celebrate Paulina and proudly list her religious achievements. It should be noted that they are divided on the one hand into initiations received in Greece into Hellenic mysteries, and on the other to mysteries celebrated in Rome and linked to the Phrygian cults of the Magna Mater, Egyptian cults of Isis, Greek cults of Hecates and Demeter, which probably adhered to the Greek rite.</p>
                <p>Paulina’s first three consecrations took place during her visits to Greece and may perhaps be related to her stay in Greece from 362-364 AD. At that time Praetextatus was <foreign>proconsul Achaiae</foreign> and was engaged in the protection of cults involving night sacrifices, which had been forbidden by the emperor Valentinianus I (see <ref type="source">Zos., 04, 03, 02-03</ref>; Plassart 1926, pp. 444-446, nr. 85 = <ref type="inscription">AE 1928, 00048</ref> = <ref type="inscription">SEG 15 (1958), nr. 322</ref> = <ref type="inscription">LSA 839</ref> = <ref type="inscription">Roesch 2007, nr. 418</ref>; Himer. 51 Colonna refers to Praetextatus’ relatives who would have accompanied him to Greece, including almost certainly his wife Paulina). The inscription recalls the ancient and glorious Greek locations of those mystery cults:</p>
                <p>l. 4 sacratae apud Eleusinam deo Iaccho, Cereri et Corae (= <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side a, ll. 5-6 husband: sacratus Libero et Eleusi[ni]is; l. 20 wife: sacrata Cereri et Eleusiniis): in Eleusis, in Attica North of Athens, the mystery rites of the cycle of Demeter (= Ceres) and Persephonae (= Corae) took place, in which Roman aristocrats and emperors had been participating for centuries (see Massa 2020; su Iacchus see Jiménez San Cristóbal 2012).</p>
                <p>l. 5 sacratae apud Laernam deo Libero et Cereri et Corae: in Lerna, in Argolis immediately South of Argos, Paulina was initiated into rites for Demeter Prosymna and Dionysios Saotes. The rites commemorated the descent of the two deities into Ades to look for Persephone (daughter of Demeter) and Semele (mother of Dionysios). They were rites linked to those of Eleusis (on this set of Dionysian mysteries, see Brenner 2014, pp. 1-20 e 100-109).</p>
                <p>l. 6 sacratae apud Aeginam deabus: these mysteries took place on the island of Aegina in the Saronic Gulf (<ref type="source">Pausan. 02, 30, 02</ref>; Brenner 2014, pp. 97-99); the inscription on the frons of the funerary altar explains that the multiple (triple) deity worshipped by Paulina is Hecate (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side a, l. 21: sacrata apud Eginam Hecatae). 
                    The goddess connected the passage between the three worlds (sky, earth, underworld) and so bore therefore the Latin epithet <foreign>Trivia</foreign> and the Greek epithet Τριοδῖτις or Τριμόρφις. Hecate is represented in the figurative arts either with three bodies or three heads, but she is identified with the goddess (<foreign>deabus</foreign>) pertaining to the three levels: Selene/Luna (Moon) on the sky, Demeter or Artemis/Diana on the earth, and the chthonian Hecate in the lower world (see Serafini 2015). 
                    The rites of the triple Hecate consisted of purifications and expiations. These mysteries to which Paulina was consecrated in Aegina are different from the Hecate priesthoods performed by Praetextatus and Paulina in Rome (below l. 7). The triple nature of the cult, which multiplies the figure of the goddess, is also indicated in the poem engraved on the funerary altar (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side d, l. 28: trina secreta).</p>
                <p>Then in the last two lines the inscription lists the mystery cults to which Paulina was initiated in Rome:</p>
                <p>l. 6 tauroboliatae (= <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret79">PPRET 79</ref>, col. 1, l. 5 husband: tauroboliato; <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side a, l. 6 husband: tauroboliatus; l. 22 wife: tauroboliata; side d, ll. 26-27: tu Dindymenes Atteos qui antistitem teletis honoras taureis consors pius): the sacrifice of a bull which was linked to the cult of the Magna Mater (Cybele/Dindymene with Attis) was widely practised by the 4th Century pagan aristocracy of Rome (concerning two altars to Attis dedicated in Rome and Ostia by the former praetorian prefect Volusianus Lampadius, tauroboliatus, and on the obligation to repeat the rite every twenty years, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret36">PPRET 36</ref> and <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret40">40</ref>).
                    The cult of Cybele / Magna Mater was added the civic cults of Rome in 204 BC and the simulacrum of the goddess had a temple on the Palatine. The ritual of the taurobolium only formed part of the worship of Cybele from the 2nd Century AD onwards (the earliest known altar dates to 160 AD, <ref type="inscription">CIL 13, 01751</ref>). However, from the 4th Century AD, the taurobolium became a private ‘elitarian’ cult, reserved for members of the Roman aristocracy (concerning the taurobolium, see McLynn 1996; Van Haeperen 2014; for the cult of the Magna Mater in Rome and in the West, see Sfameni Gasparro 1985; Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018; Van Haeperen 2019).</p>
                <p>l. 6 isiacae (= <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret79">PPRET 79</ref>, col. 1, l. 7 husband: neocoro; <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side a, l. 7: neocorus): this is the only evidence of Paulina’s devotion to Isis, although Paraetextatus was νεωκόρος, the high-priest of the temple of (Isis and) Serapis in Rome (Bricault 2014a, pp. 348-349; 2018, p. 184, nt. 163). In the inscription chiselled on the funerary altar there is no mention of Paulina’s religious initiation to the cult of Isis. 
                    Probably that cult was too widespread and common and Paulina’s role not so eminent and ‘elitarian’ to be mentioned in the epitaph. The reception of Isis into the metropolis of Rome and among the Romans was contradictory: the presence of this ‘foreign and popular goddess’ in Rome and in Roman cities was extensive, both in the <foreign>domus</foreign> and in publicly accessible sanctuaries, and was nourished by exoticism and ‘Egyptomania’ (see Versluys 2007; Swetnam-Burland 2015), but the goddess remained alien to the pantheon of gods in the city of Rome (concerning the cult of Isis, see Bricault 2013; 2014b; Brenner 2014, pp. 110-125; Bonnet, Bricault, Gomez 2020; regarding the Isiac presence in Roman cities from the Republican Age to Late Antiquity, see Versluys 2004; Scheid 2009; Coarelli 2018; on the topography of this cult in the 4th Century AD city of Rome, see Ensoli 2000). 
                    The worship of Isis, a mother, protectress, and giver of life goddess, shows similarities with the Roman Ceres and Cybele, and with Hecate (the two inclined torches), whose rites are evoked in the famous diptych of the Nicomachi and Symmachi (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret92">PPRET 92</ref>). In this diptych the two priestesses who perform the rites show great affinity with Paulina’s pagan attitudes.</p>
                <p>l. 7 hierophantriae deae Hecatae (= <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret79">PPRET 79</ref>, col. 1, l. 8 husband: hierofantae; <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side a, l. 7: hierophanta; l. 22 wife: hierophantria; side d, l. 28: Hecates ministram trina secreta edoces): in Rome Paulina and her husband Praetextatus are priest and priestess of the cult of Hecate, a deity who did not belong to the pantheon of city gods (concerning hierophantes/-tria, “the who shows the sacred”, see Clinton 2004; Van Haeperen 2004).</p>
                <p>In l. 7 the text transcribed by Pizzicolli appears incorrect: GRAECO SACRANEAE does not make sense and is never attested. The integration that I have proposed (see above and below) follows and develops a suggestion of F. Mitthof and H. Niquet (see <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, p. 4759</ref>): the adjective <foreign>graecus</foreign> is superfluous for the preceding deity, Hecate, whereas it is appropriate for the following deity, Ceres; the word <foreign>sacraneus/a</foreign> does not exist, while <foreign>consecraneus</foreign> or <foreign>consacraneus/a</foreign> (in epigraphic texts) is well attested (see ThLL 04, col. 378) and indicates those who are united by participation in the same cult, even initiatory, or in a sodality, but are not the priests of that cult. 
                    Furthermore, in Paulina’s poem engraved on the back of the funerary altar (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret77">PPRET 77</ref>, side d, l. 29) she claims to be initiated by her husband into the <foreign>sacra Cererisque Graiae</foreign>: the expression on the inscription in honour of Paulina by the Basilica of Santi XII Apostoli seems to me to be identical to the expression on the altar and indicates Paulina as συνμύστης = <foreign>consecranea</foreign> of the cult of Greek Ceres, i.e. the Greek Demeter. 
                    After the list of Paulina’s initiations into Greek or foreign cults in Rome, the inscription’s author probably wanted to mention in l. 7 Paulina’s participation in the cult of Demeter in Rome, but worshipped with a Greek rite, and different from the Roman goddess Ceres (for a similar interpretation, see Fowden 1998, p. 552). It is highly plausible, therefore, that Pizzicolli interpreted the text engraved on the stone at l. 7 in a personal way, misreading the original and correct: <foreign>hierophantriae deae Hecatae</foreign>, <foreign>Graiae consacraneae deae Cereris</foreign>, and transforming the words <foreign>Graiae consacraneae</foreign> into the untenable <foreign>Graeco sacraneae</foreign>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>CIL 06, 01780</ref> (pp. 4759-4760) = <bibl><ref>CIL 06, 31930</ref></bibl> [by mistake indicated in Benevento and Ancona, <bibl><ref>CIL 09, *0223,6</ref></bibl> and <bibl><ref>CIL 09, *0641,3</ref></bibl>]</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>ILS 1260</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Duthoy 1969, p. 21, nr. 29</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Vidman 1969, p. 216, nr. 450</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Vermaseren 1977, p. 79, nr. 295</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Niquet 2000, p. 244</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Kahlos 2002, p. 223</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Martinez-Maza 2003, p. 67</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Bricault 2005, p. 564, nr. 501/0210</ref></bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>Dubosson-Sbriglione 2018, pp. 507-508, nr. 109</ref></bibl> 
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://db.edcs.eu/epigr/edcs_id.php?p_edcs_id=EDCS-18100595">EDCS 18100595</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?id_nr=EDR138111">EDR 138111</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail-base.php?record=LSA-1474">LSA 1474</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/text/570243">TM 570243</ref></bibl>
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Alvar J., Romanising Oriental Gods. Myth, Salvation, and Ethics in the Cults of Cybele, Isis and Mithras, Leiden-Boston 2008</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barnes T.D., Regional Prefectures, in Bonner Historia-Augusta-Colloquium 1984-1985, Bonn 1987, 13-23</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barnes T.D., Praetorian Prefects, 337-361, ZPE, 94, 1992, 249-260</bibl>
                    <bibl>Berti F., Cecconi G.A., Vettio Agorio Pretestato in un’epigrafe inedita dal Valdarno, Ostraka, 6, 1997, 11-21</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bonnet C., Bricault L., Gomez C. (dir.), Les mille et une vies d’Isis. La réception des divinités du cercle isiaque de la fin de l’Antiquité à nos jours, Toulouse 2020</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bremmer J.N., Initiation into the Mysteries of the Ancient World, Berlin-Boston 2014</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bricault L., Receuil des inscriptions concernant les cultes Isiaques (RICIS), II, Corpus, Paris 2005</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bricault L., Les cultes isiaques dans le monde gréco-romain, Paris 2013</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bricault L., Gens Isiaca et identité polythéiste à Rome à la fin du IVe s. ap. J.-C., in L. Bricault, M.J. Versluys, J.-L. Podvin (eds), Power, Politics and the Cults of Isis, Leiden 2014 a, 326-359</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bricault L., Isis à Rome, in Ch. Méla, F. Möri (dir.), Alexandrie la divine, I, Genève 2014 b, 452-457</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bricault L., Les prêtres isiaques du monde romain, in V. Gasparini, R. Veymiers (eds), Individuals and materials in the Greco-Roman cults of Isis: agents, images, and practices, Leiden-Boston (Mass.) 2018, 155-197</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cagnat R., Note sur le praefectus urbi qu’on appelle à tort Aconius Catullinus et sur le proconsul d’Afrique du même nom, MEFR, 7, 1887, 258-267</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cameron Al., The last Pagans of Rome, Oxford-New York 2011</bibl>
                    <bibl>Campedelli C., Der Grabaltar von Praetextatus und Paulina: eine aristokratische Liebeserklärung über den Tod hinaus, Gymnasium, in print</bibl>
                    <bibl>Carucci M., The Sette Sale Domus - A Proposal of Reading, in P.F. Biehl, J.J. Rassamakin (eds), Import and Imitation in Archeology, Langenweißbach 2008, 213-221</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cecconi G.A., Commento storico al libro II dell’epistolario di Q. Aurelio Simmaco, Pisa 2002</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chastagnol A., Les fastes de la préfecture de Rome au Bas-empire, Paris 1962</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chastagnol A., Les préfets du prétoire de Constantin, REA, 70, 1968, 321-352</bibl>
                    <bibl>Clinton K., Epiphany in the Eleusinian Mysteries, ICS, 29, 2004, 85-109</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coarelli F., Isis Capitolina e Isis Campensis. Il culto ufficiale delle divinità egiziane a Roma, in The Iseum Campense from the Roman Empire to the Modern Age. Temple, monument, lieu de mémoire, Roma 2018, 61-77</bibl>
                    <bibl>Colin J., Cyriaque d’Ancône. Le voyageur, le marchand, l’humaniste, Paris 1981</bibl>
                    <bibl>Consolino F.E., Tradizionalismo e trasgressione nell’élite senatoria romana: ritratti di signore fra la fine del IV e l’inizio del V secolo, in R. Lizzi (a cura di), Le trasformazioni delle élites in età tardoantica, Roma 2006, 65-139</bibl>
                    <bibl>Conti S., Tra integrazione ed emarginazione: le ultime Vestali, SHHA, 21, 2003, 209-222</bibl>
                    <bibl>Croke B., Harries J., Religious Conflict in Fourth-Century Rome. A documentary study, Sidney 1982</bibl>
                    <bibl>Davenport C., The dynamics of imperial government: collegiality and regionalism, in N.J. Baker-Brian, S. Tougher (eds.), The sons of Constantine, AD 337-361: in the shadows of Constantine and Julian, Palgrave 2020, 223-254</bibl>
                    <bibl>Di Luzio M., All Call Me Blessed: the Magnificat in Paulina’s Poem to Praetextatus, JLA, 10/2, 2017, 432-453</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dubosson-Sbriglione L., Le culte de la Mère des dieux dans l’Empire romain, Stuttgart 2018</bibl>
                    <bibl>Duthoy R., The Taurobolium: its evolution and terminology, Leiden 1969</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ensoli S., I santuari di Iside e Serapide a Roma e la resistenza pagana in età tardoantica, in S. Ensoli, E. La Rocca (a cura di), Aurea Roma. Dalla città pagana alla città cristiana, Roma 2000, 267-287</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ensslin W., Praetextatus 1, in RE XXII/2, Stuttgart 1954, coll. 1575-1579</bibl>
                    <bibl>Erhart V., Inscriptions on Fabia Aconia Paulina, in L.J. Churchill, P.R. Brown, J.E. Jeffrey (eds), Women writing Latin. From Roman antiquity to early modern Europe, I. Women writing Latin in Roman antiquity, late antiquity, and the early modern Christian era, New York 2002, 151-163</bibl>
                    <bibl>Finocchi Ghersi L., Le residenze dei Colonna ai Santi Apostoli, in M. Chiabò et alii (a cura di), Alle origini della nuova Roma. Martino V (1417-1431), Roma 1992, 61-75</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fowden G., Polytheist religion and philosophy, in Av. Cameron, P. Garnsey (eds.), The Cambridge Ancient History, XIII2. The Late Empire, AD 337-425, Cambridge 1998, 538-560</bibl>
                    <bibl>R. Frei-Stolba, Coelia Concordia, la dernière Grand Vierge Vestale, et la partecipation des femmes au discours politique du IVe s. apr. J.-C., in R. Frei-Stolba, A. Bielman, O. Bianchi (édd.), Les femmes antiques entre sphère privée et sphère publique, Bern 2003, 281-315</bibl>
                    <bibl>Groag E., Die Reichsbeamten von Achaia in spätrömischer Zeit, Budapest 1946</bibl>
                    <bibl>Guidobaldi F., Domus: Vettius Agorius Praetextatus, in E.M. Steinby (a cura di), Lexicon Topographicum Urbis Romae, II, Roma 1995, 164</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jacques F., L’ordine senatorio attraverso la crisi del III secolo, in A. Giadrina (a cura di), Società romana e impero tardoantico, 1, Istituzioni, ceti, economie, Roma-Bari 1986, 81-225</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jiménez San Cristóbal A.I., Iacchus in Plutarch, in L. Roig Lanzillotta, I. Muñoz Gallarte (eds), Plutarch in the religious and philosophical discourse of late antiquity, Leiden-Boston (Mass.) 2012, 125-135</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kahlos M., Fabia Aconia Paulina and the death of Praetextatus: rhetoric and ideals in Late Antiquity (CIL VI 1779), Arctos, 28, 1994, 13-25</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kahlos M., Vettius Agorius Praetextatus. A senatorial life in between, Roma 2002</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kraemer R.S., Women’s Religions in the Graeco-Roman World. A Sourcebook, Oxford 2004</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kuhoff W., s.v. Vettius Agorius Praetextatus, in Biographisch-Bibliographisches Kirchenlexikon, XII, Herzberg 1997, 1297-1309</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lefkowitz M.R., Fant M.B., Women’s life in Greece &amp; Rome. A source book in translation, London 1992 (2nd ed.)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lizzi Testa R., Senatori, popolo, papi. Il governo di Roma al tempo dei Valentiniani, Bari 2004</bibl>
                    <bibl>MacRae D., Ludibrium Paulinae: Historiography, Anti-Pagan Polemic, and Aristocratic Marriage in De excidio Hierosolymitano 2.4, JLA, 14/2, 2021, 229-256</bibl>
                    <bibl>Magister S., La collezione di antichità del cardinale Giuliano della Rovere. Anteprima di studio, Xenia Antiqua, 9, 2000, 47-50</bibl>
                    <bibl>Magister S., Arte e politica: la collezione di antichità del Cardinale Giuliano della Rovere nei palazzi ai Santi Apostoli, Atti dell’Accademia Nazionale dei Lincei, ser. IX, 14/4, 2002, 385-631</bibl>
                    <bibl>Martínez-Maza C., Devotas mistéricas en la Roma bajoimperial, Aevum, 77, 2003, 53-68</bibl>
                    <bibl>Massa F., Vettio Agorio Pretestato: aristocrazia romana, “culti orientali” e cristianesimo, in C. Bonnet, E. Sanzi (a cura di), Roma città degli dèi. La capitale dell’impero come laboratorio religioso, Roma 2018, 63-76</bibl>
                    <bibl>Massa F., Éleusis-Rome aller / retour: mobilités religieuses autour des mystères éleusiniens à l’époque impériale, in A. Bassir (dir.), Migrations et mobilité religieuse: espaces, contacts, dynamiques et interférences, Besançon 2020, 271-293</bibl>
                    <bibl>McLynn N., The Fourth-Century “taurobolium”, Phoenix, 50, 1996, 312-330</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mitchell C., Bodnar E.W., Foss C. (eds), Cyriac of Ancona: Life and Early Travels, Cambridge Mass.-London 2015</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mustakallio K., The Ties That Bind, in K. Klaiber Hersch (ed.), Cultural History of Marriage in Antiquity, New York 2021, 77-88</bibl>
                    <bibl>Niquet H., Monumenta virtutum titulique. Senatorische Selbstdarstellung im spätantiken Rom im Spiegel der epigraphischen Denkmäler, Stuttgart 2000</bibl>
                    <bibl>North J., Gender and Cult in the Roman West: Mithras, Isis, Attis, in E.A. Hemelrijk, G. Woolf (eds), Women and the Roman city in the Latin West, Leiden-Boston (Mass.) 2013, 109-127</bibl>
                    <bibl>Piérart M., Le grand-père de Symmaque, la femme de Prétextat et les prêtres d’Argos ou les derniers feux du paganisme, in D. Knoepfler (éd.), Nomen Latinum. Mélanges de langue, de littérature et de civilisation latines offerts au professeur André Schneider à l’occasion de son départ à la retraite, Genève 1997, 149-157</bibl>
                    <bibl>Plassart A., Inscriptions de Thespies, BCH, 50, 1926, 383-462</bibl>
                    <bibl>Polara G., Iscrizioni e propaganda. Il cippo tombale di Pretestato, in F.E. Consolino (a cura di), Letteratura e propaganda nell’Occidente latino da Augusto ai regni romanobarbarici, Roma 2000, 107-126</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Le iscrizioni del Pretorio di Gortyna e la carriera prefettizia di Sex. Petronius Probus, in F. Bigi, I. Tantillo (a cura di), Senatori romani nel Pretorio di Gortina. Le statue di Asclepiodotus e la politica di Graziano dopo Adrianopoli, Pisa 2020a, 87-141</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Ipotesi sull’istituzione di una prefettura del pretorio autonoma d’Illirico nel decennio 378-387, in F. Bigi, I. Tantillo (a cura di), Senatori romani nel Pretorio di Gortina. Le statue di Asclepiodotus e la politica di Graziano dopo Adrianopoli, Pisa 2020b, 143-166</bibl>
                    <bibl>Raepsaet-Charlier M.-Th., La place des femmes dans la religion romaine: marginalisation ou complémentarité ? L’apport de la théologie, in P. Pavon (ed.), Marginación y mujer en el Imperio romano (siglos I-III), Roma 2018, 201-222</bibl>
                    <bibl>Reutter U., Damasus, Bischof von Rom (366-384): Leben und Werk, Tübingen 2009</bibl>
                    <bibl>Roesch P., Les Inscriptions de Thespies, VII, Inscriptions honorifiques (première partie). Ėdition électronique mise en forme par G. Argoud, A. Schachter, G. Vottéro, Lyon 2007, https://www.hisoma.mom.fr/sites/hisoma.mom.fr/files/img/production-scientifique/IT%20VII%20%282009%29.pdf</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rüpke J., Fasti Sacerdotum. Die Mitglieder der Priesterschaften und das sakrale Funktionspersonal römischer, griechischer, orientalischer und jüdisch-christlicher Kulte in der Stadt Rom von 300 v. Chr. bis 499 n. Chr., 3 voll., Stuttgart 2005</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scheid J., D’indispensables ‘étrangères’. Les rôles religieux des femmes à Rome, in G. Duby, M. Perrot (éd.), Histoire des femmes en Occident (dir. par P. Schmitt-Pantel), I. L’Antiquité, Paris 1991, 405-437</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scheid J., Les rôles religieux des femmes à Rome. Un complément, in R. Frei-Stolba, A. Bielman, O. Bianchi, Les femmes antiques entre sphère privée et sphère publique, Bern 2003, 137-151</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scheid J., Le statut du culte d’Isis à Rome sous le Haut-Empire, in Les Religions orientales dans le monde grec et romain: cent ans après Cumont (1906-2006), Turnhout-Bruxelles 2009, 173-186</bibl>
                    <bibl>Selter B., Astral immortality in the Carmina Latina Epigraphica of the City of Rome: a comparison between pagan and Christian views, Sacris erudiri, 45, 2006, 47-106</bibl>
                    <bibl>Serafini N., Sacrés liens ou non-liens sacrés ? Hécate, les mortels et les lieux de passage en Grèce ancienne, Euphrosyne, N.S., 43, 2015, 147-155</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sfameni C., Isis, Cybele and Other Oriental Gods in Rome in Late Antiquity: “Private” Contexts and the Role of Senatorial Aristocracy, in C. Giuffrè Scibona, A. Mastrocinque (eds), Demeter, Isis, Vesta, and Cybele : studies in Greek and Roman religion in honour of Giulia Sfameni Gasparro, Stuttgart 2012, 119-138</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sfameni Gasparro G., Soteriology and mystic aspects in the cult of Cybele and Attis, Leiden 1985</bibl>
                    <bibl>Smolak K., «Me beatam, me piam celebrant»: (Überlegungen zu CIL VI 1779), in H. Heftner, K. Tomaschitz (hrsg.), Ad fontes ! Festschrift für Gerhard Dobesch zum 65. Geburtstag am 15. September 2004, dargebracht von Kollegen, Schülern und Freunden, Wien 2004, 811-817</bibl>
                    <bibl>Swetnam-Burland M., Egypt in Italy. Visions of Egypt in Roman Imperial culture, Cambridge-New York 2015</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Haeperen Fr., Grand-prêtre ou hiérophante: les traductions grecques du terme «pontifex», AC, 73, 2004, 149-163</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Haeperen F., Prêtre(sses)s, tauroboles et mystères phrygiens, in Estienne S., Huet V., Lissarrague F., Prost F. (éd.), Figures de dieux. Construire le divin en images, Rennes 2014, 99-118</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Haeperen F., Étrangère et ancestrale. La mère des dieux dans le monde romain, Paris 2019</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vera D., Lotta politica e antagonismi religiosi nella Roma tardoantica: la vittoria sarmatica di Valentiniano II, Koinonia, 7, 1983, 133-155</bibl>
                    <bibl>Versluys M.J., Isis Capitolina and the Egyptian cults in late Republican Rome, in Isis en Occident. Actes du 2ème Colloque international sur les études isiaques, Lyon III, 16-17 mai 2002), Leiden 2004, 421-448</bibl>
                    <bibl>Versluys M.J., Aegyptiaca Romana: the widening Debate, in L. Bricault, M.J. Versluys, P.G.P. Meyboom (eds), Nile into Tiber. Egypt in the Roman World, Leiden 2007, 1-14</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vermaseren M.J., Corpus cultus Cybelae Attidisque (CCCA), III, Italia-Latium, Leiden 1977</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vidman L., Sylloge inscriptionum religionis Isiacae et Sarapiacae (SIRIS), Berlin 1969</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.2"></p>
                    <p n="1.4">father and husband of the woman to whom the monument is dedicated</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">v(iri) c(larissimi)</p>
                    <p n="8.2">praef(ecti), ex praef(ecto)</p>
                    <p n="8.4"></p>
                    <p n="8.10"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
