<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Inscription in honour of Valentinianus II, Theodosius I, Arcadius, Honorius from Antinoupolis by Tatianus praet. praefect</title>
                <editor role="edition">Giordana Franceschini</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Giordana Franceschini</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="plre" corresp="p. 876">86</idno>
                <date when="2020-03-27"/>
                <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name type="praenomen">Flavius</name>
                            <name type="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name>
                            <name type="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#Alexandria">Alexandria Museum</repository>
                        <idno type="invNo">inv. 21783; displayed in the Museum garden</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#honorary">Honorary inscription</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="grc">Greek</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#marble">red granite</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>139</height>
                                        <width>91</width>
                                        <depth>71</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">yes</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">yes</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>The inscription is chiselled on a reused monument: it is located on the back of the base; on the front face there is an earlier inscription dedicated to Antinous, dating to 130/140 AD (Bernand 1984, pp. 57-62, nr 2).</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#undamaged">Our inscription is complete and has 11 lines. The name of the awarder was deliberately erased (lines 6-7).</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#lunate">lunate letters with serifs</term>
                                <height>not recorded</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Antinoupolis</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">El Sheikh ‘Abadah, district of Mallawi (Egypt)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Thebais</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Aegyptus</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#unknown">Unknown</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p8" notBefore="0388" notAfter="0392">388/392 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found"><placeName ref="#">Antinoupolis</placeName></provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"></provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="grc">
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/>Τοὺς τῆς ὑφ’ ἡλίῳ γῆς αὐτοκρά<lb 
                            break="no" n="2"/>τορας καὶ τροπαιούχους δεσπότας 
                        <lb n="3"/>ἡμῶν, Οὐαλεντινιανόν, Θεοδόσιον, 
                        <lb n="4"/>Ἀρκάδιον, τοὺς αἰωνίους Αὐγούσ<lb 
                            break="no" n="5"/>τους, καὶ Φλάυιον Ὁνώριον, τὸν 
                        <lb n="6"/>ἐπιφανέστατον, <del rend="erasure"><expan><abbr><unclear>Φ</unclear>λ</abbr><ex>άυιος</ex></expan> Εὐτόλμιος</del>
                        <lb n="7"/><unclear>Τα</unclear><supplied reason="lost">τιαν</supplied><unclear>ός</unclear>, ὁ λαμπρότατος ἔπαρχος
                        <lb n="8"/>τοῦ ἱεροῦ πραιτωρίου, τῇ συνήθει 
                        <lb n="9"/>καθοσιώσει <expan><abbr>ἀφιέρωσε</abbr><ex>ν</ex></expan>, ἐπὶ Φλαυίου 
                        <lb n="10"/>Σεπτιμίου Εὐτροπίου τοῦ λαμπροτάτου
                        <lb n="11"/>ἡγεμόνος.
                    </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>This edition follows the text edited by LSA and Bernand 1984.</p>
            <p>
                    <app loc="6"><note>Φλ.: ILS 8809; OGIS II, 723; Wescher 1899</note></app>
                    <app loc="7"><note>Τατιανὸς: ILS 8809; OGIS II, 723</note></app>
                <app loc="9"><note>ἀφοσιωσει: Wescher 1899 read this word as the future indicative active 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> singular from ἀφοσιόω, which can be translated with “he will consecrate”.</note></app>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Agli imperatori della Terra sotto il sole, trionfanti, i nostri signori Valentinianus, Teodosius, Arcadius, perpetui Augusti, e Flavius Honorius, nobilissimo, il chiarissimo Flavius Eutolmius Tatianus, prefetto del sacro praetorio, realizzò con la consueta devozione, quando era governatore (di Tebaide) il chiarissimo Flavius Septimius Eutropius.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“To the emperors of the Earth under the sun, triumphant, our masters Valentinianus, Theodosius, Arcadius, the eternal Augusti, and Flavius Honorius, the most noble, Flavius Eutolmius Tatianus, of clarissimus rank, prefect of the sacred praetorium, set this up with the customary devotion, when Flavius Septimius Eutropius was governor (of Thebais) of clarissimus rank.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>“Aux empereurs de la Terre sous le soleil, triomphateurs, nos seigneurs Valentinianus, Theodosius, Arcadius, Augustes perpétuels, et Flavius Honorius, le très noble, Flavius Eutolmius Tatianus, clarissime préfet du prétoire sacré, a réalisé avec la dévotion habituelle, quand il était gouverneur clarissime Flavius Septimius Eutropius.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>The inscription is on a statue base in honour of Valentinianus II, Theodosius I, Arcadius and Honorius emperors and it was found in the ancient city of Antinoupolis, today el Sheikh ‘Abadah in Egypt. Initially, the monument was brought to the Cairo Museum (nr. 9274) (Dittemberg in OGIS II) and then transferred to the Alexandria Museum (nr. 21783), in 1925. 
                    Today, it is displayed in the Museum garden (Bernand 1984, p. 57; LSA 876). Our inscription is on the back of a large statue base, the front face of which retains an earlier dedication to Antinous (130/40 AD) (Bernand 1984 pp. 57-62, nr. 2; Wescher 1866, pp. 150-153). Th. Kraus (1962, p. 131) pointed out that «on the top there are foot-holes of an over life-size bronze statue, which must belong to the first use, since they point towards the first-use side» (cf. U. Gehn, LSA 876).</p>
                <p>The text is 11 lines long and has been deliberately erased on lines 6 and 7, where the awarder Flavius Eutolmius Tatianus (PLRE I, p. 876) was mentioned. He was a distinguished pagan, who held the eastern praetorian prefecture in 388-392 AD (see also <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret85">PPRET 85</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret88">88</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret90">90</ref>), falling from power in 392 AD. 
                    He suffered <foreign>damnatio memoriae</foreign> and banishment to Lycia. He was rehabilitated posthumously by his grandson at Aphrodisias in Caria (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret91">PPRET 91</ref>). His whole career is recorded in ascending order of importance from <foreign>praeses</foreign> (ἡγεμών) to <foreign>praefectus</foreign>  (ἔπαρχος) in a long inscription from Sidyma (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret87">PPRET 87</ref>).
                    During his prefecture, Tatianus was also involved in erecting honorary inscriptions on behalf of the imperial college (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret82">PPRET 82</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret83">83</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret84">84</ref>) in Aphrodisias (Caria) and in Side (Pamphylia) which is a ‘twin’ inscription of our Egyptian one (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret85">PPRET 85</ref>). 
                    Just as in our inscription the prefect uses the formula τῇ συνήθει καθοσιώσει, which probably alludes to pagan rites that accompanied the dedication and which must have been chosen by him, since it appears in Aphrodisias as well as in Egypt.</p>
                <p>Since our base can only have supported one statue, it has must been one of a group of bases with similar dedications.</p>
                <p>The inscription was set up during the mandate of the governor of the Thebais, Flavius Septimius Eutropius (PLRE I, p. 318), recorded as governor in a papyrus dated to 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December 389 AD. Since his predecessor, Flavius Eutolmius Arsenius (PLRE I, p. 111), was in office in June 388 AD and his successor, Flavius Asclepiades Hesychius (PLRE I, p. 429), in September 390 AD, our inscription has to date to 388/390 AD.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>Wenscher 1866</ref>, pp. 150-155</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>OGIS II, 723</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>ILS 8809</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>SB V, 8919</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Bernand 1984, nr. 19</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail.php?record=876">LSA 876</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://inscriptions.packhum.org/text/219137">PH 219137</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Barnes T.D., The victims of Rufinus, CQ 34, 1984, 227-230</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bernand A., Les Portes du désert. Recueil des inscriptions grecques d’Antinooupolis, Tentyris, Koptos, Apollonopolis Parva et Apollonopolis Magna, Paris 1984, nr. 19</bibl>
                    <bibl>Collignon M., Notes sur les fouilles executées à Aphrodisias par M. Paul Gaudin, CRAI 1904, 703-711</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cuvigny H., Τρισαυγούστιον et φραγέλλιον. Contrôle de qualité et mesurage du grain fiscal au IVe s. apr. J.-C. à la lumière de P.Mich. XX 800 et de l’inscription tardive du grenier d’Andriakè, Chiron 47, 2017, 95-114</bibl>
                    <bibl>Errington R., A note on the Augustal Prefect of Egypt, Tyche 17, 2002, 69-77</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grégoire H., Miettes d’histoire byzantine (IVe-VIe siècle), Anatolian Studies presented to Sir William Mitchell Ramsay, Manchester-London-New York, 1923, 151-164</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grégoire H., Quand est né l’empereur Théodose II ?, Byzantion 4, 1927-1928, 337-348</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kraus, Th., Die Basis des Epistrategen Fidus Aquila aus Antinoopolis, MDAI(R) 69, 1962, 128-135</bibl>
                    <bibl>Livrea E., I due Taziani in un’iscrizione di Afrodisia, ZPE 119, 1997, 43-49</bibl>
                    <bibl>Manganaro G., Due note tardoantiche, ZPE 94, 1992, 283-294</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mecella M., L’amministrazione di Taziano e Proculo e il destino dei Lici tra Teodosio e Arcadio, in Governare e riformare l’impero al momento della sua divisione: Oriente, Occidente, Illirico Roma, 2015</bibl>
                    <bibl>Milne J., Greek inscriptions (Catalogue Général du Musée du Caire), Oxford 1905,nr. 16</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pellizzari A., «Salvare le città»: lessico e ideologia nell’opera di Libanio, Κοινωνία 35, 2011, 45-61</bibl>
                    <bibl>Petit P., Les fonctionnaires dans l’œuvre de Libanius. Analyse prosopographique, Besançon 1994</bibl>
                    <bibl>Reinach T., Inscriptions d’Aphrodisias, REG 19, 1906, 79-150, 205-298</bibl>
                    <bibl>Robert L., Hellenica. Recueil d’épigraphie, de numismatique et d’antiquités grecques, IV, in Epigrammes du Bas-Empire 4, Paris 1948</bibl>
                    <bibl>Roueché C., Aphrodisias in Late Antiquity London 1989</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scharf R., Die Familie des Fl. Eutolmius Tatianus, ZPE 85, 1991, 223-231</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wescher C., Notice sur les inscriptions grecques du piédestal d’Antinoé et du monument d’Athribis en Egypte, Bullettino dell’Instituto di Corrispondenza Archeologica 38, 1866, 150-155</bibl>
                    <bibl>Woods D., Tatianus and the Basilica of Menas, Byzantion 65, 1995, 467-474</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"></p>
                </div>
                <div type="commentary" n="7">
                    <p n="7.2"></p>
                    <p n="7.y"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">λαμπρότατος</p>
                    <p n="8.2">ὁ λαμπρότατος ἔπαρχος τοῦ ἱεροῦ πραιτωρίου</p>
                    <p n="8.5"></p>
                    <p n="8.9"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>