<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Inscription commemorating the works on the Canopus canal (Egypt) carried out by the will of Tatianus praet. prefect</title>
                <editor role="edition">Giordana Franceschini</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Giordana Franceschini</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="new">90</idno>
                <date when="2021-05-14"/>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Tatianus"><name type="praenomen">Flavius</name>
                            <name type="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name>
                            <name type="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#unknown">Unknown</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#building">Building inscription, commemorating the works carried out by the will of the praetorian prefect Flavius Eutolmius Tatianus on the Canopus canal.</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">Prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="grc">Greek</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#marble">White marble</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">Statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>ca. 60</height>
                                        <width>ca. 45</width>
                                        <depth>ca. 11</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">yes (pavement of a muslim tomb)</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#fragmentary">The inscription is carved on one field. It consists of 9 lines and is fragmentary: the right side of the epigraphic field is lost. The inscribed slab was reused by being inserted into the floor of a muslim saint’s tomb (Sonnini 1799).</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#unknown">unknown</term>
                                <height>unknown</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Canopus</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Abukir (Egypt)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Aegyptus</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Aegyptus</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">Public space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p8" notBefore="0388" notAfter="0390">388/390 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found">Near <placeName>Aboukir (Egypt)</placeName>, embedded in the stone floor of a Muslim saint’s tomb (Sonnini 1799, p. 112)</provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"></provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="grc">
                 <div type="textpart" subtype="face" n="frons">
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1"/><supplied reason="lost">Σπουδῇ</supplied> <expan><abbr>Φλ</abbr><ex>αύιου</ex></expan> Εὐτολ<supplied reason="lost">μίου Τατιανοῦ τοῦ <expan><abbr>λαμ</abbr><ex>προτάτου</ex></expan> καὶ ὑπάρχον</supplied><lb break="no" 
                        n="2"/> τος <expan><abbr>ἐπάρχ</abbr><ex>ου</ex></expan> τοῦ ἱε<supplied reason="lost">ροῦ πραιτωρίου, ἀπὸ ἐπάρχων τῆς</supplied>
                        <lb n="3"/>Αἰγυπτιακῆς διοι<supplied reason="lost">κήσεως, ὁ ποταμὸς ἐκκεκάθα</supplied><lb 
                            break="no" n="4"/><expan><ex>ρ</ex><abbr>ται</abbr></expan> ἀπὸ θεμελί<supplied reason="lost">ων ἐπὶ τὰ γʹ στερεά</supplied>,
                        <lb n="5"/>βάθους <expan><abbr>πήχ</abbr><ex>εων</ex></expan> δέκα, <supplied reason="lost">πλάτους <expan><abbr>πήχ</abbr><ex>εων</ex></expan> ἐννέ</supplied><lb break="no" 
                            n="6"/>α, μήκους <expan><abbr>πήχ</abbr><ex>εων</ex></expan> δι<supplied reason="lost">σχιλίων, τουτῷ τῷ ἔργῳ ἐπικείμενου</supplied>
                        <lb n="7"/><expan><abbr>Π</abbr><ex>ουβλίου</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>Ἀρρ</abbr><ex>ίου</ex></expan> Ἀλεξάνδρου, <supplied reason="lost">τοῦ <expan><abbr>περι</abbr><ex>βλέπτου</ex></expan> κόμητος πρώ</supplied><lb break="no" 
                            n="8"/> του τάγματος καὶ <supplied reason="lost">αὐγουσταλίου πάσης τῆς Αἰ</supplied><lb break="no" 
                            n="9"/> γυπτιακῆς διοι<supplied reason="lost">κήσεως</supplied>.
                </ab>
                 </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>Edition based on Bernand 1970, p. 341.</p>
                <p>
                    <app loc="1"><note><supplied reason="lost">ἐπί</supplied> CIG, SB</note></app>
                    <app loc="2"><note> ἱθ Sonnini; τος <expan><abbr>ἐπάρχ</abbr><ex>ου</ex></expan> τοῦ ἱθ <supplied reason="lost">τάγματος τῆς</supplied> CIG, SB</note></app>
                    <app loc="1-2"><note><expan><abbr>Φλ</abbr><ex>αούιος</ex></expan> Εὐτόλ[μιος Τατιανὸς <expan><abbr>λαμπρ</abbr><ex>ότατος</ex></expan> ἔπαρχ<supplied reason="lost">ος</supplied> τοῦ ἱ<supplied reason="lost">εροῦ πραιτωρίου</supplied> Wescher 1866 p. 155; <supplied reason="lost">Σπουδῇ</supplied> <expan><abbr>Φλ</abbr><ex>αύιου</ex></expan> Εὐτολ<supplied reason="lost">μίου Τατιανοῦ τοῦ <expan><abbr>λαμ</abbr><ex>προτάτου</ex></expan> καὶ ὑπάρχον</supplied>|τος <expan><abbr>ἐπάρχ</abbr><ex>ου</ex></expan> τοῦ ἱε<supplied reason="lost">ροῦ πραιτωρίου, ἀπὸ ἐπάρχων τῆς</supplied> Kubitscheck 1918, p. 69</note></app>
                    <app loc="3"><note>Αἰγυπτιακῆς διοι<supplied reason="lost">κήσεως τὸ τεῖχος ? οἱ</supplied>: CIG; SB; Αἰγυπτιακῆς διοι[κήσεως αἵδε αι Kubitscheck 1918, p. 69</note></app>
                    <app loc="4"><note>αγαι Sonnini; αται CIG, SB; <supplied reason="lost">ῷκοδόμησαν</supplied> CIG, SB; ἀπὸ θεμελί[ων ἐκτίσθησαν Kubitscheck 1918, p. 69</note></app>
                    <app loc="5"><note>δεκλ Sonnini; <supplied reason="lost">ὕψους <expan><abbr>πηχ</abbr><ex>εων</ex></expan></supplied> CIG, SB; <supplied reason="lost">πλάτους <expan><abbr>πήχ</abbr><ex>εων</ex></expan> ... ἐννέ</supplied>|α Kubitscheck 1918, p. 69</note></app>
                    <app loc="6"><note>δι<supplied reason="lost">ακουςίων ? σπουδῇ</supplied> CIG, SB; δι<supplied reason="lost">ακοσίων ἐπικείμενου τουτῷ τῷ ἔργῳ</supplied> or δι<supplied reason="lost">ακοσίων πράττοντος τοῦτο τὸ ἔργον</supplied> Kubitscheck 1918, p. 69</note></app>
                <app loc="7-8"><note><supplied reason="lost">τοῦ αὐ</supplied>|τοῦ τάγματος καὶ CIG, SB; <supplied reason="lost">τοῦ περιβλέπτου κόμητος πρώ</supplied>|του Kubitscheck 1918, p. 69</note></app>
                    <app loc="8-9"><note><supplied reason="lost">αὐγουσταλίου πάσης τῆς Αἰ</supplied>|γυπτιακῆς διοι<supplied reason="lost">κήσεως</supplied> Kubitscheck 1918, p. 69</note></app>
</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Grazie allo zelo di Flavius Eutolmius Tatianus, chiarissimo prefetto del sacro pretorio, ex prefetto della diocesi d’Egitto, il canale è stato ripulito fin dalle fondazioni, nelle tre dimensioni, per dieci cubiti in profondità (m. 5,25), per nove cubiti in larghezza (m. 4,72), per duemila cubiti in lunghezza (m. 1040), sotto la supervisione di Publius Arrius Alexander, spettabile conte del primo ordine e prefetto Augustale dell’intera diocesi di Egitto”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“Thanks to the zeal of Flavius Eutolmius Tatianus, of clarissimus rank, prefect of the sacred praetorium, ex prefect of the diocese of Egypt, the canal has been dredged from the foundations, in three dimensions, for ten cubits in depth (m. 5,25), for nine cubits in width (m. 4,72), for two thousand cubits in length (m. 1040), under the supervision of Publius Arrius Alexander, spectabilis count of the first order and prefect Augustalis of the entire diocese of Egypt”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>(Bernand 1970, pp. 341-342)</p>
            <p>“Par la bienveillance de Flavius Eutolmius Tatianus, le clarissime, qui est préfet du saint prétoire, ex-gouverneur du diocèse d’Égypte, le canal se trouve curé depuis les fondations, dans les trois dimensions, sur dix coudées (5 m., 25) de profondeur, neuf coudées (4 m., 72) de largeur, deux mille coudées (1040 m.) de longueur, sous la direction de Publius Arrius Alexander, illustre comte du premier rang et préfet augustal de tout le diocèse d’Égypte”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>The text was engraved on a fragment of a white marble slab, which was found near <placeName>Aboukir</placeName> or <placeName>Abu Qir</placeName> (<placeName>Egypt</placeName>, 13 Km North-West of <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>; Hairy, Sennoune 2006, p. 276, fig. 1; ancient topography cf. Barrington Atlas 74 C 2). It was found by the French naturalist Charles-Nicolas-Sigisbert Sonnini de Manoncourt (1751-1812) in 1778, during his two-year journey through Ottoman Egypt (Sonnini 1799, p. 112; cf. Bernand 1970, p. 340; Hairy, Sennoune 2006, p. 262). The slab was reused as a part of the pavement of a muslim saint’s tomb, the precise location of which is no longer known. By following the indications provided by the discoverer in Voyage dans la Haute et la Basse Egypte (Sonnini 1799, p. 112), Bernand (1970, pp. 343-344) believes that the tomb may have been located on the road connecting <placeName>Abukir</placeName> to <placeName>Kérioun</placeName>, that is to say, between ancient <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> and <placeName>Chaireon</placeName>/<placeName>Schedia</placeName>. Sonnini (1799) also relates that his companion, a Bedouin sheikh named Hussein, felt few scruples about pulling the inscription up from the tomb’s pavement, nor selling it to him. He states that the slab was stolen, so it is lost and we have no information about its current location. In his edition, Sonnini provides the reader with a description of the slab, which appears to be missing the entirety of its right side; he also furnishes a transcription, French translation and notes. Despite thanking J.B. Gail, professor of Greek literature at the ‘College de France’ in 1792 for his help, both the reading and the interpretation are full of mistakes.</p>
<p>The inscription reveals a gap of five-letters in the first line, as described by Sonnini (1799): «La moitié de la première ligne était effacée; le reste était bien conservé, mais les caractères en étaient assez mal formés». In fact, the text is fragmentary and all the right side of the epigraphic field is lost. Some attempts have been made to re-establish the missing part. After Sonnini’s transcription, the text was published in 1853 by J. Franz in <ref type="inscription">CIG 03, 4693</ref>, with a capitalized transcription, a lower case transcription and a small Latin commentary. A little later, C. Wescher (1866, p. 155) reconstructed the first two lines, basing his interpretation on the text chiselled on the statue base from <placeName>Antinoupolis</placeName> (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret86">PPRET 86</ref>), upon which <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> is also mentioned. Thanks to Wescher, the name of the praetorian prefect <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, partially illegible, was restored in the first line of the <placeName>Canopus</placeName> inscription. This was achieved by comparing the <placeName>Canopus</placeName> inscription with the inscription of <placeName>Antinoupolis</placeName> in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, that was similar and featured <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="praenomen">Fl.</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret86">PPRET 86</ref>). W. Kubitschek (1918, p. 69), in his important study on the inscription from <placeName ref="Myra">Myra</placeName> (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret88">PPRET 88</ref>), which also mentions the prefect <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, has produced the best integration of the missing part of the inscription from <placeName>Canopus</placeName>. In 1950 E. Kiessling (SB 05, 8295) published Franz’s 1853 text, without taking into account the restorations of Wescher and Kubitschek, much to Robert’s chagrin (Robert in <ref type="inscription">BE 1952, p. 187, nr. 178</ref>). Bernand (1970, pp. 340-346) provides the main edition of our inscription.</p>
<p>The Greek inscription commemorates the repairs carried out on the <placeName>Canopus</placeName> canal between 388 and 390 AD. The works were supervised by <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="praenomen">Fl.</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>, the praetorian prefect of the East between 388 and 392 AD (on <persName ref="Tatuanus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> see PLRE I, pp. 876-878 and below; his inscritpions: <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret82">PPRET 82</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret83">83</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret84">84</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret85">85</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret86">86</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret87">87</ref> with analysis of his career, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret88">88</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret91">91</ref>). The inscription can be dated through the reference to <persName><name ref="praenomen">Publius</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Arrius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Alexander</name></persName>, who actually supervised the restoration of the canal near <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>. He was <foreign>praefectus Augustalis</foreign> under <persName ref="ruler">Theodosius I</persName>, from the Autumn of 388 to March 390 AD (his titulature is cited in <ref type="source">CTh 13, 05, 18</ref> on February 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 390 AD, and in <ref type="source">CJ 10, 40, 08</ref> on March 01<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 390 AD; cf. PLRE I, p. 42; Seeck 1906, p. 54; Vandersleyen 1962, pp. 22 nr. 57 and 179; Lallemand 1964, p. 70; Agostini 2019, pp. 291-292. His successor <persName><name>Evagrius</name></persName> [PLRE I, p. 286] he is reported to have taken office on June 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 391 AD, <ref type="source">CTh 16,  10, 11</ref>). Libanius attests that <persName><name>Alexander</name></persName> was highly esteemed by <persName ref="Tatianus"><name>Tatianus</name></persName> (<ref type="source">Lib., Ep. 871</ref> and <ref type="source">Lib., Ep. 882</ref>). The time of <persName><name>Alexander</name></persName>’s prefecture over the Aegyptian dioecesis overlaps with <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ prefectural career, who, as said, was praetorian prefect of the East from 388 to 392 AD.</p>
<p>The text observed by Sonnini does not clarify the specific type of work the prefect was meant to be supervising. Franz (1853) conjectures that it could be the construction of walls or fortifications and that the missing part of the text might have referred of a τεῖχος (l. 3). Kubitschek (1918) believes it could have been the construction of a pier, while Lallemand (1964) suspects that it might have been a building. However, Bernand (1970) is inclined to consider the possibility of hydraulic works upon a canal, for three reasons: 1) we are not aware of fortification works or walls in the area from which the inscription comes; 2) the dimensions provided by the inscription are not compatible with those of walls or buildings; the three dimensions mentioned in the inscription are suitable for the size of a channel; 3) <persName><name ref="praenomen">P.</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Arrius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Alexander</name></persName> appears in an honorary epigram on a white marble stone found in 1897 near the canal Maḥmūdiyya at Hagar el Nawatieh (Botti, 1901, 540, nr. 11; Bernand 1969, nr. 124; Bernand 1970, pp. 335-336, nr. 5; cf. Hairy, Sennoune 2006, pp. 261-262), which commemorates his responsability for the Alexandrian canal: “Je suis le prix des travaux du vaillant Alexandre, témoignage du canal qu’il a fait curer au prix de tant de peines, afin que les bateaux transportent facilement leur cargaison, sans qu’elle ait à souffrir” (transl. Bernand 1970). The works were probably intended to keep the canal that connected the Canopic branch of the Nile delta to the city of <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> navigable. Finally, Bernand (1970) concludes by assuming that the inscription of Hagar el-Nawatieh (which only mentions the supervision of <persName><name ref="praenomen">P.</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Arrius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Alexander</name></persName>) and <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ inscription, mark the beginning and the end of the works undertaken on the <placeName>Canopus</placeName> canal in 388-390 AD.</p>
<p>Furthermore Bernand (1970) also states that ἀπὸ θεμελίων (l. 4), which generally indicates the foundations of a building, takes up the final lines of the inscription from Schèdia, <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>’s port on the Canopian Nile (cf. Bernand 1970, pp. 334-335; on the excavation at Schèdia, under the direction of M. Bergmann and M. Heinzelmann, see http://www.schedia.de). Two inscriptions from Schèdia mention the works carried out on the Philagrianos River under the reigns of <persName ref="ruler">Titus</persName> and <persName>Domitian</persName> (<ref type="inscription">OGIS 672</ref> = <ref type="inscription">IGR 01, 1098</ref> = <ref type="inscription">SB 05, 8902</ref> = <ref type="inscription">Bernand 1970, p. 412, nr. 10, on 80/81 AD</ref>; <ref type="inscription">OGIS 673</ref> = <ref type="inscription">IGR 01, 1099</ref> = <ref type="inscription">SB 05, 8903</ref> = Bernand 1970, p. 412, nr. 11, on 86/87 AD, cf. Hairy, Sennoune 2006, p. 261). Bernand (1970, pp. 332-333) also points out that canal bottoms were generally covered with stone slabs. In the Schèdia inscription a further distinction is made between the slabs covering the bottom and those covering and supporting the walls. The fragment on which <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ inscription from <placeName>Canopus</placeName> was engraved could therefore be one of the stone slabs referred to on the steles of Schèdia, the use of which may have continued until the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century and could have had the purpose of commemorating the works carried out in the canal.</p>
<p><persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> completed different works on <placeName>Egypt</placeName>’s infrastructure that also left a trace in the late literary sources and papyri for a very long time. In the eighth-century <foreign>Excerpta Latina Barbari</foreign> – a Latin translation of a Greek 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century world chronicle, likely compiled in <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, also called the Barbarus Scaligeri – at year 375 this entry was inserted: <foreign>Hic</foreign> (= <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>) <foreign>condidit in </foreign><placeName ref="Alexandria"><foreign>Alexandria</foreign></placeName> <foreign>fluvium qui vocatur </foreign>‘<foreign><persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName></foreign>’ <foreign>et portas fecit auro perfusas</foreign>, <foreign>quae nunc dicuntur Petrinae</foreign> (<ref type="source">MGH AA 09, Chron. Min. 01, p. 296</ref>). The date is certaily wrong, because on 375 AD <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was <foreign>comes sacrarum largitionum</foreign> at <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> (see below), but during one of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ tenures over <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, the senator did carry out work on the canals in the metropolis. Still in the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century AD, a papyrus receipt from <placeName>Hermopolis</placeName> mentions a toponym near <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> called “<persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ Doors” (Πυλῶν Τατιανοῦ, in P. Cairo Masp. 67168, ll. 81 and 85). In the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century AD, John the Coptic Bishop of Nikiû in the Nile Delta (635-690 AD) states that: “a man named <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was appointed prefect of <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, which is the chief city of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>. And he built, in the place called <placeName>Abrâkjûn</placeName>, the two stone gates with enormous labour and he made these gates for the passage of the great river, and he fortified the country of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>” (<ref type="source">Chron. 83, 20</ref>, transl. Charles 1916, p. 84).</p>
<p><placeName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></placeName> completed important road and river connections between <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> and the Delta region. The Roman administration was well aware of the relationship between the Nile floods and the fertility of its valley and paid the phenomenon very special attention. Since the visible traces of the canal’s old course are no longer visible, our inscription constitutes an important testimony to its existence and the maintenance works carried out upon it. For centuries the canal had not only supplied the city and other nearby agglomorations (<placeName>Taposiris Magna</placeName>, <placeName>Plinthine</placeName>) with water, it had also allowed the transport of goods, favouring agricultural development in these territories (see Parcak 2010; Pellacani 2012; McCormick 2013; above all Blouin 2014). It is difficult to say whether these works were carried out when <placeName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></placeName> was praetorian prefect (388-392 AD) or whether some of them were executed during one of his previous assignments in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> (364/370 AD). This aspect calls for a brief reflection on his career.</p>
<p>The <placeName>Canopus</placeName> inscription celebrates <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> as acting praetorian prefect (of the East, ll. 1-2), when the canal works were carried out, but also records his previous assignment as prefect of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> (ll. 2-3). <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> held three positions in which <placeName>Egypt</placeName> fell within his jurisdiction. He was <foreign>praeses <placeName>Thebaidos</placeName></foreign> in 364-366 AD, <foreign>praefectus Aegypti</foreign> in 367-370 AD, and after being <foreign>consularis <placeName>Syriae</placeName></foreign>, he was <foreign>comes Orientis</foreign> in 370-373 AD, when <foreign>Egypt</foreign> was not yet an independent diocese and the <foreign>comes Orientis</foreign> was also the <foreign>vicarius</foreign> of the praetorian prefects for the Nile Valley (then, after becoming <foreign>comes sacrarum largitionum</foreign> in 374-380 AD, <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was appointed praetorian prefect of the East in 388 AD. On <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ career, cf. Seeck 1906, pp. 285-288; Ensslin 1932; PLRE I, pp. 876-878; Delmaire 1989, pp. 62-67; Petit 1994, pp. 240-243; Olszaniec 2013, pp. 394-407; see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret87">PPRET 87</ref>).</p>
<p>In the <placeName>Canopus</placeName> inscription, <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="praenomen">Fl.</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> is referred to as <supplied reason="lost">ἀπὸ ἐπάρχων τῆς</supplied> Αἰγυπτιακῆς διοι<supplied reason="lost">κήσεως</supplied> (ll. 2-3). Unfortunately, the lacuna in the right-hand side of the epigraphic field deprives us of the valuable indication regarding the position held by <placeName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></placeName> (in 367-370 AD) and by <persName><name>Alexander</name></persName> (in 388-390 AD). The sources suggest that <placeName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></placeName> was <foreign>praefectus</foreign> (ἔπαρχος) and that <persName><name ref="gentilicium">Arrius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Alexander</name></persName> was <foreign>Augustalis</foreign> (αὐγουστάλιος). Concerning <placeName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></placeName>’ appointment in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> (367-370 AD), the contemporary sources  always refer to him as ἔπαρχος Αἰγύπτου (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret87">PPRET 87</ref>). Later in the <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> inscription (dated to 391/400 AD), where the complete <foreign>cursus honorum</foreign> of <placeName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></placeName> is preserved, his second assignment in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> is expressed with the phrase “he obtained power over all <placeName>Egypt</placeName>” (ἀρχήν λάχεν ... Αἰγύπτου πάσης). In the inscription of <placeName>Canopus</placeName> (dated to 388/390 AD) both the prefect <placeName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></placeName> and the <foreign>Augustalis</foreign> <persName><name>Alexander</name></persName> are administrating a dioecesis (Αἰγυπτιακῆς διοικήσεως, ll. 2-3 and 8-9). When the inscriptions of <placeName>Canopus</placeName> and <placeName>Sidyma</placeName> were chiselled post 388 AD, the diocese of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and the <foreign>praefectus Augustalis</foreign> had already existed for some time. Scholars conjecture whether in 367-370 AD <placeName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></placeName> was already vicar of an independent dioecesis, separate from the East, or whether he was given some special assignment before the creation of a separate Aegyptian diocese. Could <placeName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></placeName> have been the first <foreign>praefectus Augustalis</foreign>, or did the Aegyptian dioecesis that he had been given bear a different title from those that came later? Do the terms Αἰγύπτου πάσης (“all <placeName>Egypt</placeName>” in <placeName>Sidyma)</placeName>, and Αἰγυπτιακῆς διοικήσεως (“the diocese of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>” in <placeName>Canopus</placeName>) already indicate a diocese, or do they only refer to an extended province of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> within the ancient and much larger diocese of Oriens. The office held by <placeName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></placeName> in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> has been the focus of a debate (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret87">PPRET 87</ref>, commentary to line 6). The sources allow us to date the birth of the independent diocese of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> entrusted to the new diocesan <foreign>vicarius</foreign> called <foreign>praefectus Augustalis</foreign> between March 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 380 and July 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 381 AD. The reform, promoted by <persName ref="ruler">Theodosius I</persName>, seems to have reinforced the administration of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> during the Gothic crisis in <placeName>Illyricum</placeName>. A constitution issued on March 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 383 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 97</ref>) is the first explicit evidence of the existence of the diocese of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, created as an administrative area separate from the diocese of Oriens. The studies of Palme (1998), Errington (2002, p. 76) and Mratscheck (2012, p. 263), plead for an expansion of the province of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> in the 370’s. The redefinement of the bounderies involved the incorporation of  Heptanomia and the entire Delta, but with the reduction of the province of <placeName>Augustamnica</placeName>. These transformations under-pinned the institution of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> as an independent diocese in 380/382 AD, controlled by its new diocesan governor, the <foreign>praefectus Augustalis</foreign>. To conclude, although the <placeName>Canopus</placeName> inscription is incomplete, according to the reconstructions of Errington (2002, pp. 76-77), Mratschek (2012, pp. 262-264), Olszaniec (2013, pp. 396-397), it seems likely that <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> – defined here as <supplied reason="lost">ἀπὸ ἐπάρχων τῆς</supplied> Αἰγυπτιακῆς διοι<supplied reason="lost">κήσεως</supplied> (ll. 2-3) – was at that point only the former prefect of the enlarged province of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, administered by him in 367-370 AD. He was thus, not the first <foreign>vicarius</foreign> (called <foreign>praefectus Augustalis</foreign>) of the new independent dioecesis of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, while <persName><name ref="praenomen">P.</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Arrius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Alexander</name></persName> referred to as <supplied reason="lost">αὐγουσταλίου πάσης τῆς Αἰ</supplied>γυπτιακῆς διοι<supplied reason="lost">κήσεως</supplied> (ll. 8-9) was the <foreign>praefectus Augustalis</foreign> of the independent diocese of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> in the years 388-390 AD.</p>
            <p>When <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was prefect of (the enlarged) <placeName>Egypt</placeName> and thus responsable for the Nile delta, it is possible that major infrastructure works for <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> were undertaken at that time (367-370 AD) and were completed in the following twenty years. It seems that several governors of the provinces and diocese of <placeName>Egypt</placeName> were clients supported by <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> in the 370’s and 380’s AD. It is thus likely that <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>' building projects in <placeName>Egypt</placeName> were also supported by other administrators in this period. <persName><name ref="gentilicium">Arrius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Alexander</name></persName> was highly esteemed by <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> (above), while <persName><name ref="praenomen">Flavius</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Ulpius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Erythrius</name></persName> (PLRE I, pp. 283-284; Agostini 2019, pp. 289-291) <foreign>praeses <placeName>Thebaidos</placeName></foreign> in 384-385 AD, then <foreign>praefectus Augustalis</foreign> in 388, seems to be related to <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>. As for <persName><name ref="praenomen">Flavius</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Eutolmius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Arsenius</name></persName>, <foreign>praeses <placeName>Thebaidos</placeName></foreign> in 388 AD, he too was a relative (PLRE I, p. 111; Agostini 2019, pp. 381-382; Scharf 1991). <persName><name ref="praenomen">Fl.</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Septimius</name> <name ref="cognomen">Eutropius</name></persName> <foreign>praeses <placeName>Thebaidos</placeName></foreign> in 389 AD (PLRE I, p. 318; Agostini 2019, pp. 382-383) and <persName><name ref="praenomen">Fl.</name> <name ref="gentilicium">Asclepiades</name> <name ref="cognomen">Hesychius</name></persName>, <foreign>praeses <placeName>Thebaidos</placeName></foreign> 390-392 (PLRE I, p. 429; Agostini 2019, pp. 383-386) were also <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ clients (concerning <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> strong client base, for the most part recruited in <placeName>Lycia</placeName>, cf. <ref type="source">CTh 09, 38, 09</ref>, on August 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 396 AD). Perhaps the reference in the <placeName>Canopus</placeName> inscription to <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ previous assignment in <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, when he was by then praetorian prefect, demonstrates that the works on the <placeName>Canopus</placeName> canal were the completion of other works undertaken by <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> and his clients in and around <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> and its delta.</p>
<p>The complicated network of connections in the administration perhaps explains why the name of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was not removed from the <placeName>Canopus</placeName> inscription. In the Spring/Summer 392 AD, <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was removed from the praetorian prefecture and was put on trial; at the end of a long trial he was sentenced to death, but the punishment was commuted to banishement, confiscation of his property and the <foreign>damnatio memoriae</foreign> (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret87">PPRET 87</ref> and <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret91">91</ref>). His son <persName><name>Proculus</name></persName> (cf. PLRE I, pp. 746-747), was also condemned and was executed near <placeName>Constantinople</placeName> in December 393 AD (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret89">PPRET 89</ref>). This fall from grace caused <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ name to be erased from many inscriptions (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret82">PPRET 82</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret83">83</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret84">84</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret85">85</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret86">86</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret88">88</ref>), but not at <placeName>Canopus</placeName> (in the inscription from <placeName>Antinoupolis</placeName> in honour of the emperors <persName ref="ruler">Valentinianus II</persName>, <persName ref="ruler">Theodosius I</persName>, <persName ref="ruler">Arcadius</persName> and <persName ref="ruler">Honorius</persName> the name of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> was erased, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret86">PPRET 86</ref>). Probably the location of the inscription outside <placeName ref="Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>, along the <placeName>Canopus</placeName> Cannal, the benefits that <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName>’ works had brought to the inhabitants and the positive memory that people still had of him (still referred to in 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Century sources) preserved his name from erasure. That being said, in the imperial inscription inside the city of <placeName>Antinoupolis</placeName> (<placeName>Thebais</placeName>) the name of <persName ref="Tatianus"><name ref="cognomen">Tatianus</name></persName> had to be deleted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>Sonnini 1799, pp. 112-116</ref> (with fac-simile)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>CIG 03, 4693</ref> (with diplomatic transcription)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Kubitscheck 1918, p. 69</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>SB 05 (1950), 8295</ref></bibl>
                <bibl><ref>Bernand 1970, p. 341</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Delmaire 1989, pp. 64-65</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/text/228282">PHI 228282</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/text/103911">TM 103911</ref></bibl>
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Agostini G., Prefetti e praesides nell'amministrazione giudiziaria dell'Egitto tardoantico: ambiti di competenza e prosopografia (284-397) [unpublished PhD Diss. Roma "Sapienza" 2019]</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bernand E., Inscriptions métriques de l'Egypte gréco-romaine. Recherches sur la poésie épigrammatique des grecs en Egypte, Paris 1969</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bernand A., Le Delta Égyptien d’après les textes grecs, I. Les confins lybiques, Le Caire 1970</bibl>
                    <bibl>Blouin K., Triangular landscapes: environment, society, and the state in the Nile Delta under Roman rule, Oxford-New York 2014</bibl>
                    <bibl>Botti G., Catalogue du Musée d'Alexandrie, Alexandrie 1901, 540, nr. 11</bibl>
                    <bibl>Charles R.H., The Chronicle of John, Bishop of Nikiu. Translated from Zotenberg's Ethiopic Text,  Merchantville (NJ) 1916</bibl>
                    <bibl>Delmaire R., Les responsables des finances impériales au Bas-Empire romain (IVe-VIe s.). Études prosopographique, Bruxelles 1989</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ensslin W., Tatianus 3, in RE IV A 2, Stuttgart 1932, coll. 2463-2467</bibl>
                    <bibl>Errington R., A note on the Augustal Prefect of Egypt, Tyche, 17, 2002, 69-77</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hairy, I., and Sennoune, O. Géographie historique du canal d’Alexandrie, Annales Islamologiques, 40, 2006, 247-287</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kubitschek W., Eine Inschrift des Speichers von Andriake (Lykien), NZ, 51, 1918, 66-70</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lallemand J., Administration civile de l’Egypte de l’avènement de Dioclétian à la création du diocèse (284-382), Contribution à l’étude des rapport entre l’Egypte et l’Empire à la fin du IIIe au IVe siècle, Bruxelles, 1964</bibl>
                    <bibl>McCormick M., What climate science, Ausonius, Nile floods, rye, and thatch tell us about the environmental history of the Roman Empire, The ancient Mediterranean environment between science and history, Columbia Studies in the Classical Tradition, 39, 2013, 61-88</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mratschek S., Melania and the Unknown Governor of Palestine, Journal of Late Antiquity, 5, 2012, 250-268</bibl>
                    <bibl>Olszaniec S., Prosopographical Studies on the Court Elite in the Roman Empire (4th Century AD), Toruń, 2013</bibl>
                    <bibl>Palme B., Praesides and Correctores der Augustamnica, AntTard 6, 1998, 123-135</bibl>
                    <bibl>Parcak S., The physical context of ancient Egypt, A Companion to Ancient Egypt, 2010, 3-22</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pellacani D., Le piene del Nilo: nota bibliografica, in Seneca e le scienze naturali, 2012, 81-92</bibl>
                    <bibl>Petit P., Les fonctionnaires dans l'œuvre de Libanius. Analyse prosopographique, Besançon 1994</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scharf R., Die Familie des Fl. Eutolmius Tatianus, ZPE, 85, 1991, 223-231</bibl>
                    <bibl>Seeck O., Die Briefe des Libanius zeitlich geördnet, Leipzig 1906</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sonnini de Manoncourt Ch.N.S., Voyage dans la haute et basse Egypte: fait par ordre de l’ancien gouvernement et contenant des observations de tous genres, II, Paris 1799</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vandersleyen Cl., Chronologie des préfets d’Egypte de 284 à 395, Bruxelles 1962</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wescher C., Notice sur les inscriptions grecques du piédestal d’Antinoé et du monument d’Athribis en Egypte, Bullettino dell’Instituto di Corrispondenza Archeologica, 38, 1866, 150-155</bibl>
                    </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="7">
                    <p n="7.3">Canopus canal</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">τοῦ λαμπροτάτου</p>
                    <p n="8.2">τοῦ λαμπροτάτου καὶ ὑπάρχοντος ἐπάρχου τοῦ ἱεροῦ πραιτωρίου</p>
                    <p n="8.4"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>