<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Fragmentary inscription in honour of Maximianus Aug. from the Roman Forum by two praet. prefects</title>
                <editor role="edition">Pierfrancesco Porena</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Irene Vagionakis</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="plre" corresp="p. 1000">03</idno>
                <date when="2020-06-26"/>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#nus">[- - -]nus</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#mus">[- - -]mus</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#Roma">Roma, Roman Forum, in front of the Curia, to the right of the entrance staircase</repository>
                        <idno type="invNo">Sopr. For.-Pal. inv. 12444</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#honorary">Honorary inscription for the emperor Maximianus</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#marble">white marble</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>105 / 99</height>
                                        <width>60 / 58</width>
                                        <depth>54 / 52</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">uncertain</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">yes</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One field in front.</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#undamaged">Undamaged, although not erased, the surface of the whole epigraphic field has deteriorated.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#rustic_capitals">rustic capitals</term>
                                <height>3 / 4.5</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Roma</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Rome (Italy)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Urbs</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Italiciana</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">(not regional before 326 AD)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">public space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p1" notBefore="0298" notAfter="0305">298/305 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found">Statue base with inscription chiselled on the front face, found in the <placeName ref="#RomanForum">Roman Forum</placeName> in 1899, «re-used as building material in an Early Medieval structure in front of the Curia» (Machado in LSA 1364).</provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed" when="1999" resp="Porena">Text was seen and verified (where possible) by Porena 1999.</provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="la">
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/><unclear>Propagatori</unclear> <unclear>Romani</unclear> <supplied reason="lost"><expan><abbr>imp</abbr><ex>eri</ex></expan></supplied>
                        <lb n="2"/><supplied reason="lost">om</supplied><unclear>nium</unclear> <unclear>virtutum</unclear> 
                        <lb n="3"/><supplied reason="lost">princi</supplied><unclear>pi</unclear>, <expan><abbr><unclear>d</unclear></abbr><ex>omino</ex></expan> <expan><abbr><unclear>n</unclear></abbr><ex>ostro</ex></expan> <expan><abbr><unclear>M</unclear></abbr><ex>arco</ex></expan> <expan><abbr><unclear>Aurel</unclear></abbr><ex>io</ex></expan>
                        <lb n="4"/><supplied reason="lost">Valeri</supplied><unclear>o</unclear> <unclear>Maximiano</unclear>, 
                        <lb n="5"/><supplied reason="lost">Pio</supplied>, <unclear>Fe</unclear><supplied reason="lost">l</supplied><unclear>ici</unclear>, <unclear>semper</unclear>
                        <lb n="6"/>   <supplied reason="lost">Augu</supplied><unclear>sto</unclear>,
                        <lb n="7"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/><unclear>nus</unclear> <unclear>et</unclear> <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>
                        <lb n="8"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/><unclear>mus</unclear> <expan><abbr><unclear>v</unclear></abbr><am><unclear>v</unclear></am><ex>iri</ex></expan> <expan><abbr><unclear>e</unclear></abbr><am><unclear>e</unclear></am><supplied reason="lost" cert="low"><abbr>m</abbr><am>m</am><ex>inentissimi</ex></supplied></expan>
                        <lb n="9"/><supplied reason="lost"><expan><abbr>pr</abbr><ex>aefecti</ex></expan></supplied> <expan><abbr><supplied reason="lost">p</supplied><unclear>raet</unclear></abbr><ex>orio</ex></expan> <unclear>devoti</unclear> <expan><abbr><unclear>n</unclear></abbr><ex>umini</ex></expan> <expan><abbr><unclear>m</unclear></abbr><ex>aiestati</ex><abbr><unclear>q</unclear></abbr><ex>ue</ex></expan>
                        <lb n="10"/>   <unclear>eius</unclear>.
                    </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>The text is based on the M. Bang edition (CIL 06, 36947), supplemented by Porena’s conjectures. For I. Grossi (EDR 135609) the inscription was totally erased after being chiselled.</p>
                <p>
                    <app loc="3"><note>[compo]<unclear>ti</unclear>: Bang and other editors.</note></app>
                    <app loc="5"><note>[P(io)]: Bang.</note></app>
                    <app loc="5-6"><note>semper [Augu]sto: Machado LSA 1346; I. Grossi EDR 135609. Bang was sure whether Augusto was written in the middle of the sixth line.</note></app>
                    <app loc="8"><note><unclear>vv</unclear>(iri) <unclear>ee</unclear>(gregii): Bang (who was able to read only the first E); G. Alföldy, A. Scheithauer CIL 06, p. 4354; Machado LSA 1364. vv(iri) ee[mm(inentissimi)]: PLRE I; Sartre 2000; Porena 2003, p. 104 nt 2.</note></app>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“To the extender of the Roman empire, to the prince endowed with all the virtues, to our master Marcus Aurelius Valerius Maximianus, Pius Felix always Augustus, [- - -]nus and [- - -]mus the [very eminent praetorian prefects] devoted to his spirit and majesty.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>“À l’auteur de l’extension de l’Empire romain, au prince doué de toutes les vertus, à notre seigneur Marcus Aurelius Valérius Maximianus, Pie Heureux toujours Auguste, [- - -]nus et [- - -]mus les [très éminents préfets du prétoire] dévoués à sa divinité et à sa majesté.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“All’autore dell’espansione dell’impero romano, al principe dotato di tutte le virtù, al nostro signore Marcus Aurelius Valerius Maximianus, Pio Felice sempre Augusto, [- - -]nus e [- - -]mus gli e[minentissimi prefetti del pretorio] devoti al nume e alla maestà sue.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>The base of the statue is compact, but it has been severely damaged by building reuses on all its surfaces. The text inscribed in the epigraphic field is heavily eroded, but not erased after chiselling. Maximianus’ onomastics was readable by the publishers Gatti (in 1899) and Bang (in 1933), and this was still the case in 1999. 
                    Thus we can exclude that the inscription was erased in order to delete the memory of the Augustus Herculius. The surface of the epigraphic field has not been lowered to engrave a new inscription over ours.</p>
                <p>The monuments of the Tetrarchs, especially those of the <foreign>Vicennalia</foreign> in the Roman Forum, would have remained intact in their place (Marlowe 2015; Kalas 2015, 23-45). 
                    Furthermore Maximianus was responsible for the reconstruction of the Diocletianic Curia after the terrible fire of 284 AD. The memory of the two Augusti was preserved in the area in front of the senate: it is very likely that our base with its statue remained <foreign>in situ</foreign>. The crisis between Herculius and his son Maxentius in 308 AD, and with his son-in-law Constantine in 310 AD, does not seem to have affected the placement of Maximianus’ monument (on the location of our inscribed monument see Bauer 1996, pp. 16-19; 102; 401).</p>
                <p>About the text: at lines 2/3 after the expression <foreign>omnium virtutum</foreign>, Bang hypothesized the adjective <foreign>compos</foreign>, due to he reads the letters TI at line 3; however, such an expression is never attested in epigraphy. 
                    Vice versa <foreign>omnium virtutum principi</foreign> is the epithet of the emperors Pertinax in <ref type="inscription">CIL 11, 03873</ref> = <ref type="inscription">ILS 0409</ref> and Probus in <ref type="inscription">CIL 02-14, 00020</ref> = <ref type="inscription">ILS 0597</ref>. At line 6, the centered position of the cognomen Augustus, seen by Bang, is perfectly suited to the layout of the epigraphy of the time.</p>
                <p>The examination of the photograph and my personal autopsy suggest that on line 9, before the word <foreign>devoti</foreign>, some letters were originally chiselled, and some vertical and horizontal strokes remain. 
                    Taking into account the difficulties in the reading, it seems – but caution is a must – possible to discern the letters RAET; these could be what remains of the abbreviation of the office <foreign>[pr(aefecti)</foreign> or <foreign>praeff(ecti) p]ṛạẹṭ(orio)</foreign>.</p>
                <p>The authors of the PLRE (I, ..mus, p. 1000) have supposed that the dedication to Maximian Augustus was raised by the two leading praetorian prefects of the whole empire, although T.D. Barnes makes no attempt to identify them (1982, p. 136 and nt. 51; Barnes 1996, p. 547 nt. 84). 
                    The abbreviation of the rank at line 8, VV EE, could be integrated: <foreign>vv(iri) ee[mm(inentissimi) praeff(ecti)</foreign> or <foreign>pr(aefecti) praet(orio)]</foreign>. Several elements would support such a proposal. 
                    The dedication was raised collegially by two officials holding the same office; from the remains of the formula we must assume that this office was normally exercised in pairs. 
                    In fact, there does not seem to be enough space in the epigraphic field to contain the indication of two different positions that may have been held by the dedicators and not even for a position that is more extensive. 
                    The rank of the officials, the same for both, can only be integrated with <foreign>vv(iri) ee[gregii]</foreign>, or with <foreign>vv(iri) ee[minentissimi]</foreign>, the latter being the prerogative of praetorian prefects in the Tetrarchic Age. 
                    No egregiate function was collegial; no dedications to emperors – or other type of inscriptions in Rome – by two or more <foreign>egregii</foreign> have been observed. We know of single <foreign>viri egregii</foreign> in inscriptions from the Roman Forum, but they are not dedicants of statue bases for emperors (<ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 02132</ref> = <ref type="inscription">ILS 4928</ref>; <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 02134</ref> = <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 32419</ref>; <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 02136</ref> = <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 32405</ref>; <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 02137</ref> = <ref type="inscription">ILS 4936</ref>; they are <foreign>fictores Virginum Vestalium</foreign>, cf. now Lindner 2015, pp. 64, 135). 
                    To restore <foreign>vv(iri) ee(gregii)</foreign> is difficult, since it seems unlikely that in the late 3rd Century, when the <foreign>perfectissimatus</foreign> extended to most equestrian offices, simple <foreign>viri egregii</foreign> would raise monuments to an Augustus in such a prestigious place, not only in the Roman Forum itself, but in the area between the Curia and the Comitium, which had just been restored.
                    The axis between the Curia, the Basilica Aemilia and the stretch of the Via Sacra towards the Velia was populated in the 4th Century with statues made by dignitaries for the emperors (Bauer 2012; Machado 2006 and 2019, pp. 95-123). 
                    Dedications made in Rome by pairs of praetorian prefects (<foreign>eminentissimi</foreign>) prior to our inscription are not unknown: <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 01009</ref> (cf. p. 4315) = <ref type="inscription">ILS 2012</ref> (140 AD); <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 01611</ref> = <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 31831</ref> (241 AD); <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 02388a fr. 5</ref> = <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 32600</ref> = <ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?id_nr=EDR122374">EDR 122374</ref> (3rd Century AD); <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 31352</ref> = <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 40710</ref> (second half of the 3rd Century AD).</p>
                <p>The ancient political centre of Rome still appears to be the most suitable place to erect a monument decreed by praetorian prefects. In fact, we know of two dedications to Maxentius placed by his praetorian prefect right in the Forum in 310/311 AD: one is now next to the Basilica Emilia (<ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 40726</ref> = <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret05">PPRET 05</ref>), a few meters from our inscription to Maximianus, the other one was found ‘summa via sacra’ near the Basilica of Maxentius (<ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 36949</ref> = <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret04">PPRET 04</ref>). 
                    Other inscriptions made by praetorian prefects for late roman emperors were displayed in the Roman Forum during late antiquity, and by emperors to a single prefect too. 
                    After these three statue bases of the Tetrarchic period, we can find in the area of the Basilica Emilia: a fragmentary dedication in honour of a 4th Century Augustus by a praetorian prefect whose name is lost (<ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 36678</ref> = <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 36990</ref> = <ref type="inscription">Panciera 1996a, nr. 195</ref> = <ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?id_nr=EDR071778">EDR 071778</ref>); a statue base for the emperor Valens made by Placidus Severus (PLRE I, Severus 28, pp. 836-837) a <foreign>vicarius urbis, agens vices praefecti praetorio</foreign> in about 364/365 (<ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 36956</ref> = <ref type="inscription">ILS 8948</ref> = <ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail.php?record=LSA-1373">LSA 1373</ref> = <ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?id_nr=EDR071728">EDR 071728</ref>). 
                    In other parts of the Roman Forum, not far from the basilica Aemilia, inscriptions in honour of praetorian prefects were found: from the area near the Column of Phocas comes the monument in honour of Vettius Agorius Praetextatus praetorian prefect of Italy and Illyricum, erected in 384 AD (<ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 01779a</ref> = <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 31929</ref> = <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret78">PPRET 78</ref>); 
                    from the zone in front of the Curia, near our base in honour of Maximianus Herculius, comes the statue base in honour of Petronius Maximus praetorian prefect of Italia Illyricum Africa, put up in 433/437 AD by Theodosius II and Valentinian III Augusti (<ref type="inscription">Panciera 1996b</ref> = <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 41398</ref> = <ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail.php?record=LSA-1525">LSA 1525</ref> = <ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?id_nr=EDR093620">EDR 093620</ref>); 
                    from an indeterminate space in the Roman Forum comes a fragmentary inscription in honour of an anonymous praetorian prefect, dated in the first half of the 5th Century AD (<ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 41346</ref> = <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret96">PPRET 96</ref>). 
                    Other potential fragmentary dedications of dignitaries of the late 3rd Century AD (prefects ?) to emperors from the area of the Curia and the Basilica Aemilia exist: <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 40707</ref> (to Aurelianus), <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 40751</ref> (to Probus). The north-eastern side of the Roman Forum between late 3rd and mid 5th Century hosted monuments related to praetorian prefects, namely between the Curia and the Basilica Aemilia. 
                    We can therefore hypothesize that what remains of the inscription <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 36947</ref> might well be a prefectural dedication in the Roman Forum, put up on the orders of the two leading praetorian prefects of the whole empire to Maximianus Augustus alone, probably for an event or an anniversary that concerned him. 
                    At the end of the military campaign in Africa (297-298 AD), in late 298 AD Maximianus Herculius stayed in Rome, where he began construction of the Baths of Diocletian (Chastagnol 1980-1981); in 299 AD (oct./dec.) his <foreign>Quindecennalia</foreign> began: the prefectural monument for Herculius in the Roman Forum may have been built in this period. 
                    The epithet <foreign>propagator</foreign> and the praise of his <foreign>virtus</foreign> were appropriate in the context of Maximianus’ recent victories.</p>
                <p>This lead to the identity of the two praetorian prefects is to be found on lines 7-8, and consists of the final parts of the cognomina. We know four colleges of praetorian prefects of Diocletianus and Maximianus (only the Augusti had one prefect each), complete with their rank (cf. Porena 2003, pp. 103-152):</p>
                
                <p><space rend="space"/></p>
                <p>284?-286 AD<space rend="space"/> <space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/>Diocletianus<space rend="space"/>Aristobulus and/then Hannibalianus vv.eemm.</p>
                <p>286-291 AD <space rend="space"/> <space rend="space"/> <space rend="space"/>Diocletianus<space rend="space"/>Hannibalianus v.em.  (inscr. of Oescus, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret01">PPRET 01</ref>)</p>
                <p><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/>Maximianus<space rend="space"/>Asclepiodotus v.em.</p>
                <p>In 292 AD <space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/> Hannibalianus et Asclepiodotus were ordinary consuls and became vv.cc.</p>
                <p><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/>(two prefects clarissimi in <ref type="inscription">CIL 06, 01125</ref> = <ref type="inscription">ILS 0619</ref>, in 293/296 AD)</p>
                <p>292-294/96 AD <space rend="space"/> <space rend="space"/>Diocletianus<space rend="space"/>Hannibalianus v.c. (then prefect of Rome in 297 AD)</p>
                <p><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/>Maximianus<space rend="space"/>Asclepiodotus v.c.</p>
                <p>294/96-297/98 AD<space rend="space"/> Maximianus<space rend="space"/>Asclepiodotus v.c. (as prefect he defeated the usurper Adlectus in 296/97 AD)</p>
                <p><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/>Diocletianus<space rend="space"/>Hermogenianus v.em. (inscr. of Brescia, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret02">PPRET 02</ref>)</p>
                <p>297/98?-305 AD<space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/>Diocletianus<space rend="space"/>Hermogenianus v.em. (he never became v.c.)</p>
                <p><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/><space rend="space"/>Maximianus<space rend="space"/>? v.em.  (two prefects eminentissimi in <ref type="inscription">CIL 14, 04455</ref>, in 297/305 AD)</p>
                <p><space rend="space"/></p>
                
                <p>It seems likely that our inscription from the Roman Forum, pertains to two praetorian prefects belonging to the last phase of the Tetrarchy, between 298 and 305 AD. 
                    The first could be [Hermogenia]nus, prefect of Diocletianus; the second could be the prefect appointed by Maximianus after the departure of Asclepiodotus (there was no prefect ordinary consul between 293 and 305 AD, therefore after Hannibalianus and Asclepiodotus there were only prefects of eminentissimus rank). 
                    In 2000 M. Sartre proposed that the first praetorian prefect of our inscription was Aurelius Rufinus (2000, 989-990 = <ref type="inscription">AE 2000, 1540</ref>; in print <ref type="inscription">IGLS 16, 0708</ref>). His reconstruction is based on a reading of the sixth line of an inscription from Teyma (Arabia), commemorating the restoration of  castra in 296 AD – <foreign>Aur(elio) Rufino p(raefecto) pr(aetorio) Ori[entis]</foreign> – but that reading was then rejected by Sartre himself (2007, 163 = <ref type="inscription">AE 2007, 1619</ref>). 
                    The position of Rufinus’ name after that of the Governor of Arabia and the mention of the Prefecture of the East before Constantine’s reform hinder this interpretation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>CIL 06, 36947</ref> (p. 4354)</bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>AE 2000, 1540</ref> (see Critical commentary)</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p></p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://db.edcs.eu/epigr/edcs_id.php?p_edcs_id=EDCS-19800521">EDCS 19800521</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/edr_programmi/res_complex_comune.php?id_nr=EDR135609">EDR 135609</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail.php?record=LSA-1364">LSA 1364</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/text/597316">TM 597316</ref></bibl>
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Barnes T.D., The New Empire of Diocletian and Constantine, Cambridge Mass.-London 1982</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barnes T.D., Emperors, Panegyrics, Prefects, Provinces and Palaces (284-317), JRA, 9, 1996, 532-552</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bauer F.A., Stadt, Platz und Denkmal in der Spätantike. Untersuchungen zur Ausstattung des öffentlichen Raums in den spätantiken Städten Rom, Konstantinopel und Ephesos, Mainz 1996</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bauer F.A., Das Forum Romanum als normativer Raum in der Spätantike, in Chiai G.F., Gauly B.M., Hartmann A., Zimmer G., Zapff B.M. (hrsg.), Athen, Rom, Jerusalem. Normentransfers in der antiken Welt, Regensburg 2012, 327-341</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chastagnol A., Maximien Hercule à Rome, BSAF 1980-1981, 183-191 (= Id., Aspects de l’antiquité tardive, Roma 1994, 303-307)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gatti G., ROMA. IV. Nuove scoperte nella città e nel suburbio, NSA, 1899, 486-492</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gatti G., Monumenti epigrafici rinvenuti nel Foro Romano, BCAR, 27, 1899, 205-247</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hülsen C., Neue Inschriften vom Forum Romanum, Klio, 2, 1902, 227-283 (242, n. 24)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kalas G., The Restoration of the Roman Forum in Late Antiquity. Transforming Public Space, Austin 2015</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lindner M., Portraits of the Vestal Virgins, Priestesses of Ancient Rome Portraits of the Vestal Virgins, Priestesses of Ancient Rome, Ann Arbor 2015</bibl>
                    <bibl>Machado C., Building the Past. Monuments and Memory in the Forum Romanum, in Bowden W., Gutteridge A., Machado C. (eds.), Social and Political Life in Late Antiquity, Leiden-Boston 2006, 157-194</bibl>
                    <bibl>Machado C., Urban Space and Aristocratic Power in Late Antique Rome, AD 270-535, Oxford 2019</bibl>
                    <bibl>Marlowe E., The Multivalence of Memory. The Tetrarchs, the Senate, and the Vicennalia Monument in the Roman Forum, in Galinsky K., Lapatin K. (eds.), Cultural Memories in the Roman Empire, Los Angeles 2015, 240-263</bibl>
                    <bibl>Panciera S., Iscrizioni greche e latine del Foro romano e del Palatino. Inventario generale - inediti – revisioni, Roma 1996 (a)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Panciera S., Il precettore di Valentiniano III, in Stella C., Valvo A. (a cura di), Studi in onore di Albino Garzetti, Brescia 1996 (b), 277-297 (= Panciera S., Petronio Massimo precettore di Valentiniano III, in Id., Epigrafi, epigrafia, epigrafisti. Scritti vari editi e inediti (1956-2005) con note complementari e indici, Roma 2006, 1153-1166)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Le origini della prefettura del pretorio tardoantica, Roma 2003</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sartre M., Gouverneurs d’Arabie anciens et nouveaux: textes inédits, in Paci G. (a cura di), Ἐπιγραφαί. Miscellanea epigrafica in onore di Lidio Gasperini, II, Tivoli 2000, 971-990 (= AE 2000, 1540)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sartre M., L’armée romaine et la défense de la Syrie du Sud. Questions de méthode et nouveau document, in Lewin A.S., Pellegrini P. (eds.), The Late Roman Army in the Near East from Diocletian to the Arab Conquest. Proceedings of a Colloquium held at Potenza, Acerenza and Matera, Italy (May 2005), Oxford 2007, 263-273 (= AE 2007, 1619)</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.3"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="7">
                    <p n="7.1"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">vv(iri) ee[mm(inentissimi)]</p>
                    <p n="8.2">[pr(aefecti) p]raet(orio) </p>
                    <p n="8.9"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>