<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Greek Inscription in honour of an Anonymous praet. prefect of Constantius II A. and Julian C. by the region of Batanea (from Aire, Phoenices Libanensis)</title>
                <editor role="edition">Pierfrancesco Porena</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Irene Vagionakis</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="new">35</idno>
                <date when="2020-06-23"/>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#anonymous_east">Anonymous praetorian prefect of the East</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#Sanamein">in the garden of a house near the Tycheion of Al-Sanamein</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#honorary">Honorary inscription for an anonymous praetorian prefect</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="grc">Greek</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#limestone">limestone</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>29</height>
                                        <width>95</width>
                                        <depth>92</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">uncertain</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">yes</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One inscribed field (<foreign>frons</foreign>); the back and left faces bear a different inscription (IGLS 14, 0556a).</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#damaged">The first line of the inscription is ruined.</rs>
                                    <p n="opistographic">Two other faces of the base bear a previous inscription, the dedication IGLS XIV, 556a.</p>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#square_capitals">Late antique Greek squared capitals</term>
                                <height>3.5</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Aire</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Al-Sanamein (Syria)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Phoenices Libanensis</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">public space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p5" notBefore="0358" notAfter="0360">358/360 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found">found in 1997 in the road to the West of the Tycheion of <placeName ref="#">Al-Sanamein</placeName></provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"></provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="grc">
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/><unclear>Τ</unclear>ὸν λ<supplied reason="lost">α</supplied><unclear>μ</unclear>πρό<unclear>τ</unclear>α<unclear>τ</unclear>ο<supplied reason="lost">ν</supplied> <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>
                        <lb n="2"/>τὸν τοῦ ἱεροῦ <sic>πρετωρίου</sic> ἔπαρχον τοῦ δεσποτοῦ ἡμῶν
                        <lb n="3"/>Κωνσταντίου τοῦ Αὐγούστου καὶ Νικήτου καὶ τοῦ ἐπι<lb 
                            break="no" n="4"/>φανεστάτου Καίσαρος Ἰουλιανοῦ διʹ οὗ <sic>ἰρήνη</sic> καὶ ἀμεριμνία
                        <lb n="5"/>ὕπηρξεν ἡ Βατανέα τὸν εὐεργετὴν καὶ σωτήρα ἀνέστησεν,
                        <lb n="6"/>ἐπὶ <expan><abbr>Φλ</abbr><ex>αουίου</ex></expan> Μαξίμου τοῦ διασημοτάτου δουκηναρίου τοῦ σάλτου.
                    </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>Edition based on IGLS 14/2; AE 1999; SEG 49.</p>
                <p>
                    <app loc="1"><note><unclear>Τ</unclear>ὸν λ[α]<unclear>μ</unclear>πρό<unclear>τ</unclear>α<unclear>τ</unclear>ο[ν - - -]<unclear>ω</unclear>ι, IGLS 14/2</note></app>
                    <app loc="2"><note>πραιτωρίου</note></app>
                    <app loc="3"><note>Νικήτου, IGLS 14/2</note></app>
                    <app loc="4"><note>ἐιρήνη</note></app>
                    <app loc="5"><note>ὕπηρξεν IGLS 14/2; εὐεργετὴν IGLS 14/2; σωτήρα IGLS 14/2</note></app>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“Of clarissimus rank, ..., the prefect of the sacred praetorium of our master Constantius Augustus and Victorious and of the most noble Caesar Julian, thanks to whom there is peace and security, the Batanaea has erected (the statue of his) benefactor and saviour, under Flavius Maximus, the most perfect ducenarius of the saltus.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>(Sartre in IGLS 14/2, nr. 0555a)</p>
                <p>“LLe clarissime ... préfet du prétoire de notre maître Constance Auguste et vainqueur et du très illustre César Julien, par lequel paix et sérénité existent, la Batanée a dressé (la statue de son) bienfaiteur et sauveur, sous Flavius Maximus, l’éminent ducénaire du saltus.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Il chiarissimo ..., prefetto del sacro pretorio del nostro signore Constantius Augusto e Vincitore e del nobilissimo Cesare Iulianus, grazie al quale c’è la pace e la sicurezza, la Batanea ha eretto (la statua del suo) benefattore e salvatore, sotto Flavius Maximus, il perfettissimo ducenario del saltus.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>...</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>Sartre 1999, pp. 219-221</ref> (with photo, fig. 3) (= <bibl><ref>Sartre 2014, pp. 277‐278</ref></bibl>) = <bibl><ref>AE, 1999, 1699</ref></bibl>; <bibl><ref>SEG 49 (1999), 2105</ref></bibl>; <bibl><ref>BE 2001, 0507</ref></bibl></bibl>
                    <bibl>(Sartre in) <ref>Yon, Gatier 2009, pp. 102‐105, nr. 23</ref> (with photo)</bibl> 
                    <bibl><ref>IGLS 14/2, nr. 0555a</ref> (with photo)</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p/>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p/>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Barrington Atlas of the Greek and Roman World, ed. R.J.A. Talbert, Princeton-Oxford 2000</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bartels J., Was tat der «praefectus saltus» ? Städtischer Grundbesitz und seine Verwaltung in der römischen Kolonie Oescus, ZPE 167, 2008, 276-282</bibl>
                    <bibl>Beaudouin É., Les grands domaines dans l’Empire romain, d’après des travaux récents, Nouvelle revue historique de droit français et étranger, 21, 1897, 543-599</bibl>
                    <bibl>Carrié J.-M., Nommer les structures rurales entre fin de l’Antiquité et Haut Moyen Âge: le répertoire lexical gréco-latin et ses avatars modernes (1re partie), AntTard, 20, 2012, 25-46</bibl>
                    <bibl>Clauss-Balty P., La kalybé de Hayat (Syrie du Sud), Syria, 85, 2008, 249-292 [online: http://journals.openedition.org/syria/483]</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dagron G., Entre village et cité: la bourgade rurale des IVe-VIIe siècles en Orient, in Koinonia, 3, 1979, 29-52 (= Id., La romanité chrétienne en Orient. Héritages et mutations, London 1984, VII)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dentzer J.-M., Hauran I. Récherches archéologiques sur la Syrie du Sud à l’époque hellénistique et romaine, Paris 1985</bibl>
                    <bibl>Freyberger K.S., Das Tycheion von as Sanamein. Ein Vorbericht, DaM (Damaszener Mitteilungen), 4, 1989, 87-108</bibl>
                    <bibl>Freyberger K.S., Heiligtümer aus römischer Zeit in den Dörfern südsyriens. Einheimische Religion und imperialer herrscherkult, BJ, 210/211, 2010/2011, 459-500</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gnoli T., Metrokomiai e comunità di villaggio nell’Oriente antico e tardoantico, in Polidoro. Studi offerti ad Antonio Carile, a cura di G. Vespignani, II, Spoleto 2013, 273-289</bibl>
                    <bibl>IGLS 14 = A. Sartre-Fauriat, M. Sartre, Inscriptions grecques et latines de la Syrie, 14. La Batanée et le Jawlān oriental, 2 voll., Beyrouth 2016</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kaplan M., Les propriétés de la couronne et de l’Eglise dans l’Empire byzantin (Ve-VIe siècles) : documents, Paris 1976</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lee A.D., Information and frontiers. Roman foreign relations in Late Antiquity, Cambridge 1993</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lo Cascio E., The Imperial Property and its Development, in P. Erdkamp, K. Verboven, A. Zuiderhoek (eds.), Ownership and Exploitation of Land and Natural Resources in the Roman World, Oxford 2015, 62-70</bibl>
                    <bibl>Oenbrink W., Römische Architektur im Hauran. Zustand und Erhaltung im Spiegel früher Zeichnungen und Photographien am Beispiel des Tyche-Heiligtums von As-Sanamein, in Munus. Festschrift für Hans Wiegartz, Münster 2000, 189-207</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sartre M., Les metrokomiai de Syrie du Sud, Syria, 76, 1999, 197-222 (= Id., L’historien et ses territoires. Choix d’articles, textes réunis par P. Brun, Bordeaux 2014, 249-287)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Soricelli G., Saltus, in A. Storchi Marino (a cura di), Economia, amministrazione e fiscalità nel mondo romano. Ricerche lessicali, Bari 2004, 97-123</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vera D., Imperial estates in late Roman southern Italy: land concentration and rent distribution, in A. M. Small (ed.), Beyond Vagnary. New Themes in the Study of Roman South Italy, Bari 2014, 285-293</bibl>
                    <bibl>Yon J.-B., Gatier P.-L. (dir.), Choix d’inscriptions grecques et latines de la Syrie, Amman - Beyrouth - Damas - Alep 2009, 102-105, nr. 23</bibl>
                    <bibl>Woods D., An unnoticed official: the praepositus saltus, CQ, 44, 1994, 245-251</bibl> 
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="2">
                    <p n="2.a"></p>
                    <p n="2.1"></p>
                    <p n="2.2"></p>
                    <p n="2.9">διʹ οὗ ἰρήνη (sic) καὶ ἀμεριμνία / ὑπῆρξεν ἡ Βατανέα τὸν εὐεργέτην καὶ σωτῆρα</p>
                    <list n="2.11">
                        <item n="2.11.d"></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">Τ̣ὸν λ[α]μ̣πρότ̣ατ̣ο[ν]</p>
                    <p n="8.2">τὸν τοῦ ἱεροῦ πρετωρίου (sic) ἔπαρχον</p>
                    <p n="8.5"></p>
                    <p n="8.9"></p>
                    <p n="8.10"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
