<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Inscription in honour of Constantine II Caesar (in Greek) from Antioch by five praet. praefects (Tubernuc’s twin inscr.)</title>
                <editor role="edition">Eleonora Angius</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Eleonora Angius</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="new">18</idno>
                <date when="2020-03-27"/>
                <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Pacatianus"><name type="gentilicium">Papius</name>
                        <name type="cognomen">Pacatianus</name>
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Ablabius"><name type="gentilicium">Flavius</name>
                        <name type="cognomen">Ablabius</name>
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Felix"><name type="gentilicium">Valerius</name>
                        <name type="cognomen">Felix</name>
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Tiberianus"><name type="gentilicium">Annius</name>
                        <name type="cognomen">Tiberianus</name>
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#Timonianus"><name type="gentilicium">Nestorius</name>
                        <name type="cognomen">Timonianus</name>
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#Antakya">roof of Antakya Museum</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#honorary">Honorary inscription for emperor Constantine II Caesar</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="grc">Greek</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#limestone">sandstone</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#stone_slab">slab originally joined to a statue base</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>29</height>
                                        <width>91</width>
                                        <depth>8.5</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">none</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">uncertain; probably yes, because the opposite side has a rough surface</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One inscribed field (<foreign>frons</foreign>).</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#damaged">Damaged: reduced on the left lower corner, while the right corner is chiselled away, also it is possible to notice two grooves on the upper side.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#uncial">uncial capitals</term>
                                <height>3 / 4</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Antiochia Syriae</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Antakya (Turkey)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Syria Coele</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">public space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p4" when="0336" precision="high">336 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found"><placeName ref="#unknown">unknown</placeName></provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"></provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="grc">
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1"/>Τὸν δεσ<unclear>πότ</unclear>ην ἡμῶν <expan><abbr>Φλ</abbr><ex>άουιον</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>Κλ</abbr><ex>αύδιον</ex></expan>
                    <lb n="2"/>Κωνσταντεῖνον τὸν ἀνδρ<unclear>ι</unclear>ότατον
                    <lb n="3"/>καὶ ἐπιφανέστατον Καίσαρα, <g ref="hedera"/> <expan><abbr>Π<unclear>άπ</unclear></abbr><ex>ιος</ex></expan>
                    <lb n="4"/>Πακατιανός, <expan><abbr>Φλ</abbr><ex>άουιος</ex></expan> Ἀβλάβιος, <expan><abbr>Oὐαλ</abbr><ex>έριος</ex></expan> Φῆλι<supplied reason="lost">ξ</supplied>,
                    <lb n="5"/><expan><abbr><unclear>Ἄ</unclear>νν</abbr><ex>ιος</ex></expan> Τιβεριανὸς καὶ <expan><abbr>Νεσ</abbr><ex>τόριος</ex></expan> Τιμωνιανὸς οἱ <expan><abbr><unclear>λ</unclear><supplied reason="lost">αμ</supplied></abbr><supplied reason="lost"><ex>πρότατοι</ex></supplied></expan>
                    <lb n="6"/><supplied reason="lost">ἔπ</supplied><unclear>α</unclear>ρχοι.
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>This edition is based on AE 1985, 0823</p>
                <p>
                    <app loc="4"><note>Φῆλιξ: Chastagnol 1986, p. 271</note></app>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“To our master, the bravest and most noble Cesar Flavius Claudius Constantinus, the praetorian prefects of clarissimus rank Papius Pacatianus, Flavius Ablabius, Valerius Felix, Annius Tiberianus and Nestorius Timonianus.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>(by Feissel 1985, p. 421)</p>
                <p>“(En l’honneur de) notre maître Flavius Claudius Constantinus, le très valeureux et très noble César, Papius Pacatianus, Flavius Ablabius, Valerius Felix, Annius Tiberianus, et Nestorius Timonianus, les clarissimes préfets.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Al nostro signore, il valorosissimo e nobilissimo Cesare Flavius Claudius Constantinus, i prefetti del pretorio chiarissimi Papius Pacatianus, Flavius Ablabius, Valerius Felix, Annius Tiberianus e Nestorius Timonianus.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>The inscription was found by Feissel on the roof of the Antakya Museum in 1980 and then published in 1985, but the findspot is unfortunately unknown. The slab was originally attached to a statue base, it was reduced on the left lower corner and damaged in the right lower one (but not chiselled away, see Feissel 1985, p. 421). The epigraphic field appears quite complete.</p>
                <p>Our monument represents an exceptional discovery because its Greek text, substantially intact and without post-writing interventions, as Feissel soon recognized, is a slightly simplified version in Greek of the Latin Tubernuc inscription (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret17">PPRET 17</ref>). This inscription is an honorary dedication in Greek to Constantine II Caesar, mirroring the African Latin one and put up by the same college of praetorian prefects listed in the same order. 
                    The comparison with the complete text in Greek confirms the existence of a college made up of five praetorian prefects under Constantine and allows us to identify the third missing prefect of the Tubernuc inscription (erased) with Valerius Felix and the previous (also erased) imperial title of Constantine II as <foreign>nobilissimus Caesar</foreign> (ἐπιφανέστατον Καίσαρα in our Greek text).</p>
                <p>The five names – Pacatianus, Ablabius, Felix, Tiberianus, Timonianus – constitute the complete list of prefects in office at that time. Their names are listed in order of appointment to the prefecture.</p>
                <p>Papius Pacatianus (PLRE I, Pacatianus 2, p. 656) was the <foreign>praeses Sardiniae</foreign> of the usurper Domitius Alexander, as testified by a milestone found in Carbonia (<ref type="inscription">Sotgiu 1961, nr. 372</ref> = <ref type="inscription">AE 1966, 0169</ref>). Then, when the usurper died in 310 AD, he probably fled to Constantine in Gaul. 
                    There, he became <foreign>vicarius Britanniarum</foreign> in 319 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 11, 07, 02</ref>; see Porena 2003, pp. 428-430 and 2012, p. 307). Pacatianus is attested as praetorian prefect (maybe of the Italician diocese, see Porena 2003, p. 482) in 332 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 03, 05, 04-05</ref>) but in these inscriptions he was listed before Ablabius (mentioned for the first time as prefect in 329 AD, see below), suggesting that he held his praetorian prefecture probably in 328 until, at least, 336 AD. He was also awarded with the consulate in 332 AD (CLRE, p. 198-199).</p>
                <p>Flavius Ablabius (PLRE I, Ablabius 4, pp. 3-4) was a native of Crete and despite his humble origins, was a capable epigrammatist (<ref type="source">Lib., Or., 42, 23</ref>). He started his career on the island as <foreign>officialis praesidis Cretae</foreign> (see Chausson 2002, pp. 207-208). His <foreign>cursus honorum</foreign> before the vicariate of Asia (324-327) is mostly unknown, but a recent survey by Porena (2014, pp. 262-268) demonstrates that Ablabius was <foreign>vicarius Italiae</foreign> in May 315 AD. A Constantinian edict (<ref type="source">CTh 11, 27, 01</ref>) ordered him to dip into state funds in order to help indigent families: the edict’s geographical extension "<foreign>per omnes civitates Italiae</foreign>" suggests he may have held the office of <foreign>vicarius Italiae</foreign>. 
                    Although his early career began in the West, he was already at that time a loyal Constantinian dignitary. Then, as has already been stated, he became <foreign>vicarius Asiae</foreign> (324-327 AD) and continued his career in the East, holding the praetorian prefecture of the Eastern diocese between 328 and 336 AD (Porena 2003, pp. 409-415) and the ordinary consulate in 331 AD (CLRE, pp. 196-197).</p>
                <p>Ablabius was probably the most influential of Constantine’s prefects: he benefitted from an intimate friendship with the emperor and married a princess of the imperial family around 330 AD (Chausson 2002, p. 216). Such a close and prolonged collaboration with Constantine cost him his life after the latter’s death in 337 AD. A cumbersome presence, Constantius II Augustus had him killed (<ref type="source">Eun., VS, 06, 03, 08-13</ref>; cf. Burgess 2008).</p>
                <p>At the beginning of his career, Valerius Felix (PLRE I, Felix 2, pp. 331-332) was perhaps the governor of Corsica in 318 AD and he likely gained a vicariate in a highly militarized diocese between 320-322 AD (Porena 2012, p. 309). 
                    Felix is attested by many Theodosian Constitutions as praetorian prefect from 333 until 336 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 03, 30, 05</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 021</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 13, 04, 01</ref>; <ref type="source">CTh 13, 05, 06</ref>) and some of them mention his residence at Carthage during that appointment. In particular the <foreign>Constitutiones Sirmondianae</foreign> (<ref type="source">Sirm. 04</ref>) provide important evidence of his regional mandate in the African diocese and of a new prefectural prerogative: Felix was ordered to spread the Constantinian edict concerning the conversion of Jews to Christianity in the African diocese entrusted to him (Porena 2003, pp. 431-441). Salway (2007, pp. 1284-1286) disputes the existence of an African regional prefecture at that time, while Vera (2015, pp. 166-167; cf. Vera 2012) argues that this prefecture was already operative under Constantine.</p>
                <p>Thus Felix’s name is deleted on the Tubernuc inscription but remains on the one of Antioch. Perhaps the prefect suffered <foreign>damnatio memoriae</foreign> after Constantine’s death due to his ties with the emperor, but actually we do not know exactly why it happened (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret17">PPRET 17</ref>).</p>
                <p>According to the historian Jerome, Annius Tiberianus (PLRE I, Tiberianus 4, pp. 911-912) originated from the region of Betica and was a famous Latin poet (<ref type="source">Hier., Vir. Ill. 123</ref>; <ref type="source">Hier., Chron., p. 233, Helm.</ref>; see Porena 2012, p. 316). He became <foreign>comes Africae</foreign> between 325 and 327 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 12, 05, 01</ref> and <ref type="source">CTh 12, 01, 015</ref>), <foreign>comes Hispaniarum</foreign> in 332 AD (<ref type="source">CI 06, 01, 06</ref>) and <foreign>vicarius Hispaniarum</foreign> in 335 AD (<ref type="source">CTh 03, 05, 06</ref>; see Porena 2003, pp. 470-473). 
                    Jerome is the only literary source to attest to his praetorian prefecture and places his mandate in Gaul during the last years of Constantine’s reign, 335-336 AD (<ref type="source">Hier., Chron., p. 233, Helm.</ref>).</p>
                <p>Nestorius Timonianus (PLRE I, p. 915) is not mentioned by any literary source or ancient codes, he only appears in our two parallel dedications. Since he is placed last in the prefectural college list, his appointment must have been later than the others (after 335 AD) and was probably short-lived.</p>
                <p>All these prefects erected a series of monuments throughout the empire in honour of Constantine II Caesar, during his <foreign>Vicennalia</foreign> (March 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 336 AD; see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret17">PPRET 17</ref>).</p>
                <p>Indeed, Tubernuc and Antioch, two of probably many cities where monuments were erected, were clearly different for political, cultural and strategic importance: on the one hand Antioch was a rich commercial capital of the Eastern diocese and seat of the imperial palace, while on the other hand, Tubernuc was a small Roman municipality that was never a capital or imperial residence.</p>
                <p>It seems unlikely that the two cities where these inscriptions were found were selected for any particular reason, it seems more probable that the finds are random and that the prefects wanted to celebrate their emperor throughout the whole empire. 
                    Another interesting aspect that clearly emerges from the comparison between these two parallel inscriptions is the use of Greek in the Antioch version, making this particular one a <foreign>unicum</foreign> among prefectural dedications of the first half of the 4th Century AD (<ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret01">PPRET 01</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret02">02</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret08">08</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret09">09</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret17">17</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret22">22</ref>). 
                    Given that the praetorian prefecture was the highest level of civil administration and that the latter had always used Latin as its epigraphic language, even in the East, where dedications concerning prefects were written in Latin, not only in cities with a strong Latin epigraphic tradition, such as Ephesus or Ancyra, but also in areas where the municipal epigraphy was almost exclusively in Greek, this is significant. Our inscription thus represents an exception and, according to Feissel, it was written in Greek exclusively for the need to translate into the local language a text already thought and spread simultaneously in Latin in other cities of the empire (see Feissel 2006, p. 105).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>Feissel 1985, p. 421</ref></bibl>= <bibl><ref>AE 1985, 0823</ref></bibl> = <bibl><ref>SEG 35 (1985), 1484</ref></bibl> = <bibl><ref>BE 1987, 497</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Chastagnol 1986, p. 271</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Di Maio, Arnold, Arnold 1992, p. 197</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Porena 2003, p. 469</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Salway 2007, p. 1283</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Olszaniec 2014, p. 21</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>Ghalia, Mahfoudh 2003, p. 786, fig. 9</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://inscriptions.packhum.org/text/322041?hs=233-242">PH 322041</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Burgess R., The Summer of Blood: The "Great Massacre" of 337 and the Promotion of the Sons of Constantine, DOP, 62, 2008, 5-51</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chastagnol A., Les inscriptions africaines des préfets du prétoire de Constantin, in Mastino A. (a cura di), L'Africa romana: atti del 3. Convegno di studio, 13-15 dicembre 1985, Sassari 1986, 263-273 (= Chastagnol A., Aspects de l’Antiquité Tardive, Roma 1994, 81-92)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chausson F., La famille du préfet Ablabius, Pallas, 60, 2002, 205-229</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coşkun A., Die Praefecti praesent(al)es und die Regionalisierung der Praetorianer-praefekturen im vierten Jahrhundert, Millennium, 1, 2004, 279-328</bibl>
                    <bibl>Di Maio Jr. M., Arnold D.W.-H., Arnold F., Per vim, per caedem, per bellum. A Study of Murder and Ecclesiastical Politics in the Year 337 A.D, Byzantion, 62, 1992, 158-211</bibl>
                    <bibl>Feissel D., Une dédicace en honneur de Constantin II César et les préfets du prétoire de 336, in Dagron G., Feissel D., Inscriptions inédites du musée d’Antioche, T&amp;MByz, 9, 1985, 421-461 (= Feissel D., Documents, droit, diplomatique de l’Empire romain tardif, Paris 2010, 385-398)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Feissel D., Les inscriptions latines dans l’Orient protobyzantin, in Harreither R., Pergola P., Pillinger R., Pülz A. (edd.), Acta Congressus Internationalis XIV Archaeologiae Christianae: Vindobonae 19.-26.9.1999 / Frühes Christentum zwischen Rom und Konstantinopel. Akten des XIV. Internationalen Kongresses für Christliche Archäologie in Wien vom 19. bis 26. September 1999, Città del Vaticano-Wien 2006, 99-129</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ghalia T., Mahfoudh F., Aïn Tebournouk-Tubernuc et sa région de l’Antiquité tardive au Moyen Âge, MEFRA, 115, 2003, 779-807</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gkoutzioukostas A., The Reforms of Constantine the Great in Provincial Administration: a Critical Approach to the Conclusions of Modern Research, Byzantina, 34, 2015-2016, 93-110</bibl>
                    <bibl>Olszaniec S., Praefektura praetorio Italii, Illyrikum i Afryki (312-425 n.e.), Toruń 2014</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Le origini della prefettura del pretorio tardoantica, Roma 2003</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., I dignitari di Costantino: dinamiche di selezione e di ascesa durante la crisi del sistema tetrarchico, in Bonamente G., Lenski N., Lizzi Testa R. (a cura di), Costantino prima e dopo Costantino. Constantine before and after Constantine, Bari 2012, 293-320</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Ancora sulla carriera di Flavius Ablabius, prefetto del pretorio di Costantino, ZPE, 190, 2014, 262-270</bibl>
                    <bibl>Salway B., The Praetorian Prefecture of Africa under Constantine: a Phantom?, in Acta XII Congressus internationalis epigraphiae Graecae et Latinae: Provinciae imperii Romani inscriptionibus descriptae, II, Barcelona 2007, 1281-1286</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sotgiu G., Iscrizioni latine della Sardegna, I, Padova 1961</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vera D., Costantino e il ventre di Roma: a proposito della discussa prefettura d'Africa, in Bonamente G., Lenski N., Lizzi Testa R. (a cura di), Costantino prima e dopo Costantino. Constantine before and after Constantine, Bari 2012, 333-345</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vera D., Costantino, l’Africa e i privilegi dell’Italia: osservazioni sulla redistribuzione statale nel IV secolo, in Vilella Masana J. (ed.), Constantino, ¿el primer emperador cristiano? : religión y política en el siglo IV, Barcelona 2015, 163-180</bibl>              
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                    <div type="commentary" n="1">
                        <p n="1.3"></p>
                    </div>
                <div type="commentary" n="7">
                    <p n="7.1"></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">λ̣[αμ(πρότατοι)]</p>
                    <p n="8.2">οἱ [ἔπ]α̣ρχοι</p>
                    <p n="8.5"></p>
                    <p n="8.9"></p>
                    <p n="8.11"></p>
                </div>
              </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>