<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Fragmentary inscription in honour of a tetrarchic Caesar (Maximinus Daia?) from Perinthus Heraclea by a praet. prefect</title>
                <editor role="edition">Pierfrancesco Porena</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Irene Vagionakis</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="plre" corresp="p. 1003">06</idno>
                <date when="2020-08-21"/>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#us">[- - -]us</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#lost">lost (between 1444 and 1902)</repository>
                        <idno type="invNo"/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#honorary">Honorary inscription for a tetrarchic Caesar, perhaps Maximinus Daia</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="la">Latin</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#marble">marble</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#base">statue base (cod. Vat. Lat. 5250, f.° 3r)</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>unknown</height>
                                        <width>unknown</width>
                                        <depth>unknown</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">unknown</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">uncertain</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One inscribed field.</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#fragmentary">Fragmentary because of two lacuna and two possible erasures.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#unknown">unknown</term>
                                <height>unknown</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city">Perinthus - Heraclea</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Marmara Ereğlisi (Turkey - Türkiye Cumhuriyeti)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province">Europa</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Thracia</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">(not regional before 326 AD)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">public space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p2" notBefore="0307" notAfter="0308">307/308 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found">Ciriaco Pizzicolli (Ancona 1391-Cremona 1452) copied the inscription on the site of the ancient thracian city of <placeName ref="#">Perinthus - Heraclea</placeName> at the end of July 1444 (cod. Vat. Lat. 5250, f.° 3r). Already lost in the second half of the 19th Century.</provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"/>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="la">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="edition">
                    <head>a) Transcription from the manuscript of the “Commentaria” by Ciriaco de’ Pizzicolli (cod. Vat. Lat. 5250, f.° 3r)</head>
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/>Diis auctoribus ad rei publicae amplificandae 
                        <lb n="2"/>gloriam procreato pi <space rend="space"/> n(ost)ro iovio 
                        <lb n="3"/>maximo 
                        <lb n="4"/>ti nobilissimo Caesari VS vcm praef. 
                        <lb n="5"/>praetor.
                    </ab>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="edition">
                    <head>b) Edition from CIL III, 12326</head>
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/><space rend="space"/> DIIS ⋅ AVCTORIBVS 
                        <lb n="2"/>AD ⋅ REI ⋅ PVBLICAE ⋅ AMPLIFICANDAE
                        <lb n="3"/><space rend="space"/> GLORIAM  PROCREATO
                        <lb n="4"/>PI //////////////////////// NOSTRO
                        <lb n="5"/><space rend="space"/> IOVIO  MAXIMO
                        <lb n="6"/>/////////////////////////////// TI
                        <lb n="7"/><space rend="space"/> NOBILISSIMO  CAESARI 
                        <lb n="8"/>////////// VS
                        <lb n="9"/>V ⋅ eM ⋅ PRAEF ⋅ PRAETOR 
                    </ab>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="edition">
                    <head>c) Reconstruction by Porena (in print)</head>
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/>Diis auctoribus 
                        <lb n="2"/>ad rei publicae 
                        <lb n="3"/>amplificandae 
                        <lb n="4"/>gloriam procreato 
                        <lb n="5"/>pi<supplied reason="lost">issimo domino</supplied>
                        <lb n="6"/>nostro Iovio 
                        <lb n="7"/><del rend="erasure"><supplied reason="lost">Galerio Valerio</supplied></del>
                        <lb n="8"/><del rend="erasure">Maxim<supplied reason="lost">in</supplied>o</del>
                        <lb n="9"/><del rend="erasure"><supplied reason="lost" cert="low">victoriosissimo</supplied></del>
                        <lb n="10"/><unclear>et</unclear> nobilissimo Caesari   
                        <lb n="11"/><del rend="erasure"><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/></del>us <expan><abbr>v</abbr><ex>ir</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>em</abbr><ex>inentissimus</ex></expan> 
                        <lb n="12"/><expan><abbr>praef</abbr><ex>ectus</ex></expan> praetor<supplied reason="lost">io</supplied>  
                        <lb n="13"/><supplied reason="lost"><expan><abbr>d</abbr><ex>evotus</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>n</abbr><ex>umini</ex></expan> <expan><abbr>m</abbr><ex>aiestati</ex><abbr>q</abbr><ex>ue</ex></expan> eius</supplied>
                    </ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>See below.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p><note>Text c</note> “By the authority of the gods generated and destined to the glory of expanding the empire, to the most pious our master Iovius, Galerius Valerius Maximinus, [most victorious ?] and most noble Caesar, [- - -]us, praetorian prefect of eminentissimus rank, devoted to his divine spirit and majesty.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p><note>Texte c</note> “Par l’autorité des dieux engendré et destiné à la gloire de l’expansion de l’empire, au très pieux seigneur notre Jovien, Galerius Valerius Maximinus, [très victorieux ?] et très noble César, [- - -]us, le très éminent préfet du prétoire, dévoué à sa divinité et à sa majesté.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p><note>Testo c</note> “Per l’autorità degli dèi generato e destinato alla gloria di espandere l’impero, al piissimo signore nostro Giovio, Galerius Valerius Maximinus, [vittoriosissimo ?] e nobilissimo Cesare, [- - -]us eminentissimo prefetto del pretorio devoto al nume e alla maestà sua.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>The fragmentary inscription in Latin from the city of Perinthus-Heraclea (Marmara Ereğlisi, Turkey; cf. Sayar 1998) is dedicated by a praetorian prefect to a Caesar, whose epithet is <foreign>Iovius</foreign>. The monument dates to the tetrarchic or post-tetrarchic age, 293-324 AD. The inscription was executed between March 293 AD and the end of 309 AD, or between March 317 AD and the end of 324 AD, since we know that the Caesars <foreign>Iovii</foreign> were only active in these two periods (cf. also U. Gehn in <ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail-base.php?record=LSA-1125">LSA 1125</ref>).</p>
                <p>The original inscription is lost. The only transcription to come down to us was made by the Italian merchant and traveller Ciriaco Pizzicolli (1391-1452) in July 1444, while he was ambling among the ruins of the ancient city. The text was inserted by Ciriaco into his <foreign>commentaria</foreign> of the journey through Thrace, Propontis and Samothrace in the second half of 1444 (cf. Bodmer, Mitchell 1976). By 1514, the original manuscript was already lost, but this section of the <foreign>commentaria</foreign> was transcribed in a 16th Century manuscript – <foreign>Vat. Lat.</foreign> 5250, f. 3<foreign>r</foreign> – by an unknown copyist, probably taken from a copy of Ciriaco Pizzicolli’s original <foreign>commentaria</foreign>, or from one of the many manuscripts derived from the traveller’s work. Ciriaco states that he was copying the inscription from a marble base, but says nothing about the size of the base, shape and size of the letters, nor about its location among the ancient buildings. In the second half of the 19th Century, when Mommsen, Hirschfeld and von Domaszewski were working on the edition of CIL III, the inscription was already lost. In 1888, G.B. De Rossi published the transcription from <foreign>Vat. Lat.</foreign> 5250, f. 3<foreign>r</foreign>: this transcription, the only one remaining, does not follow the layout of the original Latin inscription, and contains several lacunae. 
                    So Dessau in 1892 (<ref type="inscription">ILS 0665</ref>) and Mommsen in 1902 (<ref type="inscription">CIL 03, 12326</ref>) tried to reconstruct the layout of the text. The examination of the surviving words of the inscription as it was copied by Pizzicolli makes it possible to provide a new reconstructive hypothesis of the honorary inscription. The key-elements are:</p>
                <p>a) the recipient of the honorary inscription is one single Caesar, as shown by the use of the singular (<foreign>procreato</foreign>, <foreign>nostro</foreign>, <foreign>Iovio</foreign>, and above all <foreign>nobilissimo Caesari</foreign>); Dessau thought that the inscription was dedicated to an Augustus and a Caesar, but significantly he did not attempt to integrate the surviving text; an inscription in honour of both an Augustus and a Caesar is very rare (see Porena in print), and the use of the singular for the honoured Caesar is decisive in concluding that our monument with its inscription was made for only one Tetrarchic Caesar;</p>
                <p>b) this Caesar held the epithet <foreign>Iovius</foreign>, followed by a term transcribed as <foreign>maximo</foreign>, which is placed after the Caesar’s eulogy and after the formula <foreign>dominus noster</foreign>, and before the title <foreign>nobilissimus Caesar</foreign>: the word <foreign>maximo</foreign> occupies the space where the honoured Caesar’s name was;</p>
                <p>c) the dedicant is a single praetorian prefect <foreign>eminentissimus</foreign>;</p>
                <p>d) the final part contains the usual formula of devotion;</p>
                <p>e) the long initial praise and the titulature of the Caesar, as well as the rank and the titulature of the high official – chiselled by means of a few abbreviations – are easily discernible, but the names of the two figures were not read by Ciriaco; the names of the Caesar and of the praetorian prefect are missing, in all probability erased (so already De Rossi 1888 and Dessau, commentary to ILS 0665).</p>
                <p>The most important item of the transcription by Pizzicolli (or by a copyist of his work) is the sequence of the words <foreign>Iovio</foreign> and <foreign>maximo</foreign>, followed by a space without writing. The <foreign>Iovius maximus</foreign> nexus is never attested. The attribute <foreign>maximus</foreign> in our inscription cannot refer to a surname of victory (because no evidence of the ethnic name was on the stone), neither to the office of <foreign>Pontifex</foreign>, nor to other attributes; finally no tetrarchic Caesar held the epithet <foreign>maximus</foreign>. 
                    One plausible hypothesis is that the adjective <foreign>maximo</foreign> of the manuscript <foreign>Vat. Lat.</foreign> 5250, isolated in a single line in Pizzicolli’s transcription, could hide a bad reading of the <foreign>cognomen</foreign> of the <foreign>Caesar Iovius</foreign>: <foreign>MAXIMIANO</foreign>, that is Galerius, or <foreign>MAXIMINO</foreign>, that is Maximinus Daia. It is possible that the rubbing out of the Caesar’s name led Ciriaco to read <foreign>maximo</foreign> an adjective: ⟦<foreign>Maxim</foreign>[<foreign>ian</foreign>]<foreign>o</foreign>⟧, or ⟦<foreign>Maxim</foreign>[<foreign>in</foreign>]<foreign>o</foreign>⟧. It is likely that the <foreign>maximo</foreign> = ⟦<foreign>Maxim</foreign>[<foreign>in</foreign>]<foreign>o</foreign>⟧ was preceded by the names <foreign>Galerio</foreign> and <foreign>Valerio</foreign>. 
                    Should this indeed be the case, then four elements plead for Maximinus Daia being the most plausible solution:</p>
                <p>a) the <foreign>cognomen Maximino</foreign> paleographically comes closer to <foreign>maximo</foreign> than the <foreign>cognomen Maximiano</foreign>;</p>
                <p>b) Perinthus-Heraclea is located on the European coast of the Marmara Sea, an area that passed under the control of Licinius Augustus in the spring of 311 AD. During the war against Maximinus Daia in early 313 AD, the whole area was much fought. 
                    If, as hypothesized, the difficulty in reading the names of the recipient and the dedicator on the stone in question was the result of an erasure, this could be the effect of Licinius’ reprisal against the monuments in honour of Maximinus Daia, by then defeated, and indeed against the prefect who had put them up;</p>
                <p>c) the absolute ablative <foreign>Diis auctoribus</foreign> is unique, and never recurs elsewhere in Latin epigraphy. In the tetrarchical ideology, Diocletian and Maximian are generated by the highest divinities (Jupiter and Hercules) and are creators of divinities, <foreign>auctores</foreign> of the Caesars (Marotta 2007; Cecconi 2018; Kolb 2018). 
                    The concept is exalted in the inscriptions of the Greek-speaking areas during the first and second Tetrarchy. The Caesar is <foreign>pi</foreign>[<foreign>issimus</foreign>]: the eulogy and the <foreign>pietas</foreign> of the Caesar reflects the tetrarchic religious atmosphere in which our Caesar <foreign>Iovius</foreign> is exalted for his mission to expand the <foreign>imperium</foreign> with arms and for his total submission to the will of the Augusti <foreign>Iovii</foreign>. 
                    From the end of 306 AD, Galerius had witnessed the disobedience of Constantine and Maxentius and the assassination of Severus Augustus: the tetrarchic system had gone into crisis because of the revolt of the young sons of the Tetrarchs. In Thrace, in the <foreign>pars</foreign> of the <foreign>Iovius</foreign> Galerius, Maximinus Daia was the only Caesar devoted to the tetrarchic system defended by the <foreign>senior</foreign> Augustus. The praetorian prefect of Galerius could exalt the obedience of Maximinus Daia during the crisis of the late 306/late 309 AD (in 310 AD Maximinus Daia became Augustus);</p>
                <p>d) during the period 284-324 AD, each Augustus had only one praetorian prefect flanking him: when peace reigned between the Augusti, the praetorian prefects formed a united prefectural college as a manifestation of the unity of the <foreign>res publica</foreign>, mirroring the unity of the imperial college and the consular pair (see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret01">PPRET 01</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret02">02</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret03">03</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret08">08</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret09">09</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret16">16</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret17">17</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret18">18</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret22">22</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret23">23</ref>; cf. Feissel 1991). 
                    When the solidarity between the Augusti disappeared, only the single praetorian prefect of each Augustus could erect a monument in honour of his Augustus or possibly his Caesar in the region, directly under his master’s sole control (for an honorary inscription to Maxentius Augustus of the imperial college by his sole one praetorian prefect see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret04">PPRET 04</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret05">05</ref>; for a dedication to Constantine, cited as only Augustus see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret12">PPRET 12</ref>, <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret13">13</ref>). The honorary inscription for a Caesar <foreign>Iovius</foreign> in Thrace by a single praetorian prefect is limited to a short chronological period.</p>
                <p>The anonymous praetorian prefect who commissioned the Perinthus-Heraclea monument was <foreign>vir eminentissimus</foreign>. Whatever his identity, it seems highly likely that he was in office in the Eastern and Illyrian area, the <foreign>pars</foreign> of the <foreign>Iovii</foreign>, before January 310 AD, since from that moment on, Tatius Andronicus and Pompeius Probus, the prefects of Galerius and Licinius Augusti, were active in the region (PLRE I, Andronicus 7, p. 66 and Probus 6, p. 740). The two <foreign>equites</foreign> were promoted to the senatorial order via the ordinary consulate of 310 AD and thus became <foreign>viri clarissimi</foreign>, whereupon they united to form a prefectural college (CLRE, pp. 154-155). Moreover in the first half of 310 AD, the last tetrarchic Caesar, Maximinus Daia, was also acclaimed Augustus by his troops and recognized by Galerius: the monument seen by Pizzicolli on the Straits was executed before the end of 309 AD. 
                    The studies of A. Stefan (2004, 2005, 2006) and S. Corcoran (2006) have shown that from the months immediately following the elevation of Licinius to Augustus at Carnuntum by Galerius and Diocletian on November 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 308 AD, there was a change. Henceforth, the two Caesars of the imperial college imposed by Galerius, Maximinus Daia and Constantine, had the title <foreign>filii Augustorum</foreign> (always plural), and were no longer referred to as <foreign>nobilissimus Caesar</foreign>. The inscription of Perinthus-Heraclea, made in Galerius’ <foreign>pars</foreign>, celebrates a <foreign>nobilissimus Caesar</foreign>, and it must be prior to the imposition of the title <foreign>filius Augustorum</foreign> at the beginning of 309 AD for the Caesars of the ‘fourth Tetrarchy’. Finally, the isolation of the praetorian prefect outside a prefectural college cannot concern the period of the ‘second’ and ‘third Tetrarchy’ (from May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 305 AD to September 307 AD), when at least two Augusti had nominated prefects (Constantius I and Galerius, Galerius and Severus), but the phase of the ‘crisis of the third Tetrarchy’ between September 307 AD (assassination of Severus Augustus) and November 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 308 AD (Licinius is Augustus), when unity in the imperial and in the praefectural college ceased. 
                    In this phase, the imperial and prefectural college, under the aegis of the <foreign>Iovii</foreign> was set up by Galerius Augustus and Maximinus Daia <foreign>nobilissimus Caesar</foreign>, flanked by the sole praetorian prefect of Galerius. The honorary inscription by only one prefect, a <foreign>vir eminentissimus</foreign>, in Galerius’ <foreign>pars</foreign> may have been made when Maximinus Daia was <foreign>nobilissimus Caesar</foreign> between the end of 307 AD (after the death of Severus Augustus in September) and the end of 308 AD (before 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> November).</p>
                <p>It is difficult to identify the praetorian prefect, whose name only the desinence -<foreign>us</foreign> survives. Three prefects are known in the East in 306/310 AD: Flaccinus (Porena 2003, pp. 194-213), Tatius Andronicus and Pompeius Probus (Porena 2003, pp. 189-194). All three could be Galerius Augustus’ praetorian prefects. In this ‘puzzle’ Flaccinus was in office in 305/306 AD and he may well have been the man behind the Perinthus-Heraclea inscription in 307/308 AD, although he could have been replaced by Andronicus between 306 and 307 AD. The order of enumeration of the two prefects-consuls of 310 AD makes it less likely that in 307/308 AD the prefect-awarder is Pompeius Probus, appointed after Andronicus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>De Rossi 1888, p. 369, nt. 4</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>ILS 0665</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>CIL 03, 12326</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>Porena (in print)</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p/>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://db.edcs.eu/epigr/edcs_id.php?p_edcs_id=EDCS-31200897">EDCS 31200897</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://db.edcs.eu/epigr/edcs_id.php?p_edcs_id=EDCS-31300267">EDCS 31300267</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/edh/inschrift/HD068273">EDH 068273</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/database/detail-base.php?record=LSA-1125">LSA 1125</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/text/619676">TM 619676</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/text/495338">TM 495338</ref></bibl>
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Bodmer E.W., Mitchell G., Cyriacus of Ancona’s Journeys in the Propontis and the Northern Aegean, 1444-1445, Philadelphia 1976</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cecconi G.A., Diocleziano e la religione, in Eck W., Puliatti S. (a cura di), Diocleziano: la frontiera giuridica dell’impero, Pavia 2018, 45-62</bibl>
                    <bibl>Corcoran S., Galerius, Maximinus and the Titulature of the Third Tetrarchy, BICS, 49, 2006, 231-240</bibl>
                    <bibl>De Rossi G.B., Series codicum in quibus veteres inscriptiones christianae praesertim urbis Romae sive solae sive ethnicis admixtae descriptae sunt ante saeculum XVI, in ICUR II/1, Roma 1888, 356-387</bibl>
                    <bibl>Feissel D., Praefatio chartarum publicarum. L’intitulé des actes de la préfecture du prétoire du IVe au VIe siècle, T&amp;MByz, 11, 1991, 437-464 (= Id., Documents, droit, diplomatique de l’Empire romain tardif, Paris 2010, 399-428)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kolb F., La Tetrarchia. Struttura, fondamento e ideologia del potere imperiale, in Eck W., Puliatti S. (a cura di), Diocleziano: la frontiera giuridica dell’impero, Pavia 2018, 3-43</bibl>
                    <bibl>Marotta V., Gli dèi governano il mondo. Una nota sul problema della trasmissione del potere imperiale in età tetrarchica, in Fides Humanitas Ius. Studii in onore di Luigi Labruna, V, Napoli 2007, 3271-3310 (extended in Id., Esercizio e trasmissione del potere imperiale (secoli I-IV d.C.). Studi di diritto pubblico romano, Torino 2016, 139-178)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., Le origini della prefettura del pretorio tardoantica, Roma 2003</bibl>
                    <bibl>Porena P., L’iscrizione prefettizia di Perinthus - Heraclea di Tracia: un omaggio a Massimino Daia Cesare durante la crisi della Terza Tetrarchia?, MEFRA in print</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sayar M.H., Perinthos-Heracleia (Marmara Ereglisi) und Umgebung. Geschichte, Testimonia, griechische und lateinische Inschriften, Wien 1998</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stefan A., Le titre de Filius Augustorum de Maximin et de Constantin et la théologie de la Tétrarchie, AntTard, 12, 2004, 329-349</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stefan A., Un rang impérial nouveau à l’époque de la quatrième Tétrarchie: Filius Augustorum. Deuxième partie: considérations historiques, AntTard, 13, 2005, 169-204</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stefan A., Les jeux d’alliances des Tétrarques en 307-309 et l’élévation de Constantin au rang d’Auguste. A propos de CIL, III, 12121, IK 56, 19 et AEp, 2002, 1293, AntTard, 14, 2006, 187-216</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"/>
                </div>
                                
                <div type="commentary" n="7">
                    <p n="7.2"/>
                    <p n="7.y"/>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">v(ir) em(inentissimus)</p>
                    <p n="8.2">praef(ectus) praetor[io]</p>
                    <p n="8.5"/>
                    <p n="8.9"/>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
