<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Inscription relating to building works in Nakida (Niğde) made by the praet. prefect Modestus</title>
                <editor role="edition">Andrea Bernier</editor>
                <editor role="encoding">Irene Vagionakis</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename" n="new" corresp="pp. 605-608">68</idno>
                <date when="2020-05-08"/>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person><persName ref="#Modestus"><name type="gentilicium">Domitius</name> <name type="cognomen">Modestus</name></persName></person>
                </listPerson>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="#unknown">unknown</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            <term type="textType" ref="#building">building inscription</term>
                            <term type="rhythm" ref="#prose">prose</term>
                        </summary>
                        <textLang mainLang="grc">Greek</textLang>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material ref="#stone">stone</material>
                                    <objectType ref="#unknown">unknown</objectType>
                                    <dimensions>
                                        <height>unknown</height>
                                        <width>unknown</width>
                                        <depth>unknown</depth>
                                    </dimensions>
                                    <rs type="inscribed_field_reuse">no</rs>
                                    <rs type="monument_reuse">yes; built into St. John Church</rs>
                                    <rs type="opistographic">no</rs>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>One inscribed field (frons).</p>
                                    <rs type="execution" ref="#chiselled">chiselled</rs>
                                    <rs type="preservation" ref="#damaged">Incomplete.</rs>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <term ref="#unknown">unknown (no images available)</term>
                                <height>unknown</height>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>
                                <placeName type="ancient_city" ref="#Nakida">Nakida (but Tyana / Kemerhisar cannot be excluded)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="modern_city">Niğde (Turkey)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="province" ref="#Cappadocia">Cappadocia (or Cappadocia Secunda, if later than September 372 AD)</placeName>
                                <placeName type="diocese">Pontica</placeName>
                                <placeName type="prefecture">Oriens</placeName>
                                <placeName type="ancient_location" ref="#public">public space</placeName>
                            </origPlace>
                            <origDate period="#p7" notBefore="0370" notAfter="0377">370/377 AD</origDate>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found">built into the Church of St. John in <placeName ref="#">Niğde</placeName></provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed"/>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="">
            <desc/>
        </graphic>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="grc">
                    <ab>
                        <lb n="1"/>Ἐπὶ <expan><abbr>Δομ</abbr><ex>ετίου</ex></expan> <supplied reason="lost">Μ</supplied>οδέ<supplied reason="lost">σ</supplied>του το<supplied reason="lost">ῦ</supplied>
                        <lb n="2"/>λαμπροτάτου ἐπάρχο<supplied reason="lost">υ</supplied>
                        <lb n="3"/>τῶν πρετωρίων καὶ
                        <lb n="4"/>τοῦτο ἔργον ἀπὸ <supplied reason="lost">θ</supplied><lb break="no" n="5"/><supplied reason="lost">εμ</supplied>ελίων ἐκτίσθ<supplied reason="lost">η</supplied>.
                    </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <p>Edition based on Rott 1908, p. 379, nr. 102.</p>
                <p><app loc="4-5"><note>θ=[ε]<unclear>μ</unclear>ελίων or θ[ε]=<unclear>μ</unclear>ελίων IK 55, Tyana, 01, 26</note></app></p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>“When Domitius Modestus, of clarissimus rank, was praetorian prefect, this work was built from the ground.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="fr">
                <p>“Lorsque Domitius Modestus était le clarissime préfet du prétoire, cet ouvrage a été construit de toutes pièces.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="it">
                <p>“Quando il chiarissimo Domitius Modestus era prefetto del pretorio, quest’opera fu costruita dalle fondamenta.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                <p>Built into the Church of St. John in the city of Niğde (Turkey), the inscription was seen in 1906 by H. Rott. The text was published in his book on the Christian “Monuments of Asia Minor,” with a commentary by W. Weber (Rott 1908, p. 379, nr. 102). H. Grégoire, who had seen the inscription in 1907, confirmed the reading of Rott (Grégoire 1909, p. 131, nt. 1). The new edition of the text provided in 2000 by J. Nollé (IK 55, Tyana, 01, 26) reproduces the text copied and published by Rott. No information survives on the support of the inscription, nor on its current location. 
                    While other inscriptions found in Niğde can be attributed to a rural settlement that existed there in the imperial period, it is likely that our document was carried into the city from the neighbouring town of Kemerhisar, the ancient Tyana, one of the main centres of Cappadocia and capital of Cappadocia Secunda after the splitting of the province in 372 AD (Grégoire 1909, p. 131; cf. Berges-Nollé 2000, p. 198; on the division of Cappadocia see below). The text celebrates the construction of a building "from the ground" during the praetorian prefecture of Domitius Modestus.</p>
                <p>Modestus attained the praetorian prefecture of the East under the emperor Valens. This talented administrator, probably from the province of Arabia and trained in law, began his career in the last years of the reign of Constantius II (PLRE I, Modestus 2, pp. 605-608; Dagron 1974, pp. 242-244, pp. 246-247). 
                    Perhaps assessor of the praetorian prefect of the Illyricum Anatolius (Lib., ep. 582-583 with Dagron 1974, p. 242; cf. Bradbury 2000, p. 177; <foreign>contra</foreign> PLRE I, Domitius 1, pp. 263-264, followed by Laniado 2018, p. 418; on Vindaeonius Anatolius see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret47">PPRET 47</ref>), he was then promoted to the office of <foreign>comes Orientis</foreign>, a position that he held from 358 AD to 362 AD. Many letters of Libanius addressed to Modestus in this period show both the intense activity of the <foreign>comes</foreign> in the administration and his great mobility across the provinces of the eastern diocese (Seeck 1906, pp. 213-218; Petit 1994, pp. 165-172, nr. 200; Bradbury 2004, pp. 255-257). 
                    A Christian under Constantius, he apostatised under Julian, who promoted Modestus to the urban prefecture of Constantinople in the Summer of 362 AD; he was discharged from this position at the beginning of the reign of Valentinian and Valens in favour of Iovinus (Dagron 1974, pp. 242-245). 
                    But after some years (and another conversion to the Arian positions of the new ruler Valens), he was called  to service, again as urban prefect of Constantinople. It was during this mandate that he completed the construction of an important reservoir that he had begun during his first prefecture (MGH AA 09, <ref type="source">Chron. Min. 01, p. 241</ref> = Cons. Const. s.a. 369; cf. <ref type="source">Not. Urb. Const. 12, 12</ref>: <foreign>cisterna Modestiaca</foreign>; see Mango 1995, pp. 13-15). 
                    At the end of the Gothic war in 370 AD, the emperor Valens promoted Modestus to the position of praetorian prefect of the East: he kept this office until the end of 377 AD (Dagron 1974, pp. 246-247, revising the chronology of PLRE I, p. 606 for the beginning of the praetorian prefecture; cf. Errington 2000, pp. 902-904; Brauch 2002, pp. 64-65; Schmidt-Hofner 2008, pp. 552-553; Modestus is still attested in service on November 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 377 AD: <ref type="source">CI 11, 62, 05</ref>; possibly replaced by Aburgius in 378 AD: see PLRE I, p. 5). 
                    This very long tenure, in itself a testimony to the abilities of Modestus as an administrator, is not unusual for the latter part of the reign of Valens, when all the higher posts of the administration were continuously held by a small group of trusted officials (see Lenski 2002, pp. 62-63). 
                    Indeed, the prominence of Modestus is attested by the honour of the consulate that was bestowed upon him in 372 AD. Considering that Valens had never conferred the consulate on a civilian officer before, this was an honour indeed (he was <foreign>consul prior</foreign>, with Fl. Arinthaeus: CLRE, pp. 5, 278-279). Modestus is the addressee of the majority of the legislation issued of Valens in this period (list of the constitutions in PLRE I, p. 607; for the chronology cf. Schmidt-Hofner 2008; Modestus also fixed standards for weights and measures in the eastern prefecture: see Corcoran 1995, pp. 377-384; for weights and measures fixed by the Eastern praetorian prefect Tatianus, see <ref type="ppret" corresp="ppret88">PPRET 88</ref>). 
                    According to Ammianus, the prefect increased his power in jurisdiction by dissuading the emperor from personally examining the legal cases (<ref type="source">Amm. 30, 04, 01-02</ref>, with Tränkle 2008, pp. 505-508; cf. den Boeft et alii 2015, pp. 61-62); Modestus, who had already presided over the trials of Scytopolis under Constantius II, also presided over the trials of withcraft and treason in Antiochia in 372 AD (<ref type="source">Amm. 19, 12, 06</ref>; <ref type="source">Amm. 29, 01, 11-12</ref>; see Matthews 1989, pp. 217-226; Lenski 2002, pp. 223-232).</p>
                <p>The Christian writers give ample evidence of the role played by Modestus in the efforts of the emperor to impose conformity on the Christianity of the eastern empire (Lenski 2002, pp. 234-263). In these sources we also find a connection between the activity of the prefect and the province of Cappadocia, where in 370 AD Modestus unsuccessfully tried to persuade Basil of Caesarea to join the Homoian Church supported by the emperor (De Salvo 1983, pp. 137-153; Van Dam 1986, pp. 53-76; Rousseau 1998, pp. 351-353; on the letters of Basil addressed to the prefect see Bernardi 1992, pp. 7-19; Pouchet 1992, pp. 319-325, 610-613; Gascou 1997, pp. 189-204; the journeys of the <foreign>comitatus</foreign> through Cappadocia in 370 AD are discussed in Destephen 2016, pp. 327-332). 
                    Although our text has nothing to do with the religious conflict, from the epistolary of the same bishop we know that at this time the region was split into two parts and that Tyana, the city from which the inscription likely comes, was made the capital of the new province of Cappadocia Secunda (the division came probably into force from September 372 AD: see Jones 1971, pp. 182-190; Kopeček 1974, pp. 320-327; Van Dam 2002, pp. 28-36; Metivier 2005, pp. 41-43). 
                    This transformation resulted in the need to provide the city with new structures for the requirements of the administration. The building to which our inscription was attached, might have been created in this context, under the responsibility of the praetorian prefecture. The text emphasizes that the construction was built "from the ground," i.e., that it was a new structure (ἀπὸ θεμελίων; on the occurrence of this formula and of the Latin version <foreign>a fundamentis</foreign> in the epigraphy of the period, see Lenski 2002, pp. 375-379, 393-401, with an overview on the building activity under Valentinian and Valens) and the words καὶ τοῦτο ἔργον seems to imply that this was not the only work undertaken in the area under the prefecture of Domitius Modestus (cf. Berges-Nollé 2000, p. 203).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="editions">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref>Rott 1908, p. 379, nr. 102</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref>IK 55, Tyana, 01, 26</ref></bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="images">
                <p/>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="links">
                <p>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://inscriptions.packhum.org/text/287469">PH 287469</ref></bibl>
                    <bibl><ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/text/928582">TM 928582</ref></bibl>
                 </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" subtype="other">
                <p>
                    <bibl>Berges D., Nollé J., Tyana. Archäologisch-historische Untersuchungen zum südwestlichen Kappadokien, I (= IK 55, Tyana, 01), Bonn 2000</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bernardi J., La lettre 104 de saint Basile, le préfet du prétoire Domitius Modestus et le statut des clercs, in Dupleix A. (ed.), Recherches et tradition. Mélanges patristiques offerts à Henri Crouzel, Paris 1992, 7-19</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bradbury S., A Sophistic Prefect: Anatolius of Berytus in the Letters of Libanius, CPh, 95, 2000, 172-186</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bradbury S. (transl. by), Selected Letters of Libanius from the age of Constantius and Julian, Liverpool 2004</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brauch T., Notes on the Prefects of Constantinople AD 366-369, Byzantion, 72, 2002, 42-104</bibl>
                    <bibl>Corcoran S., The Praetorian Prefect Modestus and Hero of Alexandria’s "Stereometrica", Latomus, 54, 1995, 377-384</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dagron G., Naissance d’une capitale. Constantinople et ses institutions de 330 à 451, Paris 1974</bibl>
                    <bibl>De Salvo L., Basilio di Cesarea e Modesto: un vescovo di fronte al potere statale, in Basilio di Cesarea. La sua età, la sua opera e il basilianesimo in Sicilia. Atti del Congresso Internazionale (Messina 3-6 XII 1979), vol. 1, Messina 1983, 137-153</bibl>
                    <bibl>Den Boeft J., Drijvers J.W., den Hengst D., Teitler H.C., Philological and Historical Commentary on Ammianus Marcellinus XXX, Leiden-Boston 2015</bibl>
                    <bibl>Destephen S., Le voyage impérial dans l'antiquité tardive. Des Balkans au Proche-Orient, Paris 2016</bibl>
                    <bibl>Errington M., Themistius and His Emperors, Chiron, 30, 2000, 861-904</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gascou J., Les privilèges du clergé d’après la Lettre 104 de S. Basile, RSR, 71, 1997, 189-204</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grégoire H., Rapport sur un voyage d’exploration dans le Pont et en Cappadoce, BCH, 33, 1909, 3-169</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jones A.H.M., The Cities of the Eastern Roman Provinces, Oxford 1971 (rev. ed.)</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kopeček Th.A., Curial Displacements and Flight in Later Fourth Century Cappadocia, Historia, 23, 1974, 319-342</bibl>
                    <bibl>Laniado A., L'aristocratie sénatoriale de Constantinople et la préfecture du prétoire d'Orient, in Morrisson C., Sodini J.-P. (éd.), Constantinople réelle et imaginaire. Autour de l'œuvre de Gilbert Dagron, Paris 2018, 409-454</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lenski N., Failure of Empire. Valens and the Roman State in the Fourth Century A.D., Berkeley-Los Angeles-London 2002</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mango C., The Water Supply of Constantinople, in Mango C., Dagron G. (eds), Constantinople and Its Hinterland, Cambridge 1995</bibl>
                    <bibl>Matthews J., The Roman Empire of Ammianus, London 1989</bibl>
                    <bibl>Métivier S., La Cappadoce (IVe-VIe siècle). Une histoire provinciale de l’Empire romain d’Orient, Paris 2005</bibl>
                    <bibl>Petit P., Les fonctionnaires dans l’œuvre de Libanius. Analyse prosopographique, Paris 1994</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pouchet R., Basile le Grand et son univers d’après sa correspondance, Rome 1992</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rott H., Kleinasiatische Denkmäler aus Pisidien, Pamphylien, Kappadokien und Lykien, Leipzig 1908</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rousseau P., Basil of Caesarea, Berkeley-Los Angeles-London 1998</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schmidt-Hofner S., Die Regesten der Kaiser Valentinian und Valens in den Jahren 364 bis 375 n. Chr, ZRG, 125, 2008, 498-602</bibl>
                    <bibl>Seeck O., Die Briefe des Libanius, Leipzig 1906</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tränkle H., Modestus und Kaiser Valens (Amm. 30,4,2), Hermes, 136, 2008, 505-508</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Dam R., Emperor, Bishops, and Friends in Late Antique Cappadocia, JThS, 37, 1986, 53-76</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Dam R., Kingdom of Snow, Philadelphia 2002</bibl>
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" subtype="prefects">
                <div type="commentary" n="1">
                    <p n="1.1"/>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="7">
                    <p n="7.3"/>
                </div>
                
                <div type="commentary" n="8">
                    <p n="8.1">λαμπροτάτου</p>
                    <p n="8.2">ἐπάρχο[υ] τῶν πρετωρίων</p>
                    <p n="8.5"/>
                    <p n="8.9"/>
                    <p n="8.11"/>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
