<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>
                    <seg xml:lang="en">Introduction</seg>
                    <seg xml:lang="fr">Avant-propos</seg>
                    <seg xml:lang="it">Introduzione</seg>
                </title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename">Introduction</idno>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attributions-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc><p>Born digital document.</p></sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="commentary" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
                    <head>The epigraphic database PPRET Inscriptions</head>
                    <p>The database “PPRET Inscriptions. The Inscriptions pertaining to the Praetorian Prefects from 284 to 395 AD” is an open access research tool developed by the team of the <ref corresp="team.html">Projet PPRET</ref> “Les préfets du prétoire de l’Empire romain tardif. Une élite face à la crise” / “The Praetorian Prefects in the Later Roman Empire: An elite in a crisis context”, created and directed by prof. Pierfrancesco Porena (Università Roma Tre - UMR 7044 “Archéologie et histoire ancienne: Méditerranée – Europe” ARCHIMÈDE, Université de Strasbourg).</p>
                    <p>The prosopographical approach to the praetorian prefects of the Late Empire, as implemented within the framework of the PPRET Project, makes it possible to characterise these dignitarries as an ‘elite’, an aristocracy by virtue of its control over the civil administration, whose culture, religious orientations and behaviours can be studied in a comprehensive manner. 
                        The social origins of the members of this leading group, as well as the modalities of access within it, can also be examined in the light of this procedure, as well as the evolution of all these parameters over time, in particular with regard to the evolutions of the administration and the political and military changes of Late Antiquity (hence the notion of ‘crisis’, introduced in the subtitle of the PPRET project).</p>
                    <p>Project PPRET is entirely funded by the “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaire Gutenberg</ref> 2019”, an international scientific prize won by prof. Pierfrancesco Porena. On a scientific and administrative level, Project PPRET is part of the cross-disciplinary programme “Aristocracies and interculturality” of the UMR 7044 ARCHIMÈDE (University of Strasbourg), directed by prof. Michel Humm.</p>
                    <p>Within the programme of the PPRET project, the publication of some of the research products is planned in traditional printed editions (monographs and the proceedings of the International Conference in Strasbourg “La préfecture du prétoire tardo-antique et ses titulaires - IV<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>-VI<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle”, held in May 2021). These works are devoted to thematic studies on the late antique praetorian prefecture as an institution and a political-administrative instrument. The prefects are examined in relation to the political and social context of the period and space in which they were active.</p>
                    <p>But a fundamental objective of the Project is to update the epigraphic sources on the late antique praetorian prefects and to re-read the known sources. The first volume of the “Prosopography of the Later Roman Empire”, covering the whole of the 4th Century AD, was published in 1971, fifty years ago. The PPRET project aims to facilitate the updating of epigraphic sources concerning the prosopography of the praetorian prefects in the period 284-395 AD. 
                        This period is affluent in figures of praetorian prefects, the office the office takes its regional form, and Latin or Greek inscriptions concerning to the praetorian prefects have increased, while some of them, already known, have been reinterpreted. The epigraphic texts are often decisive in reconstructing the chronology of the career of the senators-office holders, in perceiving the evolution of the regional prefecture along the 4th Century AD, and they provide, as monuments, a series of important evidences (political, administrative, social and cultural), which calls for a re-examination of these texts.</p>
                    <p>In order to make available up-to-date Latin and Greek inscriptions relating to the prefects of this period, the <ref corresp="team.html">project team</ref> created and implemented the PPRET Inscriptions database.</p>
                    <p>The open access database publishes all surviving Greek and Latin inscriptions relating to the praetorian prefects in charge during the period 284-395 AD. It contains 98 inscriptions in chronological order (of these, 30 do not appear in “PLRE” I; the Latin and Greek texts of several inscriptions have been critically reviewed).</p>
                    <p>Each entry contains: prosopographical and chronological coordinates (in relation to “PLRE” I), an edition of the Latin or Greek text, with a critical apparatus, information on the form of the inscription, its provenance and conservation, its author, the praetorian prefect(s) mentioned, translations into three modern languages (English, French, Italian), a substantial commentary and an up-to-date bibliography.</p>
                    <p>A simple or combined research tool, which is fairly articulated, allows the Greek and Latin inscriptions concerning the praetorian prefects of the period to be interrogated by means of search engines. It provides a wide range of information on the origin and material aspect of the inscribed monuments, on the content of the texts inscribed in Latin and Greek, on the praetorian prefects mentioned (onomastics, titulature, the relationship between the dedicator of the monument and the honoree, etc.).</p>
                    <p>The work, started in March 2020, will be followed by regular updating of the database (bibliography, discovery of new inscriptions, etc.). The database is online from <emph>February 2022</emph>. It is located on a server of the “Huma-Num” network, and is part of the digital offer of the “MISHA” Strasbourg.</p>
                </div>
                    
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
                    <head>Technical aspects of the PPRET Inscriptions database</head>
                    <div>
                        <p>The creation of the PPRET database involved two work phases: the encoding of the inscriptions in EpiDoc XML and the actual creation of the database through the EpiDoc Front-End Services (EFES).</p>
                    </div>
                
                    <div>
                        <head type="subheading">Encoding of the inscriptions in EpiDoc XML</head>
                        <p><ref corresp="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/">EpiDoc</ref> is the international standard for the digital edition of ancient documents, especially inscriptions. It is a subset of the <ref corresp="https://tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiative</ref> (TEI) standard for the digital edition of literary and historical documents. 
                            It is based on XML (eXtensible Markup Language), a widely spread and highly compatible semantic markup language, which is based on the meaning of the text instead of on its appearance and which is currently the most advanced and spread approach for the creation of digital scholarly editions.</p>
                        <p>Among the many benefits of a semantic markup there are its high compatibility, interoperability and flexibility, which imply a long term sustainability and a low risk of obsolescence, and the fact that it allows the creation of enriched online publications with considerable usability benefits in terms of searching and browsing of the encoded materials.</p>
                        <p>The adaptation of the EpiDoc XML template to fit the PPRET specific needs led to the creation of a PPRET EpiDoc XML template, which was used for the encoding of all the documents included in the PPRET Inscriptions database, carried out by Irene Vagionakis, Eleonora Angius and Giordana Franceschini.</p>
                    </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="subheading">Creation of the database with EFES (EpiDoc Front-End Services)</head>
                    <p><ref corresp="https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES/wiki">EpiDoc Front-End Services</ref> is an open-source tool for the online publication of texts encoded specifically in EpiDoc, developed in 2017 by the Institute of Classical Studies of the University of London. It is the epigraphic specialisation of <ref corresp="https://kcl-ddh.github.io/kiln/">Kiln</ref>, a similar tool for the online publication of texts in TEI, developed in 2012 by the Department of Digital Humanities of the King’s College London.</p>
                    <p>The main points of strength of EFES that led to its adoption are the fact that is was specifically designed to be used with EpiDoc ancient documents, that it is easily customisable and that it is not just a publishing tool, but also a useful tool for testing and analysis purposes during construction.</p>
                    <p>The customisation of EFES for PPRET purposes was made by Irene Vagionakis and involved, in particular, the adaptation of graphics, the creation of a dedicated XSLT template to display the PPRET XML template properly and the enhancement of EFES search facilities, including especially the addition of very specific browse filters and of a facility to perform searches limited to the inscription texts only.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
                    <head>How to cite the database PPRET Inscriptions</head>
                    <p>In paper publications, please quote the individual entry: PPRET 01.</p>
                    <p>In electronic publications, please insert a link to the entry directly (the author of each entry is indicated in the top right-hand corner).</p>
                    <p>If you want to quote the whole database PPRET Inscriptions:
                        <lb/>AUTHORS: P. Porena (dir.), E. Angius, A. Bernier, G. Franceschini, P. Porena, I. Vagionakis, 
                        <lb/>TITLE: PPRET Inscriptions. The Inscriptions pertaining to the praetorian prefects from 284 to 395 AD. Edition and study directed by P. Porena, realised by the authors, with digital edition performed by I. Vagionakis 
                        <lb/>PROJECT: Projet Chaire Gutenberg 2019 "Les Préfets du prétoire de l'Empire tardif: une élite face à la crise"
                        <lb/>EDITION: Strasbourg (MISHA) 2022
                        <lb/>WEB ADDRESS: <ref corresp="http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr">http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr</ref>
                    </p>
                    <p>The database is a digital publication identified by the following ISSN code:  ...</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
                    <head>Credits</head>
                    <p>The funding of the Project PPRET “Les Préfets du prétoire de l'Empire tardif: une élite face à la crise” and its database PPRET Inscriptions came from the “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Cercle Gutenberg</ref>”, which in 2019 funded Prof. <ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/titulaires-et-laureats/titulaires-chaires-gutenberg/biographie-des-laureats/chaires-2019/pierfrancesco-porena/">P. Porena</ref> with a “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaires Gutenberg</ref>” award.</p>
                    <p>Many thanks to Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/michel-humm/">Michel Humm</ref> for having welcomed the Project PPRET into the <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/">UMR 7044 (Archimède)</ref> Research Unit (University of Strasbourg) and to <ref corresp="https://www.misha.fr/">MISHA of Strasbourg</ref> for having accepted the PPRET Inscriptions database into its open access digital platform.</p>
                    <p>Remerciements particuliers au Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/olivier-huck/">Olivier Huck</ref> (UMR 7044 ARCHIMÈDE, Université de Strasbourg) pour son soutien constant et irremplaçable au Projet PPRET.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
                    <head>License</head>
                        <p>All the XML, HTML and PDF contents of the database<!--, which is hosted on a server provided by the <ref corresp="https://www.huma-num.fr/">Huma-Num</ref> Digital Humanities research infrastructure thanks to an agreement with <ref corresp="https://www.misha.fr/">MISHA</ref> / <ref corresp="https://www.unistra.fr/">Université de Strasbourg</ref>,--> are released in open access mode under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License (<ref corresp="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</ref>).
                            According to the license terms, access is free to all scholars, but the reuse of the materials is subject to explicitly giving appropriate credit (including the following statement: <quote>This material is derived from the PPRET Inscriptions database, by Porena et al., hosted at <ref corresp="http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr">ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr</ref>, ISSN ...</quote>), providing a link to the same CC license and indicating if changes were made. 
                            The materials cannot be reused for commercial purposes.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
                    <head>Linked Open Data</head>
                    <p>According to the Linked Open Data principles, links to other open access online resources (like <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/ala2004/">ALA</ref>, <ref corresp="https://census.bbaw.de/">Census</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.epigraphik.uni-hamburg.de/">EDAK</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.edb.uniba.it/">EDB</ref>, <ref corresp="http://db.edcs.eu/">EDCS</ref>, <ref corresp="https://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/">EDH</ref>, <ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/">EDR</ref>, 
                        <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/insaph/iaph2007/">IAph</ref>, <ref corresp="http://telota.bbaw.de/ig/">IG Online</ref>, <ref corresp="https://iospe.kcl.ac.uk/">IOSPE<hi rend="superscript">³</hi></ref>, <ref corresp="http://inslib.kcl.ac.uk/irt2009/">IRT</ref>, <ref corresp="http://sicily.classics.ox.ac.uk/">I.Sicily</ref>, <ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/">LSA</ref>, <ref corresp="http://mizar.unive.it/mqdq/public/">MQDQ</ref>, <ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/">PHI</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/">Trismegistos</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.ubi-erat-lupa.org/">Ubi Erat Lupa</ref>) have been inserted systematically.
                        The inclusion of links to PPRET Inscriptions resources in other open online resources is warmly encouraged.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" xml:lang="fr">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
                    <head>La base de données épigraphiques PPRET Inscriptions</head>
                    <p>La base de données “PPRET Inscriptions. The Inscriptions pertaining to the Praetorian Prefects from 284 to 395 AD” est un outil de recherche en libre accès développé par le Team du <ref corresp="team.html">Projet PPRET</ref> “Les préfets du prétoire de l’Empire romain tardif. Une élite face à la crise” / “The Praetorian Prefects in the Later Roman Empire: An elite in a crisis context”, créé et dirigé par le prof. Pierfrancesco Porena (Università Roma Tre - UMR 7044 “Archéologie et histoire ancienne: Méditerranée – Europe” ARCHIMÈDE, Université de Strasbourg).</p>
                    <p>L’approche prosopographique des préfets du prétoire de l’empire tardif, telle qu’elle est mise en oeuvre dans le cadre du Projet PPRET, permet de caractériser les préfets du prétoire comme une «élite», une «aristocratie de fonction» dont la culture, les orientations religieuses, et les pratiques caractéristiques peuvent être envisagées par le moyen de mises en séries. Les origines sociales des membres de ce groupe dirigeant, ainsi que les modalités d’accès en son sein peuvent, elles aussi, être examinées à la lumière de ce procédé, de même que l’évolution de l’ensemble de ces paramètres au fil du temps, en particulier au regard des évolutions de l’administration et des bouleversements politiques et militaires de l’Antiquité tardive (d’où la notion de «crise», introduite dans le sous-titre du projet PPRET).</p>
                    <p>Le Projet PPRET est entièrement financé par le prix “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaire Gutenberg</ref> 2019”, prix scientifique international remporté par le professeur Porena. Sur un plan scientifique et administratif le Projet PPRET s’inscrit dans le cadre du programme transversal «Aristocraties et interculturalité» de l’UMR 7044 ARCHIMÈDE (Université de Strasbourg), dirigé par le prof. Michel Humm.</p>
                    <p>Dans le cadre du Projet PPRET, la publication d'une partie des résultats prévoit des éditions imprimées traditionnelles (monographies et les actes du Colloque International de Strasbourg “La préfecture du prétoire tardo-antique et ses titulaires - IV<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>-VI<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle”, tenu en Mai 2021). Ces oeuvres sont consacrés à des études thématiques sur la préfecture du prétoire tardo-antique en tant qu'institution et instrument politico-administratif. Les préfets y sont examinés en relation avec le contexte politique et social de la période et de l'espace dans lesquels ils étaient actifs.</p>
                    <p>Mais un objectif fondamental du Projet est mettre à jour les sources épigraphiques sur les préfets du prétoire de l’Antiquité tardive et relire les sources connues. Le premier volume de la “Prosopography of the Later Roman Empire”, couvrant l'ensemble du IVe siècle, est paru en 1971, il y a cinquante ans. Le projet PPRET vise à faciliter la mise à jour des sources épigraphiques sur la prosopographie des préfets du prétoire de la période 284-395 ap. J.-C. 
                        Cette période est riche en préfets du prétoire, elle connaît la transformation régionale de la fonction, et possède un patrimoine épigraphique qui a été élargi ou qui a été réexaminé au cours des dernières décennies. Les textes épigraphiques sont souvent décisifs pour reconstituer la chronologie de la carrière des sénateurs titulaires, l'évolution de la préfecture du prétoire régionale au IV<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle de notre ère, et fournissent, en tant que monuments, une série d'informations essentielles de nature politique, administrative, sociale et culturelle, ce qui appelle un réexamen précis de ces textes. Afin de mettre à disposition les inscriptions latines et grecques actualisées relatives aux préfets de cette période, l'<ref corresp="team.html">équipe du projet</ref> a créé et mis en œuvre la base de données PPRET Inscriptions.</p>
                    <p>La base de données en libre accès publie l'ensemble de l'épigraphie en grec et en latin qui subsiste concernant les préfets du prétoire de la période 284-395 ap. J.-C. Elle rassemble par ordre chronologique 98 inscriptions (parmi celles-ci, 30 n'apparaissent pas dans la “PLRE” I; les textes latins et grecs de plusieurs inscriptions ont été relus de manière critique).</p>
                    <p>Chaque fiche contient: des coordonnées prosopographiques et chronologiques (en relation avec la “PLRE” I), une édition du texte latin ou grec, avec un appareil critique, les informations relatives à la forme de l’inscription, à sa provenance et à sa conservation, à son auteur, au(x) préfet(s) du prétoire mentionné(s), des traductions (en anglais, français, italien), un commentaire substantiel et une bibliographie à jour. 
                        Un cadre de recherches simples ou combinées, assez articulé, permet d’interroger par le biais de moteurs de recherche les inscriptions grecques et latines concernant les préfets du prétoire de la période visée. Il fournit un large éventail d'informations sur l'origine et l'aspect matériel des monuments inscrits, sur le contenu des textes inscrits en latin et en grec, sur les préfets du prétoire mentionnés (onomastique, titulature, relation dédicateur-dédié, etc.).</p>
                    <p>Le travail, commencé en mars 2020, sera suivi par une mise à jour régulière de la base de données (bibliographie, découverte de nouvelles inscriptions, etc.). La mise en ligne de la base de données est en ligne de <emph>février 2022</emph>. Elle est située sur un serveur de la plateforme “Huma-Num”, et fait partie de l'offre numérique de la “MISHA” Strasbourg. </p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
                    <head>Aspects techniques de la base de données épigraphiques PPRET Inscriptions</head>
                    <div>
                        <p>La création de la base de données PPRET a comporté deux phases de travail: l'encodage des inscriptions en EpiDoc XML et la création proprement dite de la base de données avec EpiDoc Front-End Services (EFES).</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div>
                        <head type="subheading">Encodage des inscriptions en EpiDoc XML</head>
                        <p><ref corresp="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/">EpiDoc</ref> est le standard international pour l’édition numérique de documents anciens, en particulier les inscriptions. Il s’agit d’un sous-ensemble de le standard <ref corresp="https://tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiative</ref> (TEI) pour l’édition numérique de documents littéraires et historiques. 
                            Elle est basée sur le langage XML (eXtensible Markup Language), un langage de balisage sémantique largement répandu et hautement compatible, qui se fonde sur la signification du texte plutôt que sur son apparence et qui constitue actuellement l’approche la plus avancée et la plus répandue pour la création d’éditions savantes numériques.</p>
                        <p>Parmi les nombreux avantages d'un balisage sémantique, citons sa grande compatibilité, son interopérabilité et sa flexibilité, qui impliquent une durabilité à long terme et un faible risque d’obsolescence, ainsi que le fait qu’il permet la création de publications en ligne enrichies, avec des avantages considérables en termes de facilité d’utilisation pour la recherche et la navigation dans les matériaux encodés.</p>
                        <p>L’adaptation du modèle EpiDoc XML aux besoins spécifiques de la PPRET a conduit à la création d’un modèle PPRET XML EpiDoc, qui a été utilisé pour l’encodage de tous les documents inclus dans la base de données PPRET Inscriptions, réalisé par Irene Vagionakis, Eleonora Angius et Giordana Franceschini.</p> 
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="subheading">Création de la base de données avec EFES (EpiDoc Front-End Services)</head>
                        <p><ref corresp="https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES/wiki">EpiDoc Front-End Services</ref> est un outil open-source pour la publication en ligne de textes encodés spécifiquement en EpiDoc, développé en 2017 par l’Institute of Classical Studies - University of London. 
                            Il s’agit de la spécialisation épigraphique de <ref corresp="https://kcl-ddh.github.io/kiln/">Kiln</ref>, un outil similaire pour la publication en ligne de textes en TEI, développé en 2012 par le Department of Digital Humanities du King’s College London.</p>
                        <p>Les principaux points forts d’EFES qui ont conduit à son adoption sont le fait qu’il a été spécifiquement conçu pour être utilisé avec les documents anciens EpiDoc, qu’il est facilement personnalisable et qu’il ne s’agit pas seulement d’un outil de publication, mais aussi d’un outil utile à des fins de test et d’analyse pendant la construction.</p>
                        <p>La personnalisation d’EFES pour PPRET a été réalisée par Irene Vagionakis et a impliqué, en particulier, l’adaptation des graphiques, la création d’un modèle XSLT dédié pour afficher correctement le modèle XML PPRET et le développement des fonctions de recherche d’EFES, notamment l’ajout de filtres de navigation très spécifiques et d’une fonction permettant d’effectuer des recherches limitées aux seuls textes d’inscription.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
                    <head>Comment citer la base de données PPRET Inscriptions</head>
                    <p>Publication papier, veuillez citer la fiche: PPRET 01.</p>
                    <p>Publication électronique, veuillez ouvrir un lien vers l'adresse de la fiche directement (l'auteur de chaque fiche est indiqué dans le coin supérieur droit).</p>
                    <p>Si vous souhaitez citer l'ensemble de la base de données Inscriptions PPRET:
                        <lb/>AUTEURS: P. Porena (dir.), E. Angius, A. Bernier, G. Franceschini, P. Porena, I. Vagionakis, 
                        <lb/>TITRE: Inscriptions du PPRET. Les inscriptions relatives aux préfets prétoriens de 284 à 395 ap. Edition et étude dirigées par P. Porena, réalisées par les auteurs, avec édition numérique réalisée par I. Vagionakis.
                        <lb/>PROJET: Projet Chaire Gutenberg 2019 "Les Préfets du prétoire de l'Empire tardif : une élite face à la crise".
                        <lb/>ÉDITION: Strasbourg (MISHA) 2022
                        <lb/>ADRESSE WEB: <ref corresp="http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr">http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr</ref>
                    </p>
                    <p>La base de données est une publication numérique identifiée par le code ISSN suivant: ...</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
                    <head>Remerciements</head>
                    <p>Le financement du projet PPRET "Les Préfets du prétoire de l'Empire tardif : une élite face à la crise" et de sa base de données PPRET Inscriptions a été assuré par le “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Cercle Gutenberg</ref>”, qui a décerné en 2019 un prix “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaires Gutenberg</ref>” à P. Porena (P.I.).</p>
                    <p>Un grand merci au Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/michel-humm/">Michel Humm</ref> pour avoir accueilli le Projet PPRET au sein de l'Unité de recherche <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/">UMR 7044 (Archimède)</ref> (Université de Strasbourg) et à la <ref corresp="https://www.misha.fr/">MISHA of Strasbourg</ref> pour avoir accepté la base de données Inscriptions PPRET dans sa plateforme numérique en libre accès.</p>
                    <p>Remerciements particuliers au Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/olivier-huck/">Olivier Huck</ref> (UMR 7044 ARCHIMÈDE, Université de Strasbourg) pour son soutien constant et irremplaçable au Projet PPRET.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
                    <head>Licence</head>
                    <p>Tous les contenus XML, HTML et PDF de la base de données sont publiés en accès libre une licence Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License (<ref corresp="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</ref>).
                        Selon les termes de la licence, l'accès est libre pour tous les chercheurs, mais la réutilisation du matériel est soumise à la mention explicite de la source (y compris la déclaration suivante): <quote>Ce matériel est dérivé de la base de données PPRET Inscriptions, par Porena et al., hébergée à <ref corresp="http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr">ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr</ref>, ISSN ...</quote>), en fournissant un lien vers la même licence CC et en indiquant si des modifications ont été apportées.
                        Les matériaux ne peuvent pas être réutilisés à des fins commerciales.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
                    <head>Linked Open Data</head>
                    <p>Conformément aux principes des Linked Open Data, des liens vers d’autres ressources en ligne en libre accès (comme <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/ala2004/">ALA</ref>, <ref corresp="https://census.bbaw.de/">Census</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.epigraphik.uni-hamburg.de/">EDAK</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.edb.uniba.it/">EDB</ref>, <ref corresp="http://db.edcs.eu/">EDCS</ref>, <ref corresp="https://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/">EDH</ref>, <ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/">EDR</ref>, 
                        <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/insaph/iaph2007/">IAph</ref>, <ref corresp="http://telota.bbaw.de/ig/">IG Online</ref>, <ref corresp="https://iospe.kcl.ac.uk/">IOSPE<hi rend="superscript">³</hi></ref>, <ref corresp="http://inslib.kcl.ac.uk/irt2009/">IRT</ref>, <ref corresp="http://sicily.classics.ox.ac.uk/">I.Sicily</ref>, <ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/">LSA</ref>, <ref corresp="http://mizar.unive.it/mqdq/public/">MQDQ</ref>, <ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/">PHI</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/">Trismegistos</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.ubi-erat-lupa.org/">Ubi Erat Lupa</ref>) ont été insérés systématiquement.
                        L’inclusion de liens vers les ressources du PPRET Inscriptions dans d’autres ressources en ligne ouvertes est vivement encouragée.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
                    <head>The epigraphic database PPRET Inscriptions</head>
                    <p>The database “PPRET Inscriptions. The Inscriptions pertaining to the Praetorian Prefects from 284 to 395 AD” is an open access research tool developed by the team of the <ref corresp="team.html">Projet PPRET</ref> “Les préfets du prétoire de l’Empire romain tardif. Une élite face à la crise” / “The Praetorian Prefects in the Later Roman Empire: An elite in a crisis context”, created and directed by prof. Pierfrancesco Porena (Università Roma Tre - UMR 7044 “Archéologie et histoire ancienne: Méditerranée – Europe” ARCHIMÈDE, Université de Strasbourg).</p>
                    <p>The prosopographical approach to the praetorian prefects of the Late Empire, as implemented within the framework of the PPRET Project, makes it possible to characterise these dignitarries as an ‘elite’, an aristocracy by virtue of its control over the civil administration, whose culture, religious orientations and behaviours can be studied in a comprehensive manner. 
                        The social origins of the members of this leading group, as well as the modalities of access within it, can also be examined in the light of this procedure, as well as the evolution of all these parameters over time, in particular with regard to the evolutions of the administration and the political and military changes of Late Antiquity (hence the notion of ‘crisis’, introduced in the subtitle of the PPRET project).</p>
                    <p>Project PPRET is entirely funded by the “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaire Gutenberg</ref> 2019”, an international scientific prize won by prof. Pierfrancesco Porena. On a scientific and administrative level, Project PPRET is part of the cross-disciplinary programme “Aristocracies and interculturality” of the UMR 7044 ARCHIMÈDE (University of Strasbourg), directed by prof. Michel Humm.</p>
                    <p>Within the programme of the PPRET project, the publication of some of the research products is planned in traditional printed editions (monographs and the proceedings of the International Conference in Strasbourg “La préfecture du prétoire tardo-antique et ses titulaires - IV<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>-VI<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle”, held in May 2021). These works are devoted to thematic studies on the late antique praetorian prefecture as an institution and a political-administrative instrument. The prefects are examined in relation to the political and social context of the period and space in which they were active.</p>
                    <p>But a fundamental objective of the Project is to update the epigraphic sources on the late antique praetorian prefects and to re-read the known sources. The first volume of the “Prosopography of the Later Roman Empire”, covering the whole of the 4th Century AD, was published in 1971, fifty years ago. The PPRET project aims to facilitate the updating of epigraphic sources concerning the prosopography of the praetorian prefects in the period 284-395 AD. 
                        This period is affluent in figures of praetorian prefects, the office the office takes its regional form, and Latin or Greek inscriptions concerning to the praetorian prefects have increased, while some of them, already known, have been reinterpreted. The epigraphic texts are often decisive in reconstructing the chronology of the career of the senators-office holders, in perceiving the evolution of the regional prefecture along the 4th Century AD, and they provide, as monuments, a series of important evidences (political, administrative, social and cultural), which calls for a re-examination of these texts.</p>
                    <p>In order to make available up-to-date Latin and Greek inscriptions relating to the prefects of this period, the <ref corresp="team.html">project team</ref> created and implemented the PPRET Inscriptions database.</p>
                    <p>The open access database publishes all surviving Greek and Latin inscriptions relating to the praetorian prefects in charge during the period 284-395 AD. It contains 98 inscriptions in chronological order (of these, 30 do not appear in “PLRE” I; the Latin and Greek texts of several inscriptions have been critically reviewed).</p>
                    <p>Each entry contains: prosopographical and chronological coordinates (in relation to “PLRE” I), an edition of the Latin or Greek text, with a critical apparatus, information on the form of the inscription, its provenance and conservation, its author, the praetorian prefect(s) mentioned, translations into three modern languages (English, French, Italian), a substantial commentary and an up-to-date bibliography.</p>
                    <p>A simple or combined research tool, which is fairly articulated, allows the Greek and Latin inscriptions concerning the praetorian prefects of the period to be interrogated by means of search engines. It provides a wide range of information on the origin and material aspect of the inscribed monuments, on the content of the texts inscribed in Latin and Greek, on the praetorian prefects mentioned (onomastics, titulature, the relationship between the dedicator of the monument and the honoree, etc.).</p>
                    <p>The work, started in March 2020, will be followed by regular updating of the database (bibliography, discovery of new inscriptions, etc.). The database is online from February 2022. It is located on a server of the “Huma-Num” network, and is part of the digital offer of the “MISHA” Strasbourg.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
                    <head>Technical aspects of the PPRET Inscriptions database</head>
                    <div>
                        <p>The creation of the PPRET database involved two work phases: the encoding of the inscriptions in EpiDoc XML and the actual creation of the database through the EpiDoc Front-End Services (EFES).</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div>
                        <head type="subheading">Encoding of the inscriptions in EpiDoc XML</head>
                        <p><ref corresp="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/">EpiDoc</ref> is the international standard for the digital edition of ancient documents, especially inscriptions. It is a subset of the <ref corresp="https://tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiative</ref> (TEI) standard for the digital edition of literary and historical documents. 
                            It is based on XML (eXtensible Markup Language), a widely spread and highly compatible semantic markup language, which is based on the meaning of the text instead of on its appearance and which is currently the most advanced and spread approach for the creation of digital scholarly editions.</p>
                        <p>Among the many benefits of a semantic markup there are its high compatibility, interoperability and flexibility, which imply a long term sustainability and a low risk of obsolescence, and the fact that it allows the creation of enriched online publications with considerable usability benefits in terms of searching and browsing of the encoded materials.</p>
                        <p>The adaptation of the EpiDoc XML template to fit the PPRET specific needs led to the creation of a PPRET EpiDoc XML template, which was used for the encoding of all the documents included in the PPRET Inscriptions database, carried out by Irene Vagionakis, Eleonora Angius and Giordana Franceschini.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="subheading">Creation of the database with EFES (EpiDoc Front-End Services)</head>
                        <p><ref corresp="https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES/wiki">EpiDoc Front-End Services</ref> is an open-source tool for the online publication of texts encoded specifically in EpiDoc, developed in 2017 by the Institute of Classical Studies of the University of London. It is the epigraphic specialisation of <ref corresp="https://kcl-ddh.github.io/kiln/">Kiln</ref>, a similar tool for the online publication of texts in TEI, developed in 2012 by the Department of Digital Humanities of the King’s College London.</p>
                        <p>The main points of strength of EFES that led to its adoption are the fact that is was specifically designed to be used with EpiDoc ancient documents, that it is easily customisable and that it is not just a publishing tool, but also a useful tool for testing and analysis purposes during construction.</p>
                        <p>The customisation of EFES for PPRET purposes was made by Irene Vagionakis and involved, in particular, the adaptation of graphics, the creation of a dedicated XSLT template to display the PPRET XML template properly and the enhancement of EFES search facilities, including especially the addition of very specific browse filters and of a facility to perform searches limited to the inscription texts only.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
                    <head>How to cite the database PPRET Inscriptions</head>
                    <p>In paper publications, please quote the individual entry: PPRET 01.</p>
                    <p>In electronic publications, please insert a link to the entry directly (the author of each entry is indicated in the top right-hand corner).</p>
                    <p>If you want to quote the whole database PPRET Inscriptions:
                        <lb/>AUTHORS: P. Porena (dir.), E. Angius, A. Bernier, G. Franceschini, P. Porena, I. Vagionakis, 
                        <lb/>TITLE: PPRET Inscriptions. The Inscriptions pertaining to the praetorian prefects from 284 to 395 AD. Edition and study directed by P. Porena, realised by the authors, with digital edition performed by I. Vagionakis 
                        <lb/>PROJECT: Projet Chaire Gutenberg 2019 "Les Préfets du prétoire de l'Empire tardif: une élite face à la crise"
                        <lb/>EDITION: Strasbourg (MISHA) 2022
                        <lb/>WEB ADDRESS: <ref corresp="http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr">http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr</ref>
                    </p>
                    <p>The database is a digital publication identified by the following ISSN code:  ...</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
                    <head>Credits</head>
                    <p>The funding of the Project PPRET “Les Préfets du prétoire de l'Empire tardif: une élite face à la crise” and its database PPRET Inscriptions came from the “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Cercle Gutenberg</ref>”, which in 2019 funded Prof. <ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/titulaires-et-laureats/titulaires-chaires-gutenberg/biographie-des-laureats/chaires-2019/pierfrancesco-porena/">P. Porena</ref> with a “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaires Gutenberg</ref>” award.</p>
                    <p>Many thanks to Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/michel-humm/">Michel Humm</ref> for having welcomed the Project PPRET into the <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/">UMR 7044 (Archimède)</ref> Research Unit (University of Strasbourg) and to <ref corresp="https://www.misha.fr/">MISHA of Strasbourg</ref> for having accepted the PPRET Inscriptions database into its open access digital platform.</p>
                    <p>Remerciements particuliers au Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/olivier-huck/">Olivier Huck</ref> (UMR 7044 ARCHIMÈDE, Université de Strasbourg) pour son soutien constant et irremplaçable au Projet PPRET.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
                    <head>License</head>
                    <p>All the XML, HTML and PDF contents of the database<!--, which is hosted on a server provided by the <ref corresp="https://www.huma-num.fr/">Huma-Num</ref> Digital Humanities research infrastructure thanks to an agreement with <ref corresp="https://www.misha.fr/">MISHA</ref> / <ref corresp="https://www.unistra.fr/">Université de Strasbourg</ref>,--> are released in open access mode under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License (<ref corresp="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</ref>).
                        According to the license terms, access is free to all scholars, but the reuse of the materials is subject to explicitly giving appropriate credit (including the following statement: <quote>This material is derived from the PPRET Inscriptions database, by Porena et al., hosted at <ref corresp="http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr">ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr</ref>, ISSN ...</quote>), providing a link to the same CC license and indicating if changes were made. 
                        The materials cannot be reused for commercial purposes.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
                    <head>Linked Open Data</head>
                    <p>According to the Linked Open Data principles, links to other open access online resources (like <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/ala2004/">ALA</ref>, <ref corresp="https://census.bbaw.de/">Census</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.epigraphik.uni-hamburg.de/">EDAK</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.edb.uniba.it/">EDB</ref>, <ref corresp="http://db.edcs.eu/">EDCS</ref>, <ref corresp="https://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/">EDH</ref>, <ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/">EDR</ref>, 
                        <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/insaph/iaph2007/">IAph</ref>, <ref corresp="http://telota.bbaw.de/ig/">IG Online</ref>, <ref corresp="https://iospe.kcl.ac.uk/">IOSPE<hi rend="superscript">³</hi></ref>, <ref corresp="http://inslib.kcl.ac.uk/irt2009/">IRT</ref>, <ref corresp="http://sicily.classics.ox.ac.uk/">I.Sicily</ref>, <ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/">LSA</ref>, <ref corresp="http://mizar.unive.it/mqdq/public/">MQDQ</ref>, <ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/">PHI</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/">Trismegistos</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.ubi-erat-lupa.org/">Ubi Erat Lupa</ref>) have been inserted systematically.
                        The inclusion of links to PPRET Inscriptions resources in other open online resources is warmly encouraged.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
