<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>
                    <seg xml:lang="en">Introduction</seg>
                    <seg xml:lang="fr">Avant-propos</seg>
                    <seg xml:lang="it">Introduzione</seg>
                </title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>PPRET</authority>
                <idno type="filename">Introduction</idno>
                <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attributions-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc><p>Born digital document.</p></sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="commentary" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>The epigraphic database <title>PPRET Inscriptions</title></head>
                    <p>The database “PPRET Inscriptions. Inscriptions pertaining to the Praetorian Prefects from 284 to 395 AD” is an open access research tool developed within the <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/activites-de-recherche/programmes-de-recherche/chaire-gutenberg-projet-ppret/">Projet PPRET</ref> “Les préfets du prétoire de l’Empire romain tardif. Une élite face à la crise” / “The Praetorian Prefects in the Later Roman Empire: An elite in a crisis context”. This project is part of the cross-disciplinary programme “<ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/fr/activites-de-recherche/programmes-de-recherche/programmes-transversaux/aristocraties-et-interculturalite/">Aristocracies and Interculturality</ref>” of the UMR 7044 ARCHIMÈDE (University of Strasbourg). The project is fully funded by the endowment associated with the “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaire Gutenberg</ref> 2019”, an international scientific prize won by Prof. Porena (Università Roma Tre / associate member UMR 7044 ARCHIMÈDE - P.I. of Project PPRET).</p>
                    <p>The prosopographical approach to the praetorian prefects of the later Roman Empire, as implemented within the framework of the PPRET Project, makes it possible to characterise these dignitaries as an ‘elite’, an aristocracy by virtue of its control over the civil administration, whose culture, religious orientations and behaviour can be studied in a comprehensive manner. The social origins of the members of this leading group and how outsiders could gain access to it, can also be examined in the light of this procedure. Such a procedure also allows us to study the development of this social group over time, in particular with regard to the evolution of the administration and the political and military changes of Late Antiquity (hence the notion of ‘crisis’, introduced in the subtitle of the PPRET project).</p>
                    <p>Within the programme of the PPRET project, the results of the research are planned to be published via traditional printed editions (monographs and the proceedings of the International Conference in Strasbourg “La préfecture du prétoire tardo-antique et ses titulaires - IV<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>-VI<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle”, held in May 2021). These works are devoted to thematic studies on the late antique praetorian prefecture, perceived not only as an institution, but also as a political-administrative instrument. The prefects are examined in relation to the political and social context of the period and space in which they were active.</p>
                    <p>Another fundamental objective of the project is to update the epigraphic sources pertaining to the late antique praetorian prefects and to re-read the known sources. In effect the first volume of the “Prosopography of the Later Roman Empire”, covering the whole of the 4th Century AD, was published in 1971, fifty years ago. More specifically, the PPRET project aims to facilitate the updating of epigraphic sources concerning the prosopography of the praetorian prefects in the period 284-395 AD. This period produces a great many praetorian prefects. It is also the period in which the office takes its regional form, while Latin or Greek inscriptions concerning the praetorian prefects increases, some of which have now been reinterpreted. The epigraphic texts are often decisive in reconstructing the chronology of the career of the senators-office holders. Moreover, they also help us to trace the evolution of the regional prefecture during the 4th Century AD, while also providing much needed physical evidence (political, administrative, social and cultural), all of which is now in need of urgent re-examination.</p>
                    <p>In order to make available up-to-date Latin and Greek inscriptions relating to the prefects of this period, the <ref corresp="team.html">project team</ref> created and implemented the PPRET Inscriptions database.</p>
                    <p>The open access database publishes all surviving Greek and Latin inscriptions relating to the serving praetorian prefects during the period 284-395 AD. It contains 98 inscriptions in chronological order (of these, 30 do not appear in “PLRE” I; the Latin and Greek texts of several inscriptions have been critically reviewed).</p>
                    <p>Each entry contains: prosopographical and chronological coordinates (in relation to “PLRE” I), an edition of the Latin or Greek text, with a critical apparatus, information on the form of the inscription, its provenance and conservation, its author, the praetorian prefect(s) mentioned, translations into three modern languages (English, French, Italian), a substantial commentary and an up-to-date bibliography.</p>
                    <p>Thanks to a relatively simple and well articulated research tool, the Greek and Latin inscriptions concerning the praetorian prefects of the period can be looked up and studied through search filters. It provides a wide range of information on the origin and material aspect of the inscribed monuments, on the content of the texts inscribed in Latin and Greek and on the praetorian prefects themselves (onomastics, titulature, the relationship between the dedicator of the monument and the honoree, etc.).</p>
                    <p>The work, started in March 2020 is ongoing and the database will continue to be updated (bibliography, new epigraphic finds etc.). Online as of <emph>April 2022</emph>, the database will be located on a server of the “Huma-Num” network and part of the digital platform of “MISHA” in Strasbourg.</p>
                </div>
                    
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Technical aspects of the PPRET Inscriptions database</head>
                    <div>
                        <p>The creation of the PPRET database was executed in two phases: the encoding of the inscriptions in EpiDoc XML and the actual creation of the database through the EpiDoc Front-End Services (EFES).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="subheading">Encoding of the inscriptions in EpiDoc XML</head>
                        <p><ref corresp="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/">EpiDoc</ref> is the international standard for the digital edition of ancient documents, especially inscriptions. It is a subset of the <ref corresp="https://tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiative</ref> (TEI) standard for the digital edition of literary and historical documents. 
                            It is based on XML (eXtensible Markup Language), a widely spread and highly compatible semantic markup language, which is based on the meaning of the text instead of on its appearance and which is currently the most advanced and widely used approach for the creation of digital scholarly editions.</p>
                        <p>The many benefits of a semantic markup include its high compatibility, interoperability and flexibility, which imply a long term sustainability and a low risk of obsolescence. In addition, such a semantic markup also allows for the creation of enriched online publications with considerable usability benefits in terms of searching and browsing of the encoded materials.</p>
                        <p>The adaptation of the EpiDoc XML template to fit the specific needs of PPRET, led to the creation of a PPRET EpiDoc XML template, which was used for the encoding of all the documents included in the PPRET Inscriptions database. The work was carried out by Irene Vagionakis, Eleonora Angius and Giordana Franceschini.</p>
                    </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="subheading">Creation of the database with EFES (EpiDoc Front-End Services)</head>
                    <p><ref corresp="https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES/wiki">EpiDoc Front-End Services</ref> is an open-source tool for the online publication of texts encoded specifically in EpiDoc, which was developed in 2017 by the Institute of Classical Studies of the University of London. It is the epigraphic specialisation of <ref corresp="https://kcl-ddh.github.io/kiln/">Kiln</ref>, a similar tool for the online publication of texts in TEI, developed in 2012 by the Department of Digital Humanities of the King’s College London.</p>
                    <p>EFES was adopted because of its many strengths. Not only was it specifically designed to be used with EpiDoc ancient documents, it is also easily customisable and as a tool, it can be used for both publishing and testing during construction.</p>
                    <p>The customisation of EFES for PPRET purposes was made by Irene Vagionakis and involved, in particular, the adaptation of graphics, the creation of a dedicated XSLT template to display the PPRET XML template properly and the enhancement of EFES search facilities, including the addition of very specific browse filters and of a facility to perform searches limited to the inscription texts only.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>How to cite the database PPRET Inscriptions</head>
                    <p>In paper publications, please quote the individual entry: e.g. « PPRET 01 ».</p>
                    <p>In electronic publications, please insert a link to the entry directly.</p>
                    <p>The author of each entry is indicated in the top right-hand corner.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>If you want to quote the whole database PPRET Inscriptions:</head>
                    <p>AUTHORS: P. Porena (dir.), E. Angius, A. Bernier, G. Franceschini, P. Porena, I. Vagionakis,</p>
                    <p>TITLE: PPRET Inscriptions. Inscriptions pertaining to the praetorian prefects from 284 to 395 AD. Edition and study directed by P. Porena, produced by the authors, with digital edition performed by I. Vagionakis</p>
                    <p>PROJECT: Projet Chaire Gutenberg 2019 <title>Les Préfets du prétoire de l'Empire tardif: une élite face à la crise</title></p>
                    <p>EDITION: Strasbourg (MISHA) 2022</p>
                    <p>WEB ADDRESS: <ref corresp="http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr">http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr</ref></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Credits</head>
                    <p>The funding of the Project PPRET “Les Préfets du prétoire de l'Empire tardif: une élite face à la crise” and its database PPRET Inscriptions came from the “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Cercle Gutenberg</ref>”, which in 2019 funded Prof. <ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/titulaires-et-laureats/titulaires-chaires-gutenberg/biographie-des-laureats/chaires-2019/pierfrancesco-porena/">P. Porena</ref> with a “<ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaires Gutenberg</ref>” award.</p>
                    <p>Many thanks to Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/michel-humm/">Michel Humm</ref> for having welcomed the Project PPRET into the <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/">UMR 7044 (Archimède)</ref> Research Unit (University of Strasbourg) and to <ref corresp="https://www.misha.fr/">MISHA of Strasbourg</ref> for having accepted the PPRET Inscriptions database into its open access digital platform.</p>
                    <p>Special thanks go to Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/olivier-huck/">Olivier Huck</ref> for his constant and irreplaceable support of the PPRET Project.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>License</head>
                        <p>All the XML, HTML and PDF contents of the database are released in open access mode under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License (<ref corresp="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</ref>).
                            Access is free to all scholars, but the product is legally protected against any improper use by the specific European Directives on databases and their transposition into national law. 
                            The reuse of the materials is subject to explicit mention of the author(s) and the work.</p>
                    <p>The database is a digital publication identified by the following ISSN code: 2823-4197</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Linked Open Data</head>
                    <p>According to the Linked Open Data principles, links to other open access online resources (like <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/ala2004/">ALA</ref>, <ref corresp="https://census.bbaw.de/">Census</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.epigraphik.uni-hamburg.de/">EDAK</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.edb.uniba.it/">EDB</ref>, <ref corresp="http://db.edcs.eu/">EDCS</ref>, <ref corresp="https://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/">EDH</ref>, <ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/">EDR</ref>, 
                        <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/insaph/iaph2007/">IAph</ref>, <ref corresp="http://telota.bbaw.de/ig/">IG Online</ref>, <ref corresp="https://iospe.kcl.ac.uk/">IOSPE<hi rend="superscript">³</hi></ref>, <ref corresp="http://inslib.kcl.ac.uk/irt2009/">IRT</ref>, <ref corresp="http://sicily.classics.ox.ac.uk/">I.Sicily</ref>, <ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/">LSA</ref>, <ref corresp="http://mizar.unive.it/mqdq/public/">MQDQ</ref>, <ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/">PHI</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/">Trismegistos</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.ubi-erat-lupa.org/">Ubi Erat Lupa</ref>) have been inserted.
                        The inclusion of links to PPRET Inscriptions resources in other open online resources is warmly encouraged.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" xml:lang="fr">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>La base de données épigraphiques <title>PPRET Inscriptions</title></head>
                    <p>La base de données <title>PPRET Inscriptions. Inscriptions pertaining to the Praetorian Prefects from 284 to 395 AD</title> est un outil de recherche en libre accès, développé dans le cadre du <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/activites-de-recherche/programmes-de-recherche/chaire-gutenberg-projet-ppret/">projet PPRET <title>Les préfets du prétoire de l’Empire romain tardif. Une élite face à la crise</title></ref>.</p>
                    <p>Le <title>Projet PPRET</title> s’inscrit dans le cadre du <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/fr/activites-de-recherche/programmes-de-recherche/programmes-transversaux/aristocraties-et-interculturalite/">programme transversal <title>Aristocraties et interculturalité</title></ref> de l’UMR 7044 ARCHIMEDE. Il est intégralement financé par la dotation associée à la <ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaire Gutenberg</ref> 2019, prix scientifique international remporté par le Prof. Porena (Università Roma Tre / membre associé UMR 7044 ARCHIMEDE - P.I. du Projet PPRET).</p>
                    
                    <p>Le projet PPRET repose sur une approche prosopographique des préfets du prétoire de l’empire tardif. Ceux-ci sont envisagés comme une « élite », une « aristocratie de fonction » dont la culture, les orientations religieuses, et les pratiques caractéristiques peuvent être appréhendées par le moyen de mises en séries. Les origines sociales des membres de ce groupe dirigeant, ainsi que les modalités d’accès en son sein peuvent, elles aussi, être examinées, de même que l’évolution de l’ensemble de ces paramètres au fil du temps, en particulier au regard des évolutions de l’administration et des bouleversements politiques et militaires de l’Antiquité tardive (d’où la notion de « crise », introduite dans le sous-titre du projet PPRET).</p>
                    <p>Une partie des résultats du projet PPRET est diffusée sous la forme d’éditions imprimées traditionnelles (monographies et actes du colloque international <title>La préfecture du prétoire tardo-antique et ses titulaires IV<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>-VI<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> s.</title>, Strasbourg, 26-28 mai 2021). Celles-ci rendent compte d’études thématiques envisageant la préfecture du prétoire tardo-antique comme une institution et un instrument politico-administratif de l’Empire romain tardif. Les préfets y sont également examinés en relation avec le contexte politique et social de leur temps.</p>
                    <p>Cependant, au-delà de ces approches « ponctuelles », l’aspect le plus essentiel du projet PPRET consiste en la mise à jour des sources épigraphiques relatives aux préfets du prétoire de l’Empire tardif. En effet : le premier volume de la <title>Prosopography of the Later Roman Empire</title> (couvrant le IV<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle), est paru en 1971, il y a donc plus de cinquante ans désormais. Depuis lors, des découvertes sont intervenues, et de nouvelles lectures de sources connues ont été proposées, en particulier dans le domaine de l’épigraphie. Les textes épigraphiques sont souvent décisifs pour reconstituer la chronologie de la carrière des sénateurs titulaires, l’évolution de la préfecture du prétoire régionale au IVe siècle de notre ère, et fournissent, en tant que monuments, une série d’informations essentielles de nature politique, administrative, sociale et culturelle : autant d’aspects qui rendaient indispensable un réexamen précis de cette documentation. Afin de répondre à ce besoin d’actualisation, <ref corresp="team.html">une équipe rassemblée sous la direction du Prof. Porena</ref> a créé et mis en œuvre la base de données <title>PPRET Inscriptions</title>.</p>
                    <p>Celle-ci reprend l’ensemble de l’épigraphie latine et grecque relative aux préfets du prétoire de la période 284-395 ap. J.-C. Elle rassemble par ordre chronologique 98 inscriptions. Parmi celles-ci, 30 n’apparaissent pas dans la PLRE I. Par ailleurs, les textes latins et grecs de plusieurs inscriptions ont fait l’objet d’une relecture critique. 
                        Chaque fiche (relative à une inscription) contient : des coordonnées prosopographiques et chronologiques (incluant, le cas échéant, des renvois à la PLRE I) ; une édition du texte latin ou grec de l’inscription (pourvue d’un apparat critique) ; des informations relatives à la forme de l’inscription, à sa provenance, à sa conservation, à son auteur, et au(x) préfet(s) du prétoire mentionné(s) ; des traductions (en anglais, français, italien) ; un commentaire substantiel ; une bibliographie à jour. Soit un nombre considérable d’informations susceptibles, par ailleurs, d’être mobilisées dans le cadre de recherches simples ou combinées.</p>
                    <p>En ligne depuis le mois de <emph>avril 2022</emph>, la base de données PPRET Inscriptions fait l’objet d’un suivi et de mises à jour régulières (veille bibliographique, notamment). Elle est située sur un serveur de la plateforme <title>Huma-Num</title>, et fait partie de l’offre numérique de la MISHA (Strasbourg).</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Aspects techniques de la base de données épigraphiques PPRET Inscriptions</head>
                    <div>
                        <p>La création de la base de données PPRET a comporté deux phases de travail: l'encodage des inscriptions en EpiDoc XML et la création proprement dite de la base de données avec EpiDoc Front-End Services (EFES).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="subheading">Encodage des inscriptions en EpiDoc XML</head>
                        <p><ref corresp="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/">EpiDoc</ref> est le standard international pour l’édition numérique de documents anciens, en particulier les inscriptions. Il s’agit d’un sous-ensemble de le standard <ref corresp="https://tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiative</ref> (TEI) pour l’édition numérique de documents littéraires et historiques. 
                            Elle est basée sur le langage XML (eXtensible Markup Language), un langage de balisage sémantique largement répandu et hautement compatible, qui se fonde sur la signification du texte plutôt que sur son apparence et qui constitue actuellement l’approche la plus avancée et la plus répandue pour la création d’éditions savantes numériques.</p>
                        <p>Parmi les nombreux avantages d'un balisage sémantique, citons sa grande compatibilité, son interopérabilité et sa flexibilité, qui impliquent une durabilité à long terme et un faible risque d’obsolescence, ainsi que le fait qu’il permet la création de publications en ligne enrichies, avec des avantages considérables en termes de facilité d’utilisation pour la recherche et la navigation dans les matériaux encodés.</p>
                        <p>L’adaptation du modèle EpiDoc XML aux besoins spécifiques de la PPRET a conduit à la création d’un modèle PPRET XML EpiDoc, qui a été utilisé pour l’encodage de tous les documents inclus dans la base de données PPRET Inscriptions, réalisé par Irene Vagionakis, Eleonora Angius et Giordana Franceschini.</p> 
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="subheading">Création de la base de données avec EFES (EpiDoc Front-End Services)</head>
                        <p><ref corresp="https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES/wiki">EpiDoc Front-End Services</ref> est un outil open-source pour la publication en ligne de textes encodés spécifiquement en EpiDoc, développé en 2017 par l’Institute of Classical Studies - University of London. 
                            Il s’agit de la spécialisation épigraphique de <ref corresp="https://kcl-ddh.github.io/kiln/">Kiln</ref>, un outil similaire pour la publication en ligne de textes en TEI, développé en 2012 par le Department of Digital Humanities du King’s College London.</p>
                        <p>Les principaux points forts d’EFES qui ont conduit à son adoption sont le fait qu’il a été spécifiquement conçu pour être utilisé avec les documents anciens EpiDoc, qu’il est facilement personnalisable et qu’il ne s’agit pas seulement d’un outil de publication, mais aussi d’un outil utile à des fins de test et d’analyse pendant la construction.</p>
                        <p>La personnalisation d’EFES pour PPRET a été réalisée par Irene Vagionakis et a impliqué, en particulier, l’adaptation des graphiques, la création d’un modèle XSLT dédié pour afficher correctement le modèle XML PPRET et le développement des fonctions de recherche d’EFES, notamment l’ajout de filtres de navigation très spécifiques et d’une fonction permettant d’effectuer des recherches limitées aux seuls textes d’inscription.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Comment citer la base de données PPRET Inscriptions?</head>
                    <p>Publication papier, veuillez citer la ou les fiche(s) utilisées : p. ex. « PPRET 01 ».</p>
                    <p>Publication électronique, veuillez ouvrir un lien directement vers l’adresse de la fiche (des fiches) concernée(s).</p>
                    <p>L’auteur de chaque fiche est indiqué dans le coin supérieur droit.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Si vous souhaitez citer l'ensemble de la base de données Inscriptions PPRET:</head>
                    <p>AUTEURS: P. Porena (dir.), E. Angius, A. Bernier, G. Franceschini, P. Porena, I. Vagionakis,</p>
                    <p>TITRE: PPRET Inscriptions. Inscriptions pertaining to the praetorian prefects from 284 to 395 AD.</p>
                    <p>PROJET: Chaire Gutenberg 2019 <title>Les Préfets du prétoire de l'Empire tardif: une élite face à la crise</title></p>
                    <p>ÉDITION: Strasbourg (MISHA) 2022</p>
                    <p>ADRESSE WEB: <ref corresp="http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr">http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr</ref>
                    </p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Remerciements</head>
                    <p>Le projet <title>PPRET Les Préfets du prétoire de l’Empire tardif. Une élite face à la crise</title> et la base de données <title>PPRET Inscriptions</title> ont été financés par le <ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Cercle Gutenberg</ref>, via la dotation associée à la <ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaires Gutenberg</ref> 2019 de Pierfrancesco Porena.</p>
                    <p>Merci au Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/michel-humm/">Michel Humm</ref> d’avoir bien voulu accueillir le <title>Projet PPRET</title> au sein de l’<ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/">UMR 7044 ARCHIMÈDE</ref>.</p>
                    <p>Merci à la <ref corresp="https://www.misha.fr/">MISHA</ref> d’avoir accepté d’héberger la base de données <title>PPRET Inscriptions</title>.</p>
                    <p>Des remerciements particuliers vont au Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/olivier-huck/">Olivier Huck</ref> pour son soutien constant et irremplaçable au <title>Projet PPRET</title>.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Licence</head>
                    <p>Tous les contenus XML, HTML et PDF de la base de données sont publiés en accès libre une licence Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License (<ref corresp="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</ref>).
                        L’accès est libre pour tous les chercheurs, mais le produit est légalement protégé contre toute utilisation abusive par les directives européennes spécifiques sur les bases de données et leur transposition en droit national.
                        La réutilisation du matériel est soumise à la mention explicite de l’auteur(s) et de l’œuvre.</p>
                    <p>La base de données est une publication numérique identifiée par le code ISSN suivant: 2823-4197</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Linked Open Data</head>
                    <p>Conformément aux principes des Linked Open Data, des liens vers d’autres ressources en ligne en libre accès (comme <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/ala2004/">ALA</ref>, <ref corresp="https://census.bbaw.de/">Census</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.epigraphik.uni-hamburg.de/">EDAK</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.edb.uniba.it/">EDB</ref>, <ref corresp="http://db.edcs.eu/">EDCS</ref>, <ref corresp="https://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/">EDH</ref>, <ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/">EDR</ref>, 
                        <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/insaph/iaph2007/">IAph</ref>, <ref corresp="http://telota.bbaw.de/ig/">IG Online</ref>, <ref corresp="https://iospe.kcl.ac.uk/">IOSPE<hi rend="superscript">³</hi></ref>, <ref corresp="http://inslib.kcl.ac.uk/irt2009/">IRT</ref>, <ref corresp="http://sicily.classics.ox.ac.uk/">I.Sicily</ref>, <ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/">LSA</ref>, <ref corresp="http://mizar.unive.it/mqdq/public/">MQDQ</ref>, <ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/">PHI</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/">Trismegistos</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.ubi-erat-lupa.org/">Ubi Erat Lupa</ref>) ont été insérés.
                        L’inclusion de liens vers les ressources du PPRET Inscriptions dans d’autres ressources en ligne ouvertes est vivement encouragée.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary" xml:lang="it">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Il database epigrafico <title>PPRET Inscriptions</title></head>
                    <p>Il database “PPRET Inscriptions. Inscriptions pertaining to the Praetorian Prefects from 284 to 395 AD” è uno strumento di ricerca open access sviluppato nell'ambito del <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/activites-de-recherche/programmes-de-recherche/chaire-gutenberg-projet-ppret/">Projet PPRET</ref> “Les préfets du prétoire de l’Empire romain tardif. Une élite face à la crise” / “The Praetorian Prefects in the Later Roman Empire: An elite in a crisis context”. 
                        Il progetto PPRET fa parte del <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/fr/activites-de-recherche/programmes-de-recherche/programmes-transversaux/aristocraties-et-interculturalite/">programme transversal <title>Aristocraties et interculturalité</title></ref> dell'UMR 7044 ARCHIMEDE (Univ. de Strasbourg). Il progetto è interamente finanziato dalla dotazione associata alla <ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaire Gutenberg</ref> 2019, premio scientifico internazionale su bando competitivo vinto dal Prof. <ref corresp="http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr/en/texts/team.html">P. Porena</ref> (Università Roma Tre / membre associé de l’UMR 7044 ARCHIMEDE - P.I. del Projet PPRET).</p>
                    <p>Il progetto PPRET si basa su uno studio prosopografico dei prefetti del pretorio del Tardo Impero. Essi sono un’ ‘aristocrazia di servizio’ la cui cultura, gli orientamenti religiosi e i comportamenti politici e sociali possono essere esaminati in prospettiva diacronica. 
                        È di particolare interesse lo studio delle origini sociali degli individui che raggiungono la prefettura del pretorio, così come le modalità di accesso ai vertici amministrativi del tardo impero, e l’evoluzione di questi parametri nel tempo, sullo sfondo dei processi di adattamento dell’amministrazione ai cambiamenti politici e militari della tarda antichità (da qui la nozione di ‘crisi’, introdotta nel sottotitolo del progetto PPRET).</p>
                    <p>Alcuni dei risultati scientifici del progetto PPRET sono diffusi sotto forma di edizioni tradizionali a stampa (monografie e atti del Convegno internazionale “La préfecture du prétoire tardo-antique et ses titulaires IV<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>-VI<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle”, Strasburgo, 26-28 maggio 2021). 
                        Si tratta di studi tematici e d’insieme che considerano la prefettura del pretorio tardoantica come un’istituzione e uno strumento politico-amministrativo del tardo impero romano. I prefetti sono esaminati in relazione al contesto politico, sociale e culturale del loro tempo nell’ambito delle diverse circoscrizioni prefettizie.</p>
                    <p>Tuttavia, al di là di queste analisi tematiche e regionali, un aspetto importante del progetto PPRET è l’aggiornamento delle fonti epigrafiche relative ai prefetti del pretorio del Tardo Impero, limitatamente al periodo 284-395. Il primo volume della “Prosopography of the Later Roman Empire”, che abbraccia il IV secolo, è stato pubblicato nel 1971, più di cinquant’anni fa. Da allora, sono intervenute nuove scoperte epigrafiche e sono state proposte nuove letture di fonti conosciute. 
                        I testi epigrafici sono spesso decisivi per ricostruire la cronologia delle carriere dei senatori titolari, per cogliere l’evoluzione della prefettura regionale delle prefetture del pretorio nel IV secolo, ed essi forniscono, in quanto monumenti, una serie di informazioni essenziali di natura politica, amministrativa, sociale e culturale: tanti aspetti che hanno reso indispensabile un preciso riesame di questa documentazione. Per soddisfare questa necessità di aggiornamento, un <ref corresp="team.html">team</ref> di giovani studiosi sotto la direzione di P. Porena ha creato e implementato il database PPRET Inscriptions.</p>
                    <p>Il database contiene tutte le iscrizioni latine e greche relative ai prefetti del pretorio del periodo 284-395 d.C. Esso presenta in ordine cronologico 98 iscrizioni. Di queste, 30 non sono comprese nel primo volume della “PLRE”. Inoltre, i testi latini e greci di diverse iscrizioni sono stati riletti criticamente. 
                        Ogni scheda del database contiene: dati prosopografici e cronologici (compresi, se del caso, i riferimenti alla “PLRE” I); un’edizione del testo latino o greco dell’iscrizione (con un apparato critico); informazioni sull’iscrizione e sul supporto, la sua provenienza, la sua conservazione, il suo autore, e il prefetto o i prefetti del pretorio menzionati; traduzioni in lingue moderne (in inglese, francese, italiano); un commento sostanziale; e una bibliografia aggiornata. Infine una notevole quantità di informazioni possono essere ottenute attraverso l’interrogazione di diversi motori di ricerca dotati di filtri combinati.</p>
                    <p>Il database è online dal <emph>aprile 2022</emph>, è monitorato e aggiornato. Esso è posizionato trova su un server del network francese dedicato alle scienze umane “Huma-Num”, e fa parte dell’offerta digitale della “MISHA” di Strasburgo.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Aspetti tecnici del database PPRET Inscriptions</head>
                    <div>
                        <p>La creazione del database PPRET ha implicato due fasi di lavoro: la codifica delle iscrizioni in EpiDoc XML e la vera e propria realizzazione del database tramite EpiDoc Front-End Services (EFES).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="subheading">Codifica delle iscrizioni in EpiDoc XML</head>
                        <p><ref corresp="https://epidoc.stoa.org/gl/latest/">EpiDoc</ref> è lo standard internazionale per l’edizione digitale di documenti antichi, in particolar modo iscrizioni. È un sottoinsieme di TEI (<ref corresp="https://tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiative</ref>), lo standard per l’edizione digitale di testi letterari e fonti storiche. 
                            È basato sul linguaggio XML (eXtensible Markup Language), un linguaggio di marcatura semantica ampiamente diffuso e altamente compatibile, incentrato sul significato del testo anziché sul suo aspetto, che costituisce l’approccio al momento più avanzato e diffuso per la creazione di edizioni critiche digitali.</p>
                        <p>Tra i numerosi benefici che una marcatura semantica comporta vi sono la sua alta compatibilità, interoperabilità e flessibilità, che implicano una sostenibilità a lungo termine e un basso rischio di obsolescenza, e il fatto che consenta la creazione di edizioni online arricchite comportanti notevoli vantaggi in termini di usabilità in relazione alle possibilità di ricerca e navigazione dei materiali codificati.</p>
                        <p>L’adattamento del template EpiDoc XML alle esigenze specifiche del progetto PPRET ha portato alla creazione di un template EpiDoc XML PPRET, che è stato impiegato nella codifica di tutti i documenti inclusi nel database PPRET Inscriptions, realizzata da Irene Vagionakis, Eleonora Angius e Giordana Franceschini.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="subheading">Creazione del database tramite EFES (EpiDoc Front-End Services)</head>
                        <p><ref corresp="https://github.com/EpiDoc/EFES/wiki">EpiDoc Front-End Services</ref> è uno strumento open-source per la pubblicazione online di testi codificati specificamente in EpiDoc, sviluppato nel 2017 dall’Institute of Classical Studies della University of London. È la specializzazione epigrafica di <ref corresp="https://kcl-ddh.github.io/kiln/">Kiln</ref>, uno strumento affine per la pubblicazione online di testi in TEI, sviluppato nel 2012 dal Department of Digital Humanities del King’s College London.</p>
                        <p>I principali punti di forza di EFES che hanno condotto alla sua adozione sono l’essere stato ideato specificamente per essere usato con documenti antichi in EpiDoc, la sua facilità di personalizzazione e il suo essere uno strumento utile non soltanto ai fini della pubblicazione online ma anche nel contesto di verifiche e analisi in corso d’opera.</p>
                        <p>L’adattamento di EFES alle esigenze di PPRET è stato curato da Irene Vagionakis ed ha implicato, in particolare, l’adattamento della grafica, la creazione di uno specifico template XSLT finalizzato alla generazione di una visualizzazione ottimale del template XML PPRET e il miglioramento delle funzionalità di ricerca di EFES, fra cui nello specifico l’aggiunta di filtri di ricerca mirati e di una funzionalità di ricerca circoscritta ai soli testi delle iscrizioni.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Come citare il database PPRET Inscriptions</head>
                    <p>Pubblicazioni cartacee, si prega di citare la scheda con sigla e numero: per es. « PPRET 01 ».</p>
                    <p>Pubblicazioni digitali, si prega di impostare un link direttamente verso l’URL della scheda.</p>
                    <p>L’autore di ogni scheda è indicato nell’angolo superiore destro.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Citare il database PPRET Inscriptions nel suo insieme:</head>
                    <p>AUTORI: P. Porena (dir.), E. Angius, A. Bernier, G. Franceschini, P. Porena, I. Vagionakis,</p>
                    <p>TITOLO: PPRET Inscriptions. Inscriptions pertaining to the Praetorian Prefects from 284 to 395 AD.</p>
                    <p>PROGETTO: Chaire Gutenberg 2019 <title>Les Préfets du prétoire de l'Empire tardif: une élite face à la crise</title></p>
                    <p>EDIZIONE: Strasbourg (MISHA) 2022</p>
                    <p>INDIRIZZO WEB: <ref corresp="http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr">http://ppret-inscriptions.huma-num.fr</ref></p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Ringraziamenti</head>
                    <p>Il Progetto PPRET “Les préfets du prétoire de l’Empire romain tardif. Une élite face à la crise” e il database “PPRET Inscriptions. Inscriptions pertaining to the Praetorian Prefects from 284 to 395 AD” sono stati finanziati dal <ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Cercle Gutenberg</ref>, attraverso la dotazione assegnata alla <ref corresp="http://www.cercle-gutenberg.fr/chaires-gutenberg/presentation/">Chaire Gutenberg</ref> 2019 vinta da Pierfrancesco Porena.</p>
                    <p>Un ringraziamento al Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/michel-humm/">Michel Humm</ref> per aver voluto accogliere il Progetto PPRET nei programmi di ricerca dell’<ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/">UMR 7044 ARCHIMÈDE</ref>.</p>
                    <p>Un ringraziamento alla <ref corresp="https://www.misha.fr/">MISHA</ref> per aver accettato di ospitare il database “PPRET Inscriptions” nel suo portale informatico.</p>
                    <p>Un ringraziamento particolare va al Prof. <ref corresp="https://archimede.unistra.fr/laboratoire/membres/membres-titulaires/olivier-huck/">Olivier Huck</ref> per il suo costante e insostituibile sostegno al Progetto PPRET.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Licenza</head>
                    <p>Tutti i contenuti XML, HTML e PDF del database sono rilasciati in modalità open access mode sotto una licenza Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License (<ref corresp="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</ref>).
                        L’accesso è libero e gratuito ad ogni studioso, ma il prodotto è giuridicamente tutelato contro ogni uso indebito dalle specifiche Direttive europee in tema di Banche Dati e dal loro recepimento nelle varie legislazioni nazionali.
                        Il riuso dei materiali è vincolato alla menzione esplicita degli autori e dell’opera.</p>
                    <p>Il database è una pubblicazione digitale identificata dal seguente codice ISSN: 2823-4197</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section">
                    <head>Linked Open Data</head>
                    <p>Secondo i principi dei Linked Open Data, sono stati inseriti links ad altre risorse online a libero accesso (come <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/ala2004/">ALA</ref>, <ref corresp="https://census.bbaw.de/">Census</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.epigraphik.uni-hamburg.de/">EDAK</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.edb.uniba.it/">EDB</ref>, <ref corresp="http://db.edcs.eu/">EDCS</ref>, <ref corresp="https://edh-www.adw.uni-heidelberg.de/">EDH</ref>, <ref corresp="http://www.edr-edr.it/">EDR</ref>, 
                        <ref corresp="https://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/insaph/iaph2007/">IAph</ref>, <ref corresp="http://telota.bbaw.de/ig/">IG Online</ref>, <ref corresp="https://iospe.kcl.ac.uk/">IOSPE<hi rend="superscript">³</hi></ref>, <ref corresp="http://inslib.kcl.ac.uk/irt2009/">IRT</ref>, <ref corresp="http://sicily.classics.ox.ac.uk/">I.Sicily</ref>, <ref corresp="http://laststatues.classics.ox.ac.uk/">LSA</ref>, <ref corresp="http://mizar.unive.it/mqdq/public/">MQDQ</ref>, <ref corresp="https://epigraphy.packhum.org/">PHI</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.trismegistos.org/">Trismegistos</ref>, <ref corresp="https://www.ubi-erat-lupa.org/">Ubi Erat Lupa</ref>).
                        L’inclusione di link alle risorse del database PPRET Inscriptions resources in altre risorse online in open access è vivamente incoraggiata.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
